Welcome to Section 9 a real time web apps with socket I O.
In this section you're going to learn about socket IO and web sockets which enable two way communication
between the server and the client.
This means that we're not only going to be setting up a node server We're also going to be setting up
a client this client could be a web app it could be an iPhone app or an Android app for this course.
The client will be a web application.
This means that we're going to be connecting the two allowing data to flow seamlessly from either the
browser to the server or from the server to the browser.
Now with our to do app data can only flow in one direction the client had to initialize the request
with socket I O.
We're going to be able to send data back and forth instantly.
This means that for real time apps like an email app a food ordering app or a chat app the server doesn't
need to wait for the client to request information the server can say hey I just got something you probably
want to show the user.
So here it is.
This is going to open up a world of possibilities and we're going to get started by figuring out how
to integrate SOC and I go into a node app.
That's exactly what we're going to get started.
So let's dive in.