In this video you're going to start.
Part 1 of a two part series on geo location.
Instead of just sending text back and forth we're also going to set it up so I can beam my actual coordinates
my long tuning latitude to everyone else connected to the chat app.
Then we can render a link and that link could go wherever we like in our case.
We're going to set it up to pull up a Google Maps page where the actual location of the user who set
their location is marked.
Now to actually fetch a user's location or we're going to use the geo location API which is available
in your client side javascript and it's actually a pretty well supported API.
It's available on all modern browsers whether that's mobile or desktop.
And the documentation can be found by googling geo location API and looking for the NTN documentation
page the MDA docs or the Mozilla Developer Network.
They are my favorite docs for clients that technologies things like your web API is your CSSA and your
HMO guidelines.
And as I mentioned this is a well-supported feature.
You can pretty much use it everywhere except for older versions of Internet Explorer and the Opera Mini
browser but all your major desktop and mobile browsers are going to support this.
And if the browser is old we will set up a little message to let them know their browser does not support
geo location.
If you ever want to learn more about geolocation or explore features that we do not cover in the next
two videos you can refer to this page though we will be using most of the features geo location has
to offer to get started.
What we're going to do is add a new button to our application.
It's going to sit alongside of sand and it's going to say something like send location when the user
clicks that send location button.
We're going to use the geolocation API and usually this is going to require the user to confirm they
want to share their location with this tab in the browser that pop up box is going to happen.
It's going to be triggered by the browser there's no way around that you're going to need to make sure
the user actually wants to share their location.
Once you have the coordinates you're going to an event that's going to go to the server the server is
going to send it to all the other connected users.
And we're going to be able to render that information in a nice link.
Now we're going to get started in this video and we'll wrap up the feature in the next one.
To kick things off.
We're going to add that button.
This is going to be the button that starts the entire process over inside of atom inside of index.
AML.
We're going to add a button just below our form tag.
It's going to be outside of our existing form right here.
We're going to add the button tag and we're going to go ahead and give this an I.D. of send location.
Now as for the visible button text we can go ahead and use send location as our string saved the file.
And if we go ahead and refresh our app in the browser we should now see we have our second location
button showing up just below.
We're going to fix all this later when we add the default styles.
But for now this does get the job done.
Now clicking this button currently is not going to do anything.
It's not tied to a form so it's not going to do any weird form submissions or page reloads.
All we need to do is add a click listener to this button and we'll be able to run whatever code we like.
In our case we're going to run that geolocation code.
This is going to happen over inside of atom inside of index dot J.S..
We're going to add some code down near the bottom.
Now the first thing I want to do is create a variable and I'm going to call this variable location button.
And this is going to store our selector.
This is the J query selector that targets the button we just created because we're going to need to
reference it multiple times and storing it in a variable.
Saves the need to make those calls again right here we're going to call a query like we've done for
other selectors passing in one argument a string and we're selecting something by ID which means we
got to start with that pound sign.
And the actual ID is send hyphen location send hyphen location right here.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and do whatever we like in our case what we're going
to be doing is adding a click event.
We want to do something when someone clicks that button to get that done.
We're going to go to location button dot on now this is identical to doing the following.
Jay query selecting the ID central location both of these are going to do the same thing.
The benefit of the first solution is that we have a reusable variable which we are going to reference
later on making to Jay query calls to the same selector.
It wastes time because it is going to require J query to manipulate the DOM fetching that information
and that's expensive.
Location button on is going to be our event listener.
We're listening for the Click event inside of quotes for the first argument and the second argument
as always is going to be our function.
This function is going to get called when someone clicks the button.
For now all we're going to do is check if the user has access to that geolocation API.
If they don't we want to go ahead and print a message.
We're going to create an if statement.
The geolocation API exists on Navigator dot geolocation and we want to run some code if it doesn't exist.
So we're going to flip it if there is no geo location object on a navigator.
We want to do something we're going to use return to prevent the rest of the function from executing
and we're going to call the alert function available in all browsers that pops up one of those default
alert boxes that makes you click OK.
We're going to use this as opposed to a fancy or motile if you are using something like bootstrap or
foundation.
You can implement one of their built in tools.
For now though we're going to use alert which takes just one argument a string.
Your message geolocation not supported by your browser.
Awesome.
And now users who don't have support for this are gonna see a little message as opposed to wondering
whether or not anything actually happened to actually fetcher users position.
We're going to use a function available on geolocation to access it.
It's navigator dot geo location dot get current position.
You get current position is a function that starts the process.
It's going to actively get the coordinates for the user.
In this case it's going to find the coordinates based off of the browser.
And this takes two functions.
The first one is your success function.
Right here we can at our first callback.
This is going to get called within the location information.
We're going to name this argument position.
The second argument to get current position is going to be our air handler if something goes wrong.
We're going to create a function right here and we'll be learning a message to the user when we're not
able to fetch the location using alert.
Let's go ahead and call alert a second time.
Printing a message like unable to fetch location.
This is going to print.
If someone gets prompted to share their location with the browser but they click deny we're going to
say hey we can't fetch the location if you don't give us that permission.
Now the only case left is the success case.
This is where we're going to admit the event.
But before we do let's go ahead and simply logon to the screen so we can take a peek at what is happening
inside of the position argument.
I'm going to log this to the screen.
Our server is going to restart and over inside of Google Chrome we can open up the developer tools refresh
the page and we can click that send location button.
Now this is going to work on desktop and mobile.
Some mobile browsers are going to require you to be on HTP ass which is something that we're going to
have set up for Heroku as you know the Heroku you are out is secure which means it's not going to work
on localhost.
You can always test your mobile browsers by deploying the app to Heroku and running there.
For now though I will be able to click send a location.
This is going to go ahead and start that process.
The process can take up to a second.
Now as you can see I did get my geo location position but I was ever prompted as to whether or not I
wanted to share my location.
That's because I've already given it permission over here I can go ahead and click click these settings
for future visits.
This means that I'm going to need to reauthorize if I refreshed the page and click send location again.
You're going to see this little box which is probably going to show up for you.
You can either block it.
If I block it it's going to print unable to fetch location.
Or you can accept it.
I'm going to clear those settings one more time give the page a refresh.
And this time I am going to accept the location sharing and we're going to get the geo location printing
out in the con..
Now once we get it we can go ahead and dive in the object itself is pretty simple.
We have a time stamp of exactly when we fetch the data.
This is useful if you're tracking a user over time which we're not doing.
We also have our coordinates.
We have all sorts of properties we're not going to use like accuracy altitude which doesn't exist.
And other related ones we also have speed which is knowl.
The only tool we're ever going to use off this object is latitude and longitude which do indeed exist.
This is the information we want to pass to the server to the server can send it to everybody else.
This means we're going to go into the position object go into the records object and grab those two.
Let's go ahead and do that over inside of Adam.
We are going to call socket dot emit and we're going to emit a brand new event.
One we do not have registered yet.
We're going to call this one create a location message create a location message is not going to take
the standard text.
Instead it's going to take those long tattoo'd and latitude coordinates.
We're going to specify both of them starting with latitude.
We want to set latitude equal to position dot cords dot latitude.
This is the variable that we explored over inside of the council and we're going to do the same thing
for a long itude study an equal to position dot cord's dot latitude awesome now that we have this in
place we can actually go ahead and listen for this event over in the server and when we get it all we're
going to do is pass this data along to all the connected users.
Let's go ahead and do just that.
Over inside of server J s registering a new event listener I'm going to remove the old commented out
broadcast call that's no longer needed in create message and just below create message.
We're going to call socket dot on again specifying a listener for this event.
Create a location message just as we defined it over inside of index.
J.S. now we are using iOS 6 since we're in node which means we can go ahead and set up our arrow function.
We're going to have one argument this is going to be chord's and we can go ahead and finish off the
arrow function in here.
We're going to be able to run whatever code we like for the moment.
All we're going to do is emit a new message event passing along the coordinates.
Although in part two we'll be making this a lot nicer setting up that you are out for Google Maps.
Right now though we're going to call Oakshott emit.
We're going to emit a new message event and we're going to go ahead and provide the necessary data by
calling generate message.
For the moment generate message is going to take some bogus user name.
I'm going to go ahead and type in admin and we are going to set the text for now we're simply going
to set it equal to the coordinates.
Let's go ahead and use a template string to set that up.
We're going to first inject the latitude which is available on cord's dot latitude then we're going
to go ahead and add a comma a space and we'll inject the long itude chords dot long into.
Excellent.
Now that we have this call in place the location information is going to get passed back and forth between
the users and we can go ahead and actually prove this over inside of the browser.
I'm going to give this page a refresh and I'm also going to open up a second tab.
In the second tab I'm going to click send location.
It's not going to prompt me if I want to share my location since I've already told it.
I do want to share my location with this tab and right here you can see we have our admen message and
we have our latitude.
But unfortunately the long itude is undefined most likely because we typed it incorrectly somewhere
along the way.
I'm going to head back into Adam real quick and take a peek.
And right here you can see I forgot the end in long itude.
If I go ahead and add that and save the file and go back into the browser we should be able to do this
once again getting both pieces of information.
I'm going to refresh both tabs to load the latest version of our index file over inside of the first
one we're going to send the location and the second one is going to be responsible for receiving it.
Let's send the location off.
Remember this takes about a second for your browser to get the coordinates and then it emits the message
and right here you see we have the coordinates both the long itude and the latitude.
We also have it over inside of the second tab.
If I take this information we can actually Google it and prove that it is working as expected.
Now in the next video part two we're going to be setting up a nice link so this information isn't visible.
It'll be there but the user doesn't really need to know the coordinates what they really want is a link
to a map.
That's what we're going to set up.
But for now we can put this in Google.
Google is going to show us exactly where it is and the coordinates are indeed correct.
I am in Philadelphia filming this video which means the location was correctly fetched for these local
host tabs.
With this in place we are now done Part 1.
We're not going to go ahead and actually make a commit since we're not done with the feature.
We're simply going to leave things as they are and move on to part two.
Let's take just a quick moment to recap what we did because we covered quite a bit of new information
here.
Now the first thing we did is we gave a new button to the user this new button is going to allow them
to click it to send the location.
All of the heavy lifting happened over inside of index.
J.S. in here.
We set up a click listener for that send location button which means every time a user clicks it we
do something.
Now what do we do.
Well first we make sure they have access to the geolocation API.
If they do that's great.
If not we simply print a message.
If they do have access we go ahead and try to fetch the location.
This can either succeed or fail if it fails.
Once again we just give them a little message.
If it succeeds we actually emit an event with the long tattoo'd and latitude to the server the server
gets that information and it emits a new message of that to all clients and that renders it to the screen.
It is as good of a place as any to stop.
We are going to continue on in the next video.
Wrapping up the geo location API in part to stay tuned I'll see you then.