In this video you're going to wrap up the two part series on geo location in the last one we got the
data flowing and in this one we're going to make a little more useful instead of rendering latitude
and longitude information as text.
Instead what we're going to do is render a clickable link a user will be able to click that link when
they receive the location from someone else.
It's going to bring him over to Google Maps and they'll be able to view exactly where the other user
is.
This is going to be much more useful than spitting out these text.
Latitude and longitude.
Now in order to get that done we are going to need to tweak how we transmit this data the way we send
the data is still fine over inside of index Dot.
Yes we're still going to emit create location message but inside of server instead of emitting a new
message we need to emit something else entirely.
We're going to set up a new event called new location message.
We're going to emit that.
And then over inside of index dot J S will write a handler for new location message similar to new message
but distinctly different.
And instead of rendering some text it's going to help us render a link.
Now in order to get started before we can do any of this we have to figure out exactly what sort of
view or else structure we're going to use to get that data.
The latitude and longitude information showing up correctly in Google Maps and there's actually a pretty
uniform way to set up the R L which is going to make this really easy to show you exactly what you are
and we're going to be using Let's go ahead and open up a new tab.
D u r l is going to go to h TTP s colon forward slash forward slash w w w dot Google dot com forward
slash maps.
Now from here we are going to be providing a query parameter and the query parameter will be specifying
is called Q And it expects the latitude and longitude to be the value separated by a comma.
Now we actually have that here although there is a little space between the comma and the minus sign.
Either way we can copy this value head back over into the other tab.
Paste it in and just remove the space.
With this in place we now have a u r l that we can use inside of our application.
Now when I hit Enter we are going to view a map at the correct location.
But you'll notice that you are l changes that's perfectly fine as long as we send the user to this you
R-AL it doesn't really matter what it ends up becoming.
I'm going to hit enter.
You can see right away we are getting a Google map.
And as the page loads the U R L is indeed going to change.
Now we're looking at something completely different from what we typed in.
But the actual pin this red pin it is correct within a couple of houses.
I won't tell you my exact address but it is pretty close to accurate.
Now with that knowledge we can generate a u r l that follows that same format.
Spit that out inside of the Web site and we'll have that clickable link where someone can view the location
of someone else.
To get started.
Let's go ahead and move into Adam into server J.S. and instead of emitting a new message event we're
going to emit new location message.
Now we don't have a handler for that over an index.
Yes but that's perfectly fine.
We'll set that up in just a minute.
Now we are going to need to change the data we send across to Currently we're sending the plain text
data but we want to do is generate a you R-AL we're actually going to create a completely separate function
for generating a location message and we'll call it generate location message.
Now this function is going to take some arguments to generate that data just like we have for the generate
message function we're going to start with the from name.
Then we're going to move on to the data specific to this function that's going to be the latitude and
longitude.
I'm going to remove our template string and we're going to pass in the raw values.
The first value will be cord's dot latitude and the second one will be chord's dot longitude.
Now it's the second coordinate value but it is indeed the third argument with this argument's list set
up we can actually go ahead and define generate location.
We'll be able to export it required in this file and then everything is going to work as expected.
Let's go ahead and load it in.
Up top before we actually add it to the message file right here we load and generate message along alongside
of that.
We're going to load in generate location message.
Excellent.
Let's save server J.S. and move into our message file.
Now the function that we're about to create is going to look really similar to that.
We're going to take some data in we're going to return an object.
The big difference is that we'll be generating that you r l as well instead of from text and created
at we're going to have from you Arel and created that right here.
We can make a variable we can call this variable generate location message and we can go ahead and set
it equal to a function that takes those three arguments from latitude and longitude awesome now we can
finish off the arrow function.
Adding the arrow and our curly braces and inside of here we can get started by returning the empty object.
Now we're going to set up those three properties from the U R L property and created at firms going
to be easy just like we do for generate message we're simply going to reference the argument that you
are one is going to be a little trickier.
For now we'll set that equal to an empty template string.
We'll come back to it in a moment and finally created and created out.
We've done that before.
We're going to set it equal to a time stamp by getting a new date and calling get.
Time now for that you are out.
We're going to need to use that exact same format that we just typed into the browser.
HTP Yes Colon forward slash forward slash w w w Google dot com forward slash maps.
Then we got to set up our query parameter adding a question mark and our Q Param setting it equal to
the latitude followed by a comma followed by the longitude.
Right here we're going to inject the latitude then we're going to add a comma and then we're going to
inject the longitude awesome.
Now we're done.
Generate location message is going to work as expected although you will be writing a test case a little
later on.
For now we can simply export it.
I'm going to export generate location message.
Awesome.
Now the data is going to flow from the client by calling emit passing and generate location message.
We're going to get the latitude and longitude over inside of the server.
We are then going to emit the new location message event with the object that we just defined over inside
of generate location message.
The last piece to the puzzle to really get all this working is to add an event listener for the new
location message event.
Right here we can call socket dom on to do just that.
We're going to pass in our two arguments.
First up is the event name we want to listen for new location message and the second and final argument
is our function.
This is going to get called with the message information.
Once the event occurs.
Now that we have this we can go ahead and start generating the down elements that we want to spit out
to the user.
And just like we did above we're going to make a list item and we're going to add our anchor tag our
link inside of it and we'll be replacing this method completely in a few videos.
But for now it's a simple way to get started.
We're going to make a variable called a list item and we're going to make a new element using Jey query
as that first argument.
We're going to pass in our string and we are going to go ahead and set it equal to the list item just
like we did above.
Next up we can go ahead and create the second element.
We're going to need.
I'm going to make a variable.
We're going to call this variable a for the anchor tag and we're going to set it equal to the return
revalue once again to a call to J query and this time around we're going to create the anchor tag.
Now the anchor tag uses the a tag just like this and the contents inside of the tag that's the link
text.
In our case we're going to go with my current location.
Now we are going to be specifying one attribute on the anchor tag.
This is going to be a non dynamic attribute meaning it's not going to come from the message object.
This one is going to be called Target and we're going to set target equal to inside of quotes underscore
blank.
When you said Target equal to blank it tells the browser to open up to you R-AL any new tab as opposed
to redirecting the current tab.
If we redirected the current tab I'd get kicked out of the chat room if I clicked one of the links with
the target set to blank will simply open up a new tab to view the Google Maps information.
Next up we're going to go ahead and set some properties on these attributes.
We're going to set the text using ally dot text.
This is going to let us set the person's name as well as that colon right inside of template strings.
We are going to inject the value message dot from after that value we're going to add a colon and a
space.
Next up we're going to go ahead and update our anchor tag.
A dot TTR you can set and fetch attributes on your Jey queries selected elements.
Using this method if you provide one argument like Target it fetches the value in which case it would
return the string underscore blank.
If you specify two arguments it actually sets the value.
Here we can set the H ref value equal to r u r l which we have under message dot.
You r l.
Now you'll notice for all of these dynamic values and not simply adding them in template strings up
above.
Instead I'm using these safe methods like Ally text and a dom attribute.
This prevents any malicious behavior if someone tries to inject h TNL they shouldn't be injecting.
Using this code with this in place we can now go ahead and append the anchor tag to the end of the list
item which is going to add it after the text.
We just set using ally Datti penned and we're going to append the anchor tag.
And now we can go ahead and not all of this to the Dom and using the exact same statement we used above.
I'm going to copy and paste it down below.
It's fine that we pasted this line.
For the moment we'll be tweaking both of these functions later to use a different system for rendering
anyways.
But with this in place we are done.
Now I'm going to save indexed.
Yes and restart things over in the browser.
We made quite a few changes so it's all right if you had a few typos for the second first or third time
as long as you're able to track them down it's no big deal.
I'm going to refresh both of my tabs over inside of chrome.
This is going to get the new connections up and running using the latest client side code.
And to kick things off I'm going to send a simple message from the second tab to the first tab that
showing up here in the second tab.
And if I go over to the first tab we see user test right here.
Now I can click send location.
This is going to take about one to three seconds to actually get the location.
Then it's going to go through the socket IO chain and what do we get.
We get the link.
My current location showing up for user 1 and 4 user 2.
Now if I click that link it should open up a brand new tab with the proper You are al the latitude and
longitude information rendered in it.
And what do I get I get just that right here we have the location for the user who clicked that send
location button.
With this in place we have a fantastic geolocation feature.
All you do is click the button it fetches your current location no matter where you are and it renders
a clickable link so anyone else can view it inside of Google Maps.
Now before we go I would like you to add a single test case for that brand new generate location message
function over inside of the terminal I can shut down the server and use clear to clear the output.
And if I run our test suite using NPM test we see that we have our one test and it's passing.
Your job is going to be to add a second over inside of message.
Test Dhananjay Yes.
We'll get started together.
Right here we're going to add it describe block we're going to describe the following function generate
a location message and you're going to be responsible for adding a test case inside of the callback
in here.
You're going to call it.
It should generate correct location object.
Next up we can go ahead and add our function.
This is going to be a synchronous task.
So there is no need to add the Done argument.
And your job is going to be to write a test case pretty similar to this one although instead of passing
in Frome and taxed you're going to pass in from latitude and longitude then you're going to make some
assertions about the values you get back.
Make sure the from property is correct make sure created at is a number and make sure the u r l property
is what you'd expect given the input.
If I input a latitude and longitude of 1 I would expect to see that you are out like this where the
latitude is replaced by the number 1 and the longitude excuse me the longitude is replaced by the number
1 and then the latitude as well.
This would be the value that I would expect over inside the test case given an input of 1 and 1.
Now your job is going to be to write that test case then run it and make sure everything passes over
inside of the terminal.
Take a moment to knock that out.
When you're done.
Test it.
Then click play.
All right.
Hopefully you didn't have too much trouble with that to get started.
I'm going to make a few variables.
I'm going to make a from variable and I'll set that equal to something like.
Deb then we can go ahead and create a latitude variable.
I'm going to set that equal to 15 and we can go ahead and create a variable longitude set of that equal
do something like 19.
And then I can go ahead and finally create a u r l variable that u r l variable is going to be the final
result of the U r al.
I would expect to get back now that you are always going to be inside of quotes H Yes yes Colin forward
slash forward slash w w w dot Google dot com forward slash maps.
Then we're going to add the appropriate query parameter.
Given the information we're going to pass in at the latitudes 15 we would expect 15 after the equal
sign and if the longitude is 19 after the comma we would expect 19.
Now that we have that in place we can actually go ahead and call our function.
Storing the response I'm going to make a variable called message then we're going to go ahead and call
generate location message which currently isn't required we can do that in just a second and we're going
to pass in our three arguments from latitude and longitude.
Excellent.
Now let's go ahead and also pull off generate location message right here.
Generate location.
Message.
Excellent.
Now the only thing left to do is make our assertions.
We're going to start in much the same way I'm actually going to copy these two lines down below.
We're expecting the message doc created at property to be a number which it should be then and down
below.
We're expecting message to include a from property equal to Deb..
And we're going to expect it to have a u r l property equal to the U R L string we define above.
If both of these assertions pass them we know the object returned from generate location message is
correct.
I'm going to rerun the test suite over inside of the terminal.
And what do we get.
We get a failing test here we're expecting that some object with created at from and you are l equals
some other object.
Now as you can see there's a discrepancy here.
The Q was left off and the u r l right here over inside of our test case.
All I need to do is fix that.
Save it.
Rerun the test suite and this time everything should work as expected.
These error messages are super useful.
It can take a little bit of time to dig into the details.
You have three properties and you have those three properties twice.
So it can take some time to figure out where you went wrong.
But in this case I clearly went wrong inside of my assertion and a test case is only as good as the
assertions you have in place and that's it.
For this why don't we have geo location all set up.
We have our link rendered.
We are in great shape to continue on.
I'm going to go ahead and add a commit over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to run the clear command to clear the terminal output then we'll run get status to see all
of our changed files and we can use a get commit with the flag to add a message for this one.
Add geo location support via geo location API.
Awesome.
I'm going to go ahead and commit this and push it up to get hub and we can also take a quick moment
to deploy this to Heroku as well.
You can get push Heroku.
This is going to deploy our latest code which has geo location stuff built in and we'll be able to run
this and this code is going to run on things like the chrome mobile browser because we'll be in HTP
s Google Chrome's browser on mobile and other mobile browsers have pretty strict security guidelines
as to when they'll send geolocation information.
It is going to need to be over.
HTP connection which is exactly what we have here.
I'm going to open up our Heroku app in a few tabs will open it up here and will also open it up in a
second tab.
I'm going to click that send the location button.
I do need to approve this and say different.
You are Al.
Yes I do want them to be able to use my location.
It's going to grab the location send it off.
And the first tab gets the link.
Click the link and hopefully it get the same spot.
And we do.
That's it for this one.
I will see you next time.