In this video you're finally going to get some styles in place.
So our app looks a little less like an ANS tiled h DML page and a little more like a real web app.
Now on the left we have this people panel we're not going to be wiring that up yet although we are giving
it a place inside of our page.
Eventually this is going to store a list of all the people connected to the individual chat room that's
going to come a bit later over here the main area is going to be the messages panel.
Now the individual messages are still on styled.
That's going to come later.
But we do have a place to put all of that stuff Dambulla we have our footer This includes our form for
sending a message the text box and the button.
And that also includes our send location button sitting right here.
Now to get all of this done we're going to add a CSSA template that I've created for this project.
We're also going to be adding some classes to our HDMI.
All this is going to let us apply the various styles.
And finally we'll be making a few small tweaks to our javascript to improve the user experience.
Let's go ahead and Diven the first thing we're going to do is make a new folder and a new file to store
our styles.
This is going to be the template styles will be grabbing in just a moment.
Then we're going to go ahead and load it into index dot HD.
So those styles are used when we render the chat app.
Now the first thing we're going to do is create a new folder inside of public and we're going to call
this folder CSSA and we're going to add just one file to it.
A new file called styles dot C Ss.
Now before we go off and grab any styles Let's go ahead and import this file into our application.
And in order to test and make sure that's working what we're going to do is write a very simple selector.
We're going to select everything using the star than inside of curly braces we're going to add a style
setting the color for everything equal to red.
Go ahead and make your file just like this one.
We're going to save that and then we'll import it over inside of index dot each time M.
Right here at the bottom of the head tag below are met a tag we're going to add a link tag.
This is going to let us link a style sheet we have to provide two attributes to get that done.
First off we have to tell HVM exactly what we're linking to by specifying the RTL or relation attribute.
In this case we're trying to link a stylesheet.
So we're going to provide that as the value.
Now the next thing we need to do is provide the ref attribute.
This is similar to the source attribute for the script tag.
It's the path to the file you want to link.
In this case we have that at forward slash CSSA and we just created the file styles.
Success forward slash styles.
Dot C-s that's with this in place we can save index dot h TNL and give our page a refresh over inside
of the browser or load it up for the very first time.
And what we see is a hideously ugly page.
We've managed to make it even uglier than it was previously but this is great because it means our stylesheet
file is getting imported correctly now in order to grab the actual template.
We're going to be using for the chat app.
We're going to visit a u r l h t t p colon forward slash forward slash length's dot Meade dot IO my
site forward slash chat hyphen CSSA.
This is just a bit like length that's going to redirect you over to a jest.
And here we have two options we can grab either the minute style template or the.
UNIDENTIFIED one I'm gonna go ahead and grab this minute one by either highlighting it or clicking this
raw link which brings us to the file.
We're going to grab the entire contents we see here.
Head over into Adam and paste it inside of our CSSA file.
Removing obviously the previous selector.
Perfect.
Now that we had this in place we can give our page a refresh although we're not really going to see
much improvement over inside of localhost 3000.
I'll give the browser a refresh and clearly things are different but it doesn't look anything like that
screen shot we had in the beginning of this video.
That is because we need to apply some classes to our DML in order to get everything to work correctly.
We're also going to need to tweak the structure adding a few container elements to help with alignment
over inside out and we can get this done in just a few minutes.
This template was built around a few key classes the first one needs to get applied to the body by setting
the class attribute equal to inside of quotes chat.
This tells the style sheet to load the styles for this chat page and we're going to go ahead and remove.
Welcome to the chat app.
This is no longer necessary.
Now the next thing we're going to do is create a div and this div is going to house that people list
we saw on the left hand side.
It's going to be empty for the moment but that's fine.
We can still go ahead and create it right here.
We're going to make a div
and we're going to give this div a class and that class is going to get set equal to the following chat
underscore underscore that's two underscores side bar.
This is a naming convention used in some style sheet templates.
It's really a matter of preference.
You could call this whatever you want when you create the style sheet.
I happen to call it chat underscore underscore sidebar.
It's a sub element inside of the greater chat app.
Now inside of here we're going to add a little title using the header three tag we're going to give
this a title of people or whatever you want to call that side bar list.
And we're also going to provide a div which will eventually house the individual users although as I
mentioned we're not going to be wiring that up yet.
Now we can go ahead and give this an I.D. setting it equal to users so we can target it a bit later.
And that's all we need for the chat sidebar at the moment.
Now the next thing that we're going to do is create a div and that this debt is going to house that
main area which means it's going to contain not only our chat messages but also the little form at the
bottom everything on the right hand side of the sidewalk.
This also is going to require a custom class for some styles.
This one is called Chat underscore underscore Maine and inside of here we're going to add not only are
unordered lists but also our form and button.
Let's go ahead and take all of our current markup the unordered list down to the send location button.
Cut it out and paste it inside of chat main.
Now we're not quite done yet.
There are a few more things to tweak.
First up we have to add a class to our ordered list.
We'll set the class equal to chat messages.
This is going to provide the necessary styles and the last div we need to create is going to be for
that FOTR.
This is going to be the gray bar at the bottom that contains both your form as well as the send location
button.
We're going to make a div which is going to help with alignment.
And we're going to add the form and the button inside of it by kind of get out and pasting it right
in here.
Now we are going to need to add a class here too as you might have guessed setting the class attribute
equal to the string.
Chat underscore underscore footer.
Now we have all of our classes in place and we can head over to the browser and see what we get when
we give the page a refresh what we get is something a little similar to what we had previously.
But obviously there are some notable differences.
The footer is not quite rendering correctly.
If we head back over into ADOM we can take a look at just why right here we have a div this div has
a class of chapt footer but class was spelt wrong.
All I have to do is go ahead and fix that typo.
Give the browser a refreshed one more time.
And now we're getting the complete picture.
We have our styled chat application and we can still do whatever we were able to do before I can send
off a message hey this should still work.
Hit enter.
And hey this should still work shows up to the screen.
The same thing is true for send location.
I can send off my location is going to send it to the server.
It's going to send it to all the clients and right here I can click the my current location link and
the location is going to show up inside of Google Maps.
We've maintained all of the old functionality well adding a nice set of styles.
Now for the second half of this video I want to make some user experience improvements to the form down
below what improvement we're going to make as wiping the text value once a message was successfully
sent.
We're also going to do something similar with send location as you might have noticed it can take up
to a second or two for the send location geo location called to actually complete.
We're going to set this button to be disabled so someone doesn't span it.
Wondering what's happened.
We're also going to update the text to say sending location so someone knows that something is happening
in the background.
Now in order to get those things done all we need to do is modify a few lines over inside of index dot.
J.S. near the bottom of the file we have our two.
Jay queery event listeners both of these are going to get changed.
Now the first thing we're going to change is going to be the form submit listener.
Right here we fetch the value from the field and that's what we pass along what we want to do down below
inside of the acknowledgement callback is clear the value once the request has been received by the
server there's no reason to keep it around.
So what we can do is add the same J Aquarius selector which will break out in just a moment.
Targeting the field worthy name attribute equals message and we're going to go ahead and clear its value
by calling Val once again.
But instead of getting a value by providing no arguments like we do here we're going to set the value
to an empty string by passing in an empty string as the first argument.
You could set the value to anything you like but in this case we just want to clear it.
So we're going to use the following method call.
Now we have the same selector twice to speed things up.
We're going to make a variable we'll call that variable message text box and then we can go ahead and
set it equal to the selector we just created down below.
And now we can refer to message text box any anywhere we need access to that input.
Right here we can reference it message text box and down below message text box.
Awesome.
Now the listener for create message which is over inside of server.
J.S. sits right here and we do indeed call the call back with a string.
For now we're going to just remove that bogus value passing zero arguments.
This means that the acknowledgement function will still get called over here but we don't actually need
any data.
We just need to know when the server responded.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and refresh things over inside of local host 3000 type
a message.
Here is a message and hit the enter key and what do we get.
We get the value cleared and was indeed sent.
The same thing is going to hold true if I type in a message and click the send button.
Now one thing we're going to do real quick is update the input tag for this text box.
If I refresh the page we're currently not brought right into the message feel that would be really nice
to do that would also be really nice to turn off auto complete as you can see auto complete isn't really
a useful feature.
It's hidden down below and the values inside of it are usually trash.
So what we're going to do over inside of Adam is add two attributes to customize the input.
The first one is going to be auto focus which doesn't require a value.
Autofocus is going to auto focus on this input when the template gets rendered and the second one we're
going to add is auto complete and we're going to set that equal to the string off.
With this in place we can save index dot HD and now head back over to Chrome refresh the page and test
things out.
I'm going to type in test right here.
I have no auto complete which is good.
We turned that off and if I clicked the send button I am indeed still sending the message.
I was also brought right into the text box when I reloaded the page.
I didn't need to do anything in order to start typing perfect.
The next thing we're going to do is customize that send location by using a bit more Jay query.
Now we're new to Jay Aquarians isn't really a jay queery course.
You can feel free to try to treat some of these as challenges though I won't be giving you many Jay
query related challenges.
We're going to stick to the challenges that require you to do some node code.
The goal here is to change the button text and disable it while the process is occurring.
When the process is complete meaning that the location was either sent or not sent we can return them
back into its normal state.
But well the geolocation call is happening.
We don't want someone spamming away to get that done.
We're gonna make some tweaks to the final on listener we have inside of index dot J s just below our
on submit listener We have our on click listener here.
We're going to need to make some changes to the button the location button variable we have defined
right here.
We're going to set an attribute that's going to disable the button to get that done.
We will reference the selector up above location button and we're going to call Jay Querrey method.
Now we're only going to disable it after we've confirmed that even have support for it.
If they don't have support for the feature there's no reason to go ahead and disable it right here location
button.
TR is going to let us set an attribute.
We're going to set the disabled attribute equal to the value disabled.
Now this disabled needs to be in quotes as well just like this.
Now that we have disabled the button we could actually test this out.
We never undecidable it so it's going to be broken after clicking at once.
But we can confirm that this line works over in the browser.
I'm going to give things a refresh click send location and you can see right away that the button does
get disabled.
Now it is going to send off location once but if I try to click it again the buttons disabled and it's
never going to refire the click event.
The goal here is to only disable it.
Well the process is actually occurring once it's sent like it is here.
We want to re-enable it so someone can send an updated location to get that done over inside of Adam.
We're going to add a line of Jay queery into both the success handler and the error handler.
If things go well we're going to reference location button and we're going to remove the disabled attribute
by using remove a TTR.
And this takes just one argument in the name of the attribute.
In this case we have that it's a string disabled.
This is going to remove the disabled attribute we defined above re-enabling the button and we can do
the exact same thing literally copying and pasting the line down below.
If for some reason we're not able to fetch that location maybe the user denied the request for geo location.
We still want to disable that button so they can try again.
Now that we have this set up we can test out that code by refreshing the browser and trying to send
off our location.
We should see the buttons disabled for a little bit and then it gets re-enabled.
There we go.
It's disabled.
It's about one to three seconds.
And there we go.
The location has been processed.
We can click it to prove that it is working as expected.
And the button was re-enabled which means we can go ahead and click it at a later time sending our location
once again.
Now the last thing we're going to do is update the button text.
Well the process is occurring to get that done over inside of Adam.
We're going to use that text method that we've used in the past right here.
We're going to set the text equal to my calling text sending location dot dot dot.
Now the real button text is send a location with a capital L..
I'm going to go ahead and lowercase that to keep things uniform.
Awesome.
Now that we have this set up we are updating the text while the process occurs.
The only thing left to do is tweak it back to its original value down below by setting text equal to
the string send location here and we're going to do the exact same thing down below calling text passing
in the string send location.
Excellent.
Now we can go ahead and test that this is working as expected.
Both of these lines are identical regardless of whether it succeeds or fails.
We're going to do the same thing over inside of chrome.
Going to give my page a refresh one more time.
We're going to click that send location button and you can see the button is disabled and the text was
changed sending location shows up and as soon as the process is complete and the location was actually
sent the button returns to its default state.
With this in place we now have a much nicer user experience than we had previously had only do we have
a nice set of styles.
We also have a better UI for our form and the send location button.
That is where we are going to stop for this one.
Let's go ahead and make a quick commit by shutting down the server running get status running get add
to add all of those files.
And finally we're going to go ahead and run get commit with the flag providing a message and see SS
for chat page.
We can go ahead and push this up to get how then I'm going to avoid deploying for Heroku right now although
you are welcome to deploy and test your application live.
And that is it for this one.
I will see you next time.