Throughout the course we have used time stamps quite a bit.
We've generated them in the to do app and we also have them generated for all of our messages in the
chat app but we've never gone as far as formatting them to something human readable that's going to
be the topic in this video.
And in the next one we'll put that into action.
By the end of the next video we'll have a formatted message area with the name time stamp and message
and we'll have some better styles for it as well.
Now in this one it's going to be all about time and time stamp are not going to make any changes to
the front end of our app.
We're simply going to learn how time works inside of Node.
Now to explore this we're going to create a new playground file over inside of Adam.
We're going to make a playground folder to store this file.
And inside of the playground directory we can make a new file calling it time.
J.S..
And then here we'll play around with time and we'll take what we learn here into the front end of the
application in the next video.
Now we are no strangers to time stands we know they're nothing more than just integers whether positive
or negative.
Something like 781 is a perfectly valid time stamp.
So is something like minus a couple of billion or whatever this number happens to be all valid even
0 is a perfectly valid timestamp.
Now all of these numbers they're all relative to a certain moment in history referred to as the Unix
APIC which is January 1st 1970 at midnight 0 hours 0 minutes and 0 seconds.
M This is stored in UTC which means it's time zone independent.
Now I timestamps 0 actually represents this moment in history perfectly.
And positive numbers like 1000 head into the future while negative numbers like minus a thousand head
into the past minus 1 0 0 0 0 0.
As a time stamp would represent December thirty first 1969 at eleven fifty nine and fifty nine seconds.
We've gone one second into the past from here.
Now these timestamps inside of javascript they're stored in milliseconds.
The unix epic inside of a regular UNIX timestamps they're actually stored in seconds.
So we are using javascript in this course we will always be using milliseconds as our time stamp values
which means that a time stamp like this one thousand represents one second into January 1st.
Since there's 1000 milliseconds in a second a value like 10000 would be ten seconds into this day and
so on and so forth.
Now the problem for us was never getting the time stamp getting the time stamp was really easy.
All we had to do was call new date calling get time method.
Things are going to get a lot harder though and you want to format a human readable value like the one
we have above.
We're going to want to print something to the screen inside of our web app that's not just the time
stamp we're gonna want to print something like maybe 5 minutes ago letting a user know the message was
sent five minutes ago or maybe you want to print the actual date with the month day hour minute and
am or pm value regardless of what you want to print.
We are going to need to talk a bit about formatting and this is where the default date object falls
short.
Yes there are methods that allow you to get the specific values out of a date like the year the month
or the day of month.
But they are very limited and it is a huge burden to customize something like what we have above to
talk about exactly the problem let's go ahead and pull up the documentation for date by googling MDMA
date.
This is going to bring us to the Mozilla developer network documentation page for date which is a really
great set of documentation Double-O we have access to all of the methods available.
These are all methods kind of like get time that return something specific about the date.
For example we have a get date method that returns the day of the month a value from 1 to 31.
We have something like Get minutes which returns the current minutes for the time stamp.
All of these exist inside of date.
Now the problem is that these are really on flexible.
For example inside of Adam we have this little date right here it's a shorthand version for January.
Now we can get the actual month to show you how we'll create a variable called Date.
We'll go ahead and create a new date and then we're going to go ahead and call a method on an unused
council that like to print the value to the screen and we're going to call date dot get month get month
as defined over inside of the documentation is going to return a zero based month value from 0 to 11
where 0 is January and 11 is December over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to kick off our app using gnomon since we're going to be restarting it quite a bit.
Gnomon it's in the playground folder not the server folder and the file itself is called time.
Yes.
Once it's up and running we see we get it back which is expected.
It's currently September 22nd 2016 and a zero indexed value for September would be 8.
Even though you commonly think of it as 9.
Now this is fine.
We have the number 8 but getting an actual string Jan or January is going to be much more difficult.
There is no built in way to get this value which means if you do want to get that value you're going
to have to create an array maybe you call the array months and you store all of the values like this
this is going to be fine and it might not seem like that big of a deal for a month but things get just
as confusing for the day of that month like the first we have here.
All we can really get back is the number one actually formatting it to first second or third is going
to be much more difficult.
There just are not a good set of methods for formatting your date.
Things get even more complex when you want to have a relative time string something like three minutes
ago.
It would be nice to print that inside of the web app along side of the message.
Printing the actual month the day and the year is not particularly useful.
It will be quick if we could say hey this message was sent three hours ago three minutes ago or 3 years
ago like a lot of chat applications do.
Now when you get into a formatting like this your first instinct is usually to create some utility methods
that help with formatting a date but there is no need to do that because what we're going to look at
in this video is a fantastic time library called Moment moment is pretty much the only library of its
kind.
It is universally accepted as the go to library for working with time in javascript.
I've never worked on a node or Front-End project that didn't have Moment used.
It is truly essential when you're working with dates in any capacity.
Now in order to show off why moment is so great we are going to first install it over inside of the
terminal.
Then we're going to play around with all of its capabilities.
It has a lot right here.
We can install it by running NPM.
I am going to go ahead and use the current version moment at Version 2 point fifteen point one.
And I will also use the save flag to add it as a dependency a dependency that we're going to need on
Heroku as well as locally.
Now once it's installed I can use clear to clear the terminal output and we can go ahead and restart
node Mohn over inside of the playground.
It's time to require moment and take a look at exactly what it can do for us to kick things off.
Let's go ahead and try to fix the problem we tried to solve with date.
We want to print the shorthand version of a month like Jan FEBE and so on.
The first step is going to be to comment this out in load in Moment up above requiring it.
I'm going to make a variable called Moment and require it by requiring the moment library then and down
below will kick things off by making a new moment.
Now just like we create a new date to get a specific date object we're going to do the same thing with
moment.
I'm going to call this variable date and we're going to set it equal to a call to moment.
The function we loaded in above without any arguments.
This creates a new moment object that represents the current point in time.
From here we can go ahead and try to format things using its really useful format method.
The format method is one of the main reasons I just love moment.
It makes it dead simple to print whatever you want as a string.
Now in this case we have access to our date and we're going to go ahead and call that method I just
talked about format before we get into what we pass to format.
Let's go ahead and run it just like this.
When we do that over inside of the terminal node mine is going to go ahead and restart itself.
And right here we have our formatted date we have the year the month the day and other values.
It's not still really user friendly but it is a step in the right direction.
The real power of the format method comes when you pass a string inside of it.
Now what we pass inside of here is patterns which means that we have access to a specific set of values
we can use to output certain things.
We're going to explore all of the patterns available to you in just a second.
For now let's go ahead and just use one.
It's the triple upper case and the pattern when moment sees this pattern inside a format.
It's going to go ahead and grab the shorthand version of the month which means that I save this file
restarting it over inside of the terminal.
Once again we should see the shorthand version for the current month September which would be S E P.
Right here we have Sep.
Just as expected and we were able to do that.
Super simply by using format now format returns a string that has just the things you specify.
Here we only specified that we want the shorthand version of the month.
So all we got back was the shorthand version of the month.
We could also add on another pattern for YS which prints out the full year in the current case it would
print out 2016 in numbers.
I'm going to go ahead and save time again and right here we get Sep 2016.
Now moment as a fantastic set of documentation so you can use whatever patterns you like over inside
of the browser we can pull it up by going to moment.
J.S. dotcom the documentation for a moment is fantastic.
It's available on the docs page and to get started in order to figure out how to use format we're going
to go to this display section.
The first item in display is format.
There's a few examples about how to use format but the really useful information is what we have down
below.
Here we have all of the tokens that we can put inside of the string to format our day as we like.
Up above you can see you can use as many of these tokens as you like to create a really complex date
outputs.
Now we already explored two we explored triple and which is defined right here under the month Hetter.
As you can see there are five different ways to represent the month the 4 y pattern which we used for
a year is defined down below.
There's three ways to use year.
We just explored one of them and there are sections for everything Year day of week day of month AM
PM hour minute second.
All of those are defined right here and all of them can be put inside a format just like we did for
the current values.
Now in order to explore this just a little more let's head back into Adam and take advantage of some
of these what we're going to try to do is print what we have right here the shorthand month in the year
which we already have.
But now we need the day of the month formatted like first second third as opposed to 1 to 3 in order
to do that.
What I would do if I had not used a moment before is I would look in the docs for the day of month section
which happens to be sitting right here and I look at the available options.
I have the db pattern which prints 1 through 31.
I also have D.O. and that print is what we want first second third.
So on and so forth and we also have double uppercase D which prints the number with a 0 in front of
it for the values less than 10.
Now in this case we want to use this pattern so all we have to do is type it over inside a format I
can open up the terminal and add him so we can see it refresh in the background and we're going to type
d o right here saving the file whenever he starts.
What do we get we get September 22nd 2016 which is indeed correct.
Now we can also add other characters in here like a comma.
A comma is not part of the patterns that format expects.
So it's simply going to pass it through which means right here the comma get shown just as we typed
it in September 22nd comma twenty six team using format.
In this way we have a lot of flexibility as to how we want to print the date.
Now format is just one of many methods.
There are a ton of methods on moment for doing just about anything although I find I use pretty much
the same sex and most of my projects.
There really isn't a lot of need for most of them although they do exist because they are useful in
certain situations.
To take a quick peek at some other things a moment can do.
Let's head back into the docs and go to the Manipulate section.
The first two methods defined under manipulate are add and subtract.
This lets you easily add and subtract time as you can see here.
We can call add adding 7 days and we can call subtract subtracting 7 months down below.
You can get a quick idea about what you can add and subtract years courters months weeks.
Pretty much any unit of time can be added or subtracted.
Now to take a look at what exactly that does to the time stamp.
We can go ahead and add and subtract some values right here.
I'm going to call it date dot ad and we're going to go ahead and add a year by putting one in as the
value and year in as the unit.
Now it doesn't matter if you use the single or plural version.
Both are going to work the same.
Here you can see we get 20:17 in the terminal.
If I change it to your singular I also get that same value.
You can add as many years as you like.
I'm going to go ahead and out one hundred years and now we're at 21 16.
Same thing is true with subtract we can chain on the call or we can add it as a separate statement.
I'm going to subtract 9 months just like this.
And we are currently in September and when we subtract 9 months we go back to December.
Now you notice we went from 21 16 to 21 15 because subtracting those nine months required us to change
years.
Moment is really great at handling just about anything you throw at it.
Now your challenge for this video is going to be to play around with for a little more.
I'm going to give you the output I would like and you will need to figure out which patterns to use
over inside of the documentation to get that output.
Now the current time as I'm filming this is ten thirty five on my iPhone it looks like this.
Ten thirty five and it is in the am.
So I have a lower case i am sitting right here.
Your goal is to print a format like this.
Now obviously if it's 12 or 15 when you run the code you're going to see 12 15 as opposed to 10 35.
It's just the format that matters the actual values aren't that important.
Now as you'll see when you try to print hours and minutes you're going have a lot of options for both
of them.
You're going to have a padded version like 0 1 or an unpadded version like one.
I want you to use the padded version for minutes and the unpadded version for hours which would be six
like this and 0 1 if you padded the hour it looks kind of weird.
And if you don't pad the minute it looks just terrible.
So we would want to print something like this if it happened to be 6 0 1 a.
M now for our You're also going to have the option to do either 1 to 12 or 1 to 24.
I usually use the 12 hour clock so I'm going to do that using am right here before I set you free.
I am going to comment out the code above.
I would like you to write everything from scratch just below.
So take some time create a new moment date and call format printing the value to the screen.
You should see something formatted like this.
Test it out.
And when you're done go ahead and click play hopefully you are able to find all of the necessary patterns
to print this to the screen.
To kick things off I am going to make a new date by calling moment with no arguments and we're also
going to go ahead and call format inside of console dialogue so we can print that format add value to
the screen.
Date dot format inside of here we're going to provide our pattern.
We're going to start with the unpadded hour and deep Hadad minute we can grab both of those patterns
by heading over to the doc's going back to display and taking a peek.
If we scroll down below the first one and we're going to run into an hour right here and we have quite
a few options.
We have 24 hour options we have 1 through 12.
What we want is lowercase H which is 1 through 12 unpadded the padded version which is two lowercase
aitches exists right below that is not what we want for this one right here.
We're going to take things off by adding an h.
I'm also going to save the file.
Check it out in the terminal and right here we have 10 which looks great.
Next up is that padded minute.
We're going to go ahead and find that pattern just below for a minute we have a lot fewer options either
padded or unpadded we want to use to lower case ends.
Now before I add those two m's I am going to add a colon.
This is going to get passed through in plain text meaning it's not going to get changed.
Right here we're going to add our two lowercase M's we can then save time.
Yes and make sure the correct thing prints in the terminal and does 10:38 shows up right here.
Next up is going to be grabbing that lowercase am and pm value we can find that pattern over inside
of Google Chrome just above our.
Here we can either use uppercase a for uppercase am and pm or lowercase a for the lower case version.
I'm going to go ahead and use a lower case.
After a space to use that lowercase version I can save the file and over inside of the terminal I do
indeed have 10 39 printing to the screen.
We have the AM after it.
Everything looks great.
If you completed the challenge successfully you should be seeing something just like this.
That is it for this video in the next one we're going to actually integrate moment into our server and
our client rather than just having it in a playground File.
Stay tuned.
We'll see you then.