In this video you're going to be formatting your time stamps and you're going to be displaying them
to the screen along with the chat message currently we show who it's from and the text.
But the created that time stamp is not used anywhere.
Now the first thing we need to figure out is how we can take that time stamp and get a moment object
back because in the end of the day we want to call the format method to format it as we like in order
to do that.
All you have to do is take your time stamp will make a variable called created to represent value and
pass it in as the first argument to moment which means I simply passen created that just like this.
When I do this we're creating a moment with the same methods like format add and subtract but it's representing
a different point in time.
By default it uses the current time.
If you pass in a time stamp it uses that time.
Now this number 1234 is barely a second pass the Unix epic.
But if we go out and run the file we should see the correct thing printing gnomon in the playground
folder or on time ADOT J.S. and right here we get 7 pm which would be expected census taking into account
our local time zone.
Now that we have this in place we have everything we need to actually take those time stamps and get
back formatted values.
The other thing we can do is we can create timestamps with moment.
It has the exact same effect as the new date don't get time method we've used in order to do this all
we do is we call it moment dot value of for example we can make a variable called some time stamp setting
an equal to a call to moment.
We're going to generate a new moment and we're going to call it's value of method.
This is going to go ahead and return a time stamp in milliseconds since the Unix epic console dot log
we're going to log out these some time stamp the variable just to make sure it looks correct.
And here we are we have our time stamp value with this in place we are ready to go.
The first thing we're going to do is tweak our message.
J.S. file currently inside of message dot Jap's we generate timestamps using new Date Time.
We're going to switch over to moment not because it changes anything.
I just want to be consistent with using moment everywhere we use time.
This is going to make it a lot easier to maintain and figure out what's going on right here.
I'm going to make a variable called a moment sending a vehicle to require moment and we're going to
go ahead and replace this with calls to value of what I would like you to do is go ahead and do just
that calm moment to call the value of method here and here then and go ahead and run the test suite
and make sure both tests pass when you're done.
You can go ahead and click play.
All right the first thing we need to do is tweak the created property for generate message.
We're going to call a moment just like this.
Then we're going to call value of getting back the time stamp and we're going to do the same thing down
below.
Moment dot value of awesome.
Now we can go ahead and save message Aegeus head over into the terminal and run our test suite using
NPM test.
And what do we get.
We get two tests and they're both still passing which means the value we're getting back is indeed a
number as our tests assert now that we have moment integrated on the server.
We're going to go ahead and do the same thing on the client.
Now the first thing we need to do is load in moment.
Currently the only library we load in on the front end is Jey query.
We can do this a few different ways.
I'm going to go ahead and actually grab a file out of node modules.
We've installed a moment the version right here to point fifteen point one and we can actually grab
the file we need for the front and it's sitting inside of the node modules directory.
We're going to go into node modules.
We have a really long list of alphabetical folders I'm looking for the one called Moment h i j k l m
m moment.
We're going to go into moment and we're going to grab moment dot J.
S. I'm going to Right-Click to copy it.
Then I'm going to scroll up to the very top close node modules and I'm going to paste it right inside
of our J libs directory right here.
We now have a moment.
Yes.
And if you open it it's a really really really long library file.
There's no need to make any changes to that file.
All we have to do is loaded in index.
J.S. just below our J query import.
We're going to add a brand new script tag Well then provide that source attribute setting it equal to
forward slash J.S. forward slash lives forward slash moment.
Jap's just like this.
Now that we have this in place we have access to all of those moment functions only on the client side.
Which means that over inside an index we can properly format the time stamp that comes back inside of
message.
Now before we make any changes lets go ahead and start up our server using gnomon gnomon server board
slash server.
J.S. is going to start it up.
Then we can go ahead and move into the browser going to localhost 3000 and giving it a refresh.
And our app is working as expected.
I open up the developer tools inside of the console.
We can actually use moment.
We have it accessible via a moment just like we did over inside of node I can use moment like this calling
format.
And what do we get we get back our string.
You should be able to make this call if you've successfully imported moment if you are seeing this then
you are ready to move on to the actual updating of index Dom.
J.S..
Now if you remember on a message we have a created app property for both new message and new location
message.
All we need to do is get that value passed into moment and then generate our formatted string.
I'm going to do it for new message and then you will do it as a challenge for a new location message
right here.
We can make a new variable called format at time and we can set this equal to a call to moment passing
in the time stamp message dot created at.
Now we can go ahead and do whatever we like.
We could call format like this passing in the exact same string we use over in time.com.
Yes the hour the minutes and the AM PM lowercase h colon to lower case ambs followed by a space and
a lower case a.
With this in place we now have that formatted time and we go ahead and add it inside of here.
Now I know I'm using template sharings inside of our client side code.
We'll be removing this pretty soon so there's no need to make that tweak yet since I'm not testing an
Internet Explorer or any other browser.
Although the final version of the apple not include template strings.
Right after the from statement we're going to go ahead and inject another value the formatted time which
we just created up above.
So our message should read name like outman the time followed by the text.
I'm going to go ahead and save index dot Jap's give the browser a refresh to load that client side code.
And right here we see admin 2 0 6 pm.
Welcome to the chat app and that is the correct time.
I can go ahead and send a message.
This is from a user send it off and right here we see it's now 2 or 7 pm.
This is from a user.
Shows up everything is working great now for send a location we currently don't use moment.
We only updated the new message event listener.
This means that when we print that location message we don't have the time stamp.
Your challenge for this video is going to be to get that done.
Why are you to take a quick moment to modify new location message.
You can go ahead and use the same techniques we used above to get the job done.
Now in terms of where to actually render the formatted time you can simply put it right here just like
we did earlier.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Knock that out.
Make sure the time stamp shows up when you send a location.
Then you can go ahead and click play.
All right.
Step one in the process is going to be to make that variable called formatted time.
We can actually go ahead and copy this line directly pasting it right here.
We want to do the exact same thing we want to take that created out field we want to get a moment object
and we want to call format.
Next up we do have to modify what gets displayed.
We want to show this formatted time variable and we're going to put it right here formatted time.
Excellent.
Now we can go ahead and refresh the app.
And we should see our time stamp for regular messages.
We can send off a regular message and everything still works then we can send off a location message
which we just changed it to take just a second to get going and here we are we have our current location
link.
We have our name and we have the time stamp which is fantastic.
That is it for this one let's go ahead and actually make a commit to save our changes even though we're
not quite done with the message area we have all the data correctly showing up it's just showing up
in a way that's not really pleasing to the eye.
For now though we will head into the terminal shut down the server and get status.
Here we have new files as well as some modified files get ad is going to take care of all of that.
Then we can make our commit get commit with the M flag and a good message for this one is format with
an uppercase s timestamps using moment.
Yes I am going to go ahead and push this up to get help.
And we are done.
And that's it for this one I will see you next time.