Now that we have our time stamps rendering correctly to the screen we're going to go ahead and talk
about a templating engine called Moustache Scott.
Yes.
This is going to make it much easier to define some markup and render it multiple times.
In our case our messages are going to have the same set of elements in order to render it properly.
We're going to have a better tag for the user's name.
We're going to add the text into a paragraph.
All that sort of stuff.
Now instead of doing that inside an index just like we currently are we're going to create some templates
some markup in index dot h DML and we're going to render those here which means we're not going to need
to manually create and manipulate these elements which can be a huge burden.
Now in order to get started before we actually create any templates or render them we do need to download
the library.
We can get this by going to google chrome and Googling mustache dot Yes and we're looking for the get
hub repository which in this case happens to be the first link.
You can also go to mustache dot get help.
Oh and click the javascript link to get to the same location.
Now once you're here we do want to grab a specific version of the library.
We can go to the branch drop down and switch from branches to tags.
This is going to show us all of the versions that were released the version I'm going to be using here
is the most recent one to point to point one.
I'm going to grab that.
It's going to refresh the repository code down below and we're looking for a file called Moustache dot.
J.S. This is the library file We're going to need to download and add into index.
Each team out right here I can click raw to grab the raw javascript file and I can go ahead and save
it into the project by right clicking and clicking save it as I'm going to go into the project on the
desktop.
The public J.S. libs folder and right here we're going to add the file.
Now once you have the file in place we can kick things off by importing it inside of index dot HMO
near the bottom we currently have script tags for Jay queery and the moment.
This one is going to look pretty similar.
It's going to be a script tag then we'll add that source attribute so we can load in the new file forward
slash J.S. forwards slash libs.
Finally it's forwards slash mustache dot J.
S. Now with this in place we can go ahead and create a template and render it.
This is going to give you a pretty good idea about exactly what mustache can do.
And then we'll go ahead and actually wire it up with our new message and a new location message callbacks
to kick things off over inside an index.
You know we are going to make a new template by defining a script tag.
Now inside of the script tag we're going to add our markup.
But before we can do that we have to provide a couple of attributes on script.
First up this is going to be a reusable template and we're going to need a way to access it so we'll
give it an ID.
I'm going to call this one message template and the other property we're going to define is something
called the type.
Now the type lets your editor and the browser know what's stored inside of the script tag.
We're going to set the type equal to inside of quotes text forward slash template.
Now we can write some markup inside of here and it's going to work as expected to get things off.
Let's just go ahead and make a really simple paragraph takk.
We're going to make a p tag inside of the script tag and we'll add some text inside of it.
This is a template and you're going to go ahead and close the paragraph tag.
And that is it.
This is where we're going to start.
We have a message template script tag we can go ahead and now render this over inside of index dot Jap's
by commenting out all the code inside of the New Message listener.
I'm going to comment out all of that code.
Now we can implement the mustache.
J.S. rendering method.
First up we have to grab that template we can make a variable called template to do just this and we're
going to do is select it with Jay query using the ID we just provided message hyphen template.
Now we need to call the H TNL method which is going to return the markup inside of message template
which is the template code or paragraph tag.
In this case once we have that we can go ahead and actually call a method on moustache which was available
to us because we added that script tag.
Let's make a variable called H DML.
This is the thing we're eventually going to add it to the browser and we're going to set it equal to
a call to mustache dot render.
Now mustache dot render takes the template you want to render.
In this case we have access to that right here.
We're going to go ahead and render it.
And now we can spit it out in the browser.
But adding it to the messages Id just like we do.
So we're going to select the element with an ID of messages and we're going to call append and we're
going to append the template we just render which we have access to inside of H DML.
Now with this in place our server restarted and we can actually play around with this by refreshing
the browser.
I'm going to give the browser a refresh and what do we get.
We got this is a template for our welcome message and if I type anything else we also get this as a
template not super interesting not super useful.
What is cool that was that mustache lets you inject values which means we can set up places in our template
where we expect a value to get passed in.
For example we have that text property in order to reference a value you can use the double curly braces
syntax like this.
And then you can go ahead and type the name like text.
Now in order to actually provide this value we have to send in a second argument to the render method
instead of just passing in the template.
We're going to pass in the template and we're going to pass in an object.
This object is going to have all the properties that you're going to be allowed to render.
Now we're currently expecting this text property so we should probably go ahead and provide it right
here.
I'm going to set text equal to the value that comes back on a message dot text.
Now we're rendering the template in a dynamic way.
The template serves as the reusable structure but the data it's always going to change because it gets
passed in when we call Brender.
With this in place we can go ahead and refresh Crome and right here we see welcome to the chat app.
And if I go ahead and type a message that is going to show to the screen which is fantastic.
Now the next step in the process is going to be to get all the data showing we have a firm property
and a created at property 2.
We actually have access to that created at property the formatted time.
We're going to go ahead and uncomment this formatted time line.
This is the only one we're actually going to carry over to the new system.
I'm going to add it up top right here because we do still want to use form at a time when we render.
Now before we do anything else with the template Let's go ahead and simply pass in the values we already
passed the text value in.
Next up we can pass in from it's accessible via message from.
And we can also pass in a time stamp.
You can call that property whatever you like.
I'm going to continue to call it created at and I'm going to set it equal to the formatted time up above.
Now with this in place all the data is indeed getting passed in we just need to actually go ahead and
use it in index.
We can use all of it.
And we're also going to provide a custom structure just like we did when we set up the code above.
We're going to be using some classes I've defined inside of the template for this project.
We're going to start off with a list item using the tag from here.
We're going to go ahead and add a class and we're going to call this class message and in here we can
add two divs the first div is going to be the title area where we add the From and created at values.
And the second div is going to be the body of the message.
Let's add one right here and we'll add a second one just below.
Now for the first div we are going to provide a class the class will equal message underscore underscore
title this is where the message title information is going to go.
And we're going to kick things off in here by providing an H for tag which is going to render a nice
header to the screen and we're going to put inside of H for is the from data which we can do by using
those double curly braces and putting from right here the same exact thing holds true for span that's
going to happen down below we'll add span tag and inside of the span tag we're going to inject created
at adding our double curly braces and specifying the property name.
Now we can go ahead and move on to the actual message body itself.
That's going to happen down below inside of our second div which we will be giving a class.
The second is going to have a class equal to message underscore underscore body.
And for a basic message a non location based message all we're going to do is add a paragraph tag and
we're going to render our text inside it by providing it to curly braces followed by text with this
in place.
We actually have a really great system for rendering our message template the code the markup it's defined
over here which means that it's reusable.
And inside an index dot J.S. we just have a little bit of code to get everything wired up.
This is a much more scalable solution.
It's a lot easier than managing the elements like we did down below for new location message.
I'm going to go ahead and save index Dot.
Yes.
Move into the browser and give things a refresh.
When we do we can see we now have a nice set of styles for the message.
This is some the message I'm going to send that off we get the name the time stamp and the text all
printing.
It looks a heck of a lot better than it did earlier.
Now our send location message is still going to look like trash.
If I click send a location it's going to take a few seconds to get the job done.
And here it is.
It's an styled because it is not using a template.
Well we're going to do is add a template for the new location message.
We'll do some of that together and some of it is going to be a challenge for you.
Together we're going to set up the markup for the template.
Your job will be to render it and pass in the necessary values over inside of index.
HTL we can get started doing this by creating a second template.
Now the second template is going to be pretty similar to the first.
We can actually go ahead and duplicate this template by copying and pasting it down below.
All we need to do is change the ID from message template to location message template.
Now the title area is going to be the same we're going to have our Froment property as well as created
at it's the body that's going to change instead of rendering a paragraph with the text we're going to
render a paragraph that has the link using an anchor tag.
Now to add that anchor tag we're going to add the a tag just like this.
Then inside of the ATF attribute we're going to be injecting the value.
This is going to be the you R-AL that gets passed from server to client.
We're going to add our equal signs are curly braces and the value we want to add here is you are l.
Next up we are going to carry over that target property sending an equal to blank underscore blank which
will open up the link in a new tab.
And finally we can go ahead and close the anchor tag adding the text for the link inside.
Good text for this link would be my current location.
Just like we have right now and this is all we need to do for the template you're part of the challenge
is going to be to wire up all of this inside of index dot J.S. which means down here inside of new location
message you want to do something pretty similar to what we have above.
Instead of rendering everything with J queries you're going to render the template passing in the necessary
data text you R-AL and the formatted time stamp.
Take a moment to knock this out.
When you're done I want you to go ahead and move into the browser send some location messages and make
sure it looks like it should styled where the name is in bold.
The time stamp is in a light gray and the link shows up down below.
Once you're done and everything is working you can go ahead and click play.
All right the first thing we're going to do is comment out the code.
We no longer need that's everything but the variable formatted time.
Next up we're going to go ahead and grab the template from the HD now by making a variable called template
and we're going to use J query to select it by ID right inside of the quotes we'll add our selector.
We want to select by ID so we'll add that pound sign location hyphen message hyphen template is the
IDB provided and now we want to go ahead and call each team to get its inner TNL back.
This is everything I have highlighted right here.
Next up we're going to go ahead and actually render the template by creating a variable called H TNL
to store the return value.
And we're going to call mustache dot render.
This takes those two arguments.
The template you want to render and the data you want to render into that template.
Now the data is optional but we do indeed need to pass some data through.
So we will be providing that as well template is our first argument.
And the second one is going to be an object.
I'm going to start by setting from equal to message from and we can do the same thing with the u r l
u r l equals a message dot A u r l for created at.
We're going to use the form at a time variable instead created at get set equal to formatted time which
is defined just above.
Now that we have access to the HVM we need to render we can use a J query selector to select the element
with an idea of messages and we're going to call it pend to add a new message the new message we want
to add is available via the T.M. variable.
Now that we have our function completely converted over we can remove the old commented out code.
Save the file and test things out over inside of chrome.
I'm going to give the page to refresh to load that latest code.
I'll send a text message to make sure that still works.
Now we can go ahead and send a location message.
We should see in just a second the new data rendering and it is indeed working as expected.
We have the name the time stamp and the link.
I can go ahead and click the link to make sure it is still working.
And it is the little marker shows up right here.
With this in place we now have a much better set up for creating these front end templates instead of
having to do the heavy lifting inside of index.
Yes we can do the template inside of index.
H t m l.
Simply passing the data in.
It's a much more scalable solution.
Now that we have this in place we are done and we can go ahead and commit our changes by shutting down
the server and running get status.
Here we have a new file as well as a couple of modified ones get add dot is going to take care of all
of that for us and we can make our commit get commit with the a flag.
Actually we already added it so we can just use the M flag and mustache J us for message templates.
Excellent.
I'm going to push this up to get hub and we can go ahead and take a quick moment to deploy to Heroku
to use and get push Heroku master.
I'm going to push this up just to make sure all the templates are rendering properly on Heroku just
like they are locally.
It should take just a second to deploy once it's up.
We can open it up by either running Heroku open or grabbing that u r l as we've done before here it's
launching the app it looks like everything and did go as expected.
I'm going to grab the app.
You are all move into chrome and open it up.
And now we're doing the application live inside of Heroku.
And the message data is showing up as expected.
The same thing should hold true for sending the location the send location message should use the new
setup.
It is indeed working as expected which is fan tactic.
That's it for this one.
I will see you next time