If we're going to build a front end we might as well do it right.
And in this video we're going to add an auto scrolling feature.
So if a new message comes in it is visible inside of the messages panel.
Now right away this is not a problem.
I type in I had entered it shows up but as we get further down the list A B C D E F G H I J K you see
the messages start to disappear down the bottom of the bar.
Now I can indeed scroll down to see the most recent messages but it would be nice if I'm automatically
scrolled to the most recent message.
So if a new message comes in like one two three I'm automatically brought to the bottom.
Now obviously if someone does scroll up to read an old message we're going to want to keep them there
we're not going to want to scroll them to the bottom.
That would be just as annoying as not being able to see the new messages in the first place.
Which means that we're going to go ahead and calculate a threshold.
If someone can see that last message like I can here I can CD you in user.
We're going to go ahead and scroll down to the bottom when a new message comes in.
If I'm above that message like I am here we're going to go ahead and leave them alone.
There's no reason to scroll them to the bottom if they're digging through the archives.
Now in order to do that we are going to have to run a calculation.
Grabbing a few properties mostly the height properties of various things.
Now to talk about those higher properties and figure out exactly how we're going to run this calculation
I put together a really short set of slides.
Let's go ahead and dive right in to illustrate exactly how we're going to run this calculation.
Let's take a look at the following example.
We have this light purple box that's taller than the dark purple one.
This is the entire messages container.
It's probably going to contain or way more messages than we can actually see in the browser.
This dark purple area.
This is what we actually see as we scroll down the dark purple area is going to move down to the bottom
and as we scroll up it's going to shift up to the top.
Now we have access to three high properties that are going to let us make the calculations necessary
to determine whether or not we should scroll down a user.
These are the following.
First up scroll height.
This is the entire height of our messages container regardless of how much is actually visible inside
of the browser.
This means that if we have messages before and after what we can see they are still going to be accounted
for in scroll height.
Next up we have clients.
This is the visible height container.
And finally we have scroll top.
This is the number of pixels we have scrolled down into the purple container which would be just this
area here.
Now in the current situation what do we want to do we want to do nothing the user really isn't scrolled
that far down.
It would be a burden to them if they got to the bottom.
Every time a new message came in in the next scenario we scroll down just a little bit more.
The scroll top has increased the client height has stayed the same and so has the scroll height.
Now if we keep going down the list eventually we're going to get to the very bottom.
Currently we should do nothing.
But when we get to the bottom the calculations look a little different here.
You can see the scroll top value which is the space above what we can see plus the client height value
is identical to scroll height.
And this is going to be the basics of our equation.
If the scroll top plus the client height equals the scroll height we do want to scroll the user down
when a new message comes in because we know they're at the very bottom of the panel.
So in this situation what should we do.
We should scroll to the bottom when a new message comes in.
Now there is one slight little quirk we are going to have that message already added.
So we're going to take into account the new message height in our calculation adding up skirl top client
tight end message height comparing that value to the scroll height using this.
We will once again be able to scroll the user to the bottom.
Let's go ahead and wire this up in Adam now that we know how we're going to run that calculation.
Let's go ahead and actually do it over inside of index.
Yes.
We're going to make a new function that's going to do all this heavy lifting for us.
It's going to determine whether or not we should scroll the user to the bottom depending on their position.
Let's make a function right here at the top of index.
Jay Yes.
It's not going to take any arguments and we're going to go ahead and call this function scroll to bottom
and we're going to call scroll to bottom.
Every time we add a new message to the chat area which means we need to do it twice once inside of new
message and once inside of new location message right here I can call scroll to bottom passing in no
arguments and I'll do the same thing down below.
When we have penned a new location message scroll to bottom.
Awesome.
Now all we need to do is wire up this function to one determine if we should scroll them to the bottom
end to actually scroll them to the bottom.
If it's necessary to get started we are going to select the messages container creating a new variable
to store that in.
We're going to actually be creating quite a few variables to run our calculations.
I'm going to add two comments selectors and heights.
This is going to help us just break up the long list of variables right here.
We can make a variable we'll call this variable messages and we're going to set messages equal to a
query selector call.
We're going to select all elements with an ID equal to messages which is just our one.
Now that we have messages in place we can focus on getting those heights.
We're going to go ahead and fetch client right scroll height and scroll top.
First up we can make a variable called Client height setting that equal to messages.
And then we're going to call a prop method which gives us a cross-browser way to fetch a property.
This is a J query alternative to doing it without Jey query this make sure it works across all browsers
regardless of what they call the Propp right here.
We're going to go ahead and provide inside of quotes client height to fetch that client height prop
and we're going to do the exact same thing two more times for the other two values.
Skrill top is going to get set equal to messages dot Propp fetching the Propp scroll upper case t top
and last but not least scroll height.
A new variable called scroll height will store that value and we're going to set it equal to messages.
Drop prop passing in the prop We want to fetch scroll height.
Awesome.
Now that we have this in place we can get started with our calculation.
We want to figure out if the scroll top plus the client height is greater than or equal to the scroll
height.
If it is then we want to go ahead and scroll the user to the bottom because we know they're already
near the bottom.
If client height plus scroll top is greater than or equal to scroll height.
And if this is the case then we are going to go ahead and do something for now we'll just use console
dialog to put a little message to the screen.
Right here we'll just print should scroll.
Awesome.
Now our calculation is not quite complete since we are running this function after we append the new
message.
We do need to take that into account also and as we saw over inside of atom if we can see that last
message we do want to scroll down to the bottom if I'm further up the list.
We won't scroll them but if i'm pretty close to the bottom a few pixels up above we should scroll them
to the bottom because that's most likely what they want.
Now in order to get this done we have to take into account the height of that new message and the height
of the previous message right here inside of atom.
We're going to go ahead and get that done by first up.
Adding a selector.
We're going to make a variable called new message and this is going to store the selector for the last
list item the one that was just added before the call to scroll to bottom.
I'm going to use Jey query to get this done but instead of creating a new selector we can actually build
off of our previous one messages and we're going to call its children method.
This lets you write a selector specific to the children of the message which means that we have all
of our list items so we could select our list items in another context.
Maybe we want to select all the children that are paragraphs.
In our case though we're going to select the list items that are the last child using this last child
modifier.
Right here we now have just one item.
The last list item in the list and we can go ahead and get it's height by making a variable called New
Message height and we're going to set that equal to new message and we're going to call its inner Heights
method this is going to calculate the height of the message taking into account the padding that we've
also applied via C-s.
Now we need to take into account the height of the second to last message as well.
To do that we're going to create a variable called The last message I promise.
This is the last variable.
We're going gonna make and we'll set it equal to new message and we're going to call the Prevx method.
This moves us to the previous child so if we were at the last list item we are now at the second to
last list item and we can get it right by once again calling inner height just like this.
Now we can account for both of these values inside of our IF statement as well.
We're going to add them up right here.
New message right.
And we're also going to add the last message height.
Taking that into account as we make our calculation now that our calculation is complete we can actually
test out that things are working as expected we should see should scroll when we should scroll over
inside of the browser.
I'm going to go ahead and give things a refresh and I'm also going to open up the developer tools so
he can view our console logs statement.
You'll notice on smaller screens these styles and remove these sidebar here you can see new message
dot Prevx inner height is not a function over inside of atom.
I accidentally added a lowercase H.
Pretty easy fix there.
I can save those changes go back into the browser give the page a refresh and we should be good to go.
Now I'm going to hit enter a few times.
Obviously we shouldn't be able to send empty messages but we can for the moment and you can see that
should scroll.
Is printing is not actually going to scroll because of the height of our messages container doesn't
actually exceed the height of the browser space given to it.
But it does indeed pass that condition.
Now as we get down further and messages start to drop off the bottom of the screen you'll notice this
count stops going up the count incremented every time it should scroll printed.
But now it stays at 12.
Even then adding new messages down below.
In this case we can scroll back down to the bottom and add in new message ABC.
This should cause the browser to scroll we're kind of near the bottom.
When I do it should scroll increments to 13 which is fantastic.
If I scroll up to the top of the list and type 1 2 3 and hit Enter should scroll does not increment
to 14 which would be correct.
Would you not want to scroll a user to the bottom if they're up at the very top.
Now the only thing left to do is actually scroll the user when necessary.
That's going to happen over inside of our IF statement we can remove our should scroll console dialog
call and we're going to replace it with a call to messages dot scroll top which is the J Querrey method
for setting that scroll top value.
And we're going to set it to the scroll height which is the total height of the container which means
that we're going to be moving to the bottom of the messages area over inside of Google Chrome we can
now refresh the page to grab that latest index not just file.
And I'm just going to hold the enter key for a little bit.
And as you see we are scrolling down the list automatically if I add a new message.
But it shows up right there from up near the top and a new message comes in like one two three.
I do not scroll down the list which is correct.
Now if I'm not quite at the bottom but I'm pretty close like I would be right here.
And a new message comes in.
You can see I am scroll to the bottom but if I'm a little past that last message like I would be right
here we're not going to get scroll to the bottom which is exactly what we want.
This is all happening because of our calculations.
Let's wrap this up with a commit over inside of the terminal.
If we run get started we see we just have one changed file I can use get commit am to make it commit
scroll to your bottom.
If the user is close to bottom.
Awesome.
I'm going to go ahead and push that up to get Hobb and this is considered a wrap on the first part of
this project.
We have a basic chat application in place from here on out.
The goal is going to be to add chat rooms and names.
So I go to a sign up page.
I enter the room I'd like to join.
And the name I'd like to use then I get brought to a chat page like this one but only for that specific
room.
So there's two rooms users in room one are not going to be able to talk to users in a room too and vice
versa.
That's all coming up next so stay tuned.
I'm super excited to get to it.
I will see you then.