As I mentioned in the end of the last video starting from here on out the goal is to add a joined page
like the one you see here where you provide a name and you provide the room name you want to join.
You'll then be able to join a given room talk to anybody else in that room and you won't be able to
communicate with other people in other rooms.
This means that when you click this form you're going to click join and we're going to have some custom
information passed into the you R-AL into the chat application as we know it.
The one that looks like this.
Now in order to get that done the first thing we're going to do is tweak the current age template file
right now indexed.
Tim L. is going to load first.
We actually don't want that to be the case when we go to local 3000.
We want to show our new joined page.
So what I'm going to do instead is move this by renaming it we're going to rename index ADOT h DML to
chat dot h DML and I'm going to do the exact same thing with index dot J.S. renaming it to chat.
J.S..
And last but not least I'm going to update the reference.
Down below where we load an index datcha Yes Instead we'll load and chat.
Yes.
Now that we have this in place we no longer have an HTL page that's going to load when you visit the
site.
If I try to go to localhost 3000 we're going to get an error saying we cannot get that route.
Nothing's coming back from the server to fix this.
We're going to create our brand new page as index dot h DML.
This is going to be the one that loads when a user visits the app.
Now we'll start off with the very basic template specifying things we've done before like a dock type
setting equal to H.T. in L5 and then we're going to go ahead and at our age Tamal tag inside of here
we can then add our head and body tags and I had my head tag first then I can go ahead and add my body
tag and we'll kick things off by adding a few tags into the head like Mehta So we can set our char set
right here.
Charsadda is going to equal UTF 8 and we're also going to see a few other properties.
I'm going to set a title tag.
This is going to show up inside of the tab as the tabs title.
We can set ours to join then we can add a space a vertical line by using shift backslash and the name
of our app something like chat app.
This will show up in the tab a title and then we can go ahead and link in our stylesheet just like we
did for chat.
HTL right here.
I'm going to get that style sheet reference.
Copy it into the head and I'm going to add that title tag to chat h out right here in Schacht out aged
TNL know we can specify a title just like we did over inside of index dot h DML.
We can give this one a page of chat with a bar surrounded by spaces.
And we're also going to give it the same app name chat app.
Awesome.
Now that we have this in place there is one more thing I want to do before we start updating the body.
This is set a viewport.
Tag viewport tags let you specify certain things about how your site should be rendered.
The viewport tag I'm about to add is going to make our website display much better armed mobile instead
of being really zoomed out.
It's going to fit to the width of your phone tablet or any other device.
We're going to copy this tag from index that TNL to chat.
H.
Female when we're done.
But for now we'll kick things off by adding a metal tag this time around instead of specifying char
set like we've done in the past.
We're going to give it a name equal to view part.
And now we can go ahead and add a few options about what we want to do to that viewport.
All this is going to happen inside of content.
This is going to be a comma separated list of key value pairs one for example is with we're going to
set that equal to device hyphen with.
And this tells your browser to use the devices with as the web pages with then we can add a comma space
and specify our next key value pair.
I'm going to use initials scale.
We're going to set that equal to 1.
This is going to scale the website appropriately so it doesn't look all zoomed out.
And finally user high and scalable will set that equal to.
No we have styles in place to make the text bigger and to make sure that user can always see everything.
So there's no reason to give users the ability to scale.
Now as mentioned we're going to take this matter a tag copy it to the clipboard and add it for chapter
HVM Tamal as well.
Awesome.
And now that we have our head tags set up for index HGL we can move on to the body we're going to be
using a similar set of classes designed to work with this page to get things off on the body.
We're going to add a class of centered hyphen form.
This is going to center that form in the screen and give the entire website that blue background with
the gradient.
Next up we can go ahead and provide the little box.
This is going to be the centered white box that has our form in it.
That's going to be via a div and we're going to give this div a class we're going to set that class
equal to inside of quotes centered high and form.
Underscore underscore form.
Awesome.
Now that we have these two classes in place we are ready to move on actually adding some of the fields
that are going to go in that white box starting with that title.
Chat to do this.
We're going to create a few divs they're all going to look identical so we'll make them once and duplicate
them.
And we're going to add a class equal to form high thin field.
Now we're going to use this four times once for the title once for the name.
Once for the room name and once for the button in order to get that done what we're going to do is simply
copy the line and paste it four times right here.
Now all of this needs to go inside of a form tag the whole goal of this page is to take that data and
submit it redirecting the user to the chat page where we can then bring them into a specific chat room
using the name they provided.
That means we want to wrap these form fields inside of a form tag by opening here and closing it down
below.
Now previously we saw the default behavior for a form tag is to reload the current page posting the
data as a query string.
Well we're going to do instead is specify an action attribute which lets us customize which page to
go to.
In this case we're going to go to a forward slash chat.
H TNL the page that we set up just now.
This means that when someone's done filling out the form field they're going to get redirected to the
chat page and the data down below will get passed along to.
Now the title div is easy or we're going to do is at an H three with whatever title you want.
You could say chat or join the chat.
That looks pretty good then I can go ahead and close my H-3 and move on to the next to form field which
is going to be the display name.
I am going to use a label a label is going to describe a field.
This one will be display name so will open and close the label tag like this and next up we can add
an input right here.
We're going to add an input just like we did for the input on our message form.
We're going to specify type equal to text.
We want the user to be able to enter some text and we're also going to give it a name equal to name.
We are going to use auto focus.
Once again this is going to make sure that when a user first visits the app their cursor is placed inside
of the name field.
Next up is the field for the room name which is going to look pretty similar to the one above.
We are going to start with a label once again this label is going to be a string something like room
name and we're also going to add an input right here.
So the user can specify the room name type equals text and the name will equal a room.
There is no need for autofocus on this one since we already have an auto focused input up above.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and the final form field which is going to be the submit
button for our form by simply creating a button just like this and giving it a text value.
We can have ours set to join with this in place our index.
Each time a file is actually done.
We can load it over inside of the browser.
Our server had automatically restarted.
So a quick refresh should show our page join a chat app.
The goal is to set this up to take a name like Andrew and a room name like Noad course students you
click join and it joins you into this room with this name.
Now currently it's going to do is redirect us to chat dot h TNL.
But as you'll see it does indeed pass the data along.
Here we have a name equal to Andrew and we have real name equal to Noad course students just like we
specified over inside of index dot h t.
And now with this in place we are now ready to start talking about how we can join a specific rooms
inside a socket I O.
Making sure the events we emit only go to other people connected to that room.
We have the stuff in place to get this done.
So we're gonna get started with all of that in the next video.
For now we have a pretty great looking joined page.
This is where we can join a room.
Let's wrap this up with a commit committing our changes.
If Iran gets status you're going to see that we have a modified file index.
H TNL.
And that also thinks we deleted index dot J us although we add something down below.
When we run get add dot and rerun get status to understand exactly what happened here you can see we
copied indexed HVM to chat.
HVM.
We then modified index.
H TNL and we renamed index dot J s to chat.
J asked.
Which is exactly what we did.
I'm going to go ahead and actually make the commit using get commit with the M flag and join page that
submits to chat DML.
We can then make the commit push it up to get how and that is it for this one.
I will see you next time