In the last video we created a little chat page we can type in a name like Andrew and a room like Noad
course and we can go ahead and join that room.
Now when we do we're brought to the chat page but nothing is actually happening behind the scenes to
use any of these values.
They're showing up in the you are l but that's about it.
The goal in this video is to take these values and pass them from the client to the server so the server
can keep track of who's in which room.
And we can set up that private communication.
Currently if User 1 is in Noad course and user two is in re-act course both of them are going to be
able to talk to each other because this data is not used.
Now the first step in getting this data to the server is figuring out where it lives.
This actually lives in the location object.
We're going to use the council to just play around with it.
Location is a global object as provided by your browser.
And on it we have a whole bunch of really interesting things.
Things like host hostname Tref origin path name what we're going to be using is search as you can see
here search is the query string everything from the question mark to the end of the word course.
What I have highlighted here the goal is to get this into a more useful format.
Right now we have just the string we're going to need to parse this.
We're actually going to use a library to do that.
Now that we know where it lives we can access window that location dot search to get this value.
Now I'm adding window up front just to make sure we're accessing the global location property as opposed
to a local variable which may or may not exist called location.
This is going to be the most foolproof way to fetch the query string.
Now the next thing we're going to do is talk about programs and deep harams inside of J.
Querrey we actually have access to the function we can access it by calling Jay query dot PERVAN and
we can pass in an object.
Let's go ahead and create a little object right here.
We'll set name equal to your first name.
I'm going to set it equal to Andrew and we'll set age equal to something like 25.
Now when I run this statement J query is going to take that object and convert it into a set of parameters
that could be added onto what you are out here.
You can see we have name equals Andrew and age equals 25.
This is similar to the format we had up above minus the question mark.
All we'd have to do is add one onto the beginning and we would have a complete search string.
Now the problem with Jay Querrey is that it cannot do it in the other direction meaning it cannot take
this string and convert it back into an object which is kind of what we want.
We want to be able to access this data easily.
Currently that is just not possible.
There's also quirks like encoding and plus characters.
This was originally a space but it got converted to a plus by the form.
We don't want to decode all of that too.
Luckily there is a simple library we can include and we can grab it by going to Linx dot mead and I
go forward slash and de-program Param takes your object and returns the string de-program takes the
string and returns an object and here we have a simple just it's a really short function that we're
going to be adding to our project.
Let's go to the raw version of this page.
Then we're going to save it using right click save as and we're going to add it right into a project.
We have our public J.S. libs folder and right in here we'll simply save it as deep.
J.S. Now once we have that file saved we can actually include it.
This is going to make it much easier to work with the search data down below inside of Adam.
I'm going to head over to chat Dom HTL.
We're not going to need this in index HVM Al but inside of chat Scott H DML we are going to load it
in.
Down below we'll make a new script tag
and we're going to go ahead and set the source equal to inside of quotes forward slash James forwards
slash libs forward slash d Param dot J.
S.
Now when we save chat.
HTL melon head back into the browser.
We can actually refresh the page and play around with this in the council before ever adding it to our
code.
We now have access to Jay queery dot D parameter.
If I run this statement we're going to get our function back confirming that it does exist and all we
need to do is pass in the string.
This is the search string.
Window that location dot search.
So we're taking that search string we're passing it into deep RAM and the resulting object is exactly
what we want.
We have a name property equal to Andrew and we have a room property equal to node space.
Course all those special characters like the end symbol the question mark and the plus character they've
all been removed and replaced with this nicely formatted object.
This is what we're going to use inside of our client side code to get the values and pass them to the
server which is what we're going to do right now inside of atom.
This is all going to happen in chat Dhananjay s right here we have our connect callback function.
This happens when we first connect and right away when we connect we're going to emit an event that's
going to start the process of joining a room socket Io has a built in support for the idea of Romes
creating these little isolated areas where only certain people can emit and listen to events.
All of that gets set up on the server though.
Which means right in here when we connect to the server.
All we're going to do is emit an event called join.
This is going to start the process.
First up let's go ahead and grab our parameters.
The ones that we just learned how to deep program over inside of the console.
Var Parama equals J.
Queried dot deep herem and we're going to pass in window ADOT location and search just like we did.
But for now we have our object and we can go ahead and emit an event right here.
We're going to call socket dot emit and the event that we're going to emit it's going to be a custom
event we'll be creating is going to be called join.
This is going to get emitted from the client and it's going to get listened to by the server when the
server hears this you join in that it's going to go through the process of setting up the room.
Now not all of that is going to happen in this video but we can get started if the data that we're going
to send across is just going to be the Paramo object.
It may or may not include everything we need we'll be doing a little validation on the server.
And last but not least we are going to set up acknowledgements for this one.
If someone does join the room we want to know that if someone doesn't we want to know that too because
if they don't join the room it's most likely because they provided invalid data which means that we
want to kick them back to that joined form forcing them to provide both a name and a room name right
here.
We can go ahead and set up our function and this function could take an argument.
We're going to be setting it up ourselves so we can decide if it takes an argument.
And it definitely does make sense for it to take one in this case.
We're going to go ahead and provide any errors if there is an error.
That's fine we'll be able to handle it if there is no error.
That's great too.
We'll go ahead and do something else right in here.
We can do something if an error exists using if air and we can go ahead and add an else clause to if
there is no error we want to do a different thing.
Now we're not going to fill this out at the moment.
Well we're going to do at this point in time is go ahead and actually set up the listener inside of
server.
As for join that is going to happen over in server J.S. we can make that the very first event just above
create message right here Sacket dot on join.
Now as we already know we are going to be taking some arguments in the callback function.
We're going to get our parameters.
We can call these programs and we're also going to get that call back functions since we are setting
up acknowledgements inside of the join function.
The first thing that we're going to want to do is actually validate the data that came through both
the name and the room.
These are both potential properties on Puranas.
All we really care is that they are not empty strings meaning that it's not just a space it's not just
an empty string and it's not a non string type like a number or an object something like this might
have a length but it's not exactly going to be a valid username or a valid or room name in order to
set up this validation which we're going to be doing other places to like create message.
We're going to create a separate tills file in here.
I'm going to call this validation Dot.
Yes and this is where we can put some validators that we're going to need throughout the project.
In this video we're going to create one called is real strength.
This is going to verify that a value is of a type string and that it's not just a bunch of spaces it
actually has real characters inside of it.
We're going to set this equal to a function that takes a string.
This is going to be the string we validate and it's actually not going to be terribly difficult.
We're going to return and we're going to return in the following conditions it'll return true if it
is a real string and false.
If it's not first up we'll use Type of this is going to get the type of the string variable.
This needs to equal in quotes string.
Now currently this is going to return true for any string and false for any non string value.
But it does not take into account these spaces.
What we're going to do is use the trim method available on Strang's which takes a string like this and
converts it into a string like this.
Trimming all whitespace if you pass a string like this it's going to convert it into a string like this.
Trimming leading and trailing whitespace only.
It's not going to trim any interior spacing.
So if I have space are down below I am still gonna get that space between F and R but all of the leading
and trailing spaces are removed.
We're going to use that right here.
As TR ADOT trim has a length greater than zero after we called trim.
We do need a length greater than zero.
Otherwise we have an empty string.
This is going to be R is real string function and we're going to go ahead and export it real quickly.
Module exports setting it equal to an object where we set is real string equal to the is real string
function as defined above.
Awesome.
Now I can go ahead and save this file.
I'm also going to go ahead and inside of server J S call this function we need to import it first before
we can actually validate those two properties just up above.
We're going to do that right here and we can make a contest and use E.S. six destructuring to grab is
real string and we're gonna grab it using require we're requiring a local file dot forward slash it's
in that utility directory and the file name is validation.
Just like this.
Now we can call is real string inside of join.
That's exactly what we're going to do.
We're going to check if either of them are not real strings if one or more are not real strings.
We're going to call the call back passing in the error right here.
If Prim's dot name is the first one we're going to pass that into is real string
harams dot name.
Now we want to check if it's not a real string so we're going to flip that or.
And here we're going to check if the other property the room name is not a real string.
Now inside of the query string that is called Room a back inside of Adam if it's not is real string
passing in the correct value Puranas room then that's going to be an error too.
And right here we can handle that error.
All I'm going to do is call the callback with a little string message name and room name are required.
Perfect.
Now if that's not the case we do still want to call the call back but we don't want to pass any arguments
and because remember that first argument we set that up to be the error argument.
And if both things are valid we do not want to pass any errors back over inside of a server.
J.S. we now have some pretty basic validation set up.
And before we actually do anything in here which is going to be in the upcoming videos all we're going
to do is add a few cases right here.
If it isn't air that's a pretty big problem and we're going to want to send the user back to the root
of the application by changing one of the properties under location window and data location.
RATH here we can manipulate which page the users on.
Essentially we're going to be read you're writing them back to that root page by having the forward
slash value set to the H ref property.
Now before we do that we can do whatever we like maybe we want to splay a modal using our framework
of choice whether it's foundation bootstrap or anything else to keep things simple here.
All we're going to do is call alert passing in the error just like this.
So a user will see a little alert box.
They'll then click OK and they'll be redirected back to the home page.
Now if there is no error.
All we're going to do for the moment is use console dialog.
To print no error.
Awesome.
With this in place let's go ahead and test that.
Things are working as expected.
Over inside of the browser I'm going to get my current pager refreshed.
Now here we do have a valid name and a valid room.
So when I click refresh we should see no error printing in the council and that's exactly what we get
the data.
We passed through was indeed valid.
Now we can go ahead and go to the root of the page and try some invalid data to demonstrate this.
All I'm going to do is click join without providing either value.
This is going to bring us to the chat app and you can see we can get our little alert box name and room
name are required.
We click OK which is all we can do and we're immediately redirected back to join a chat.
If I do provide some valid data like I display name of Mike and a room name of developers we are going
to be brought to the chat page and we'll see no error shows up which is fantastic.
Now one last test real quick if we have just spaces.
I'm going to change the room name to a bunch of spaces and we click join.
We are going to still get the error even though we do have a bunch of plus signs for spaces up above.
Those are going to be swapped out for spaces when we run our code through deep herem and the air is
still going to occur.
Now that we have this in place we are in a pretty good spot to actually integrate rooms in the next
video before we do though.
Your challenge for this one is going to be to write some test cases for the brand new validation function
we just created which means we're going to make a new test file called a validation test.
Yes.
And inside of here we're going to load in expect making a variable called expect.
We could also make it a constant.
We're going to set that equal to require and we're going to require the expect library just like we
always do.
Next up we're going to load in a real string which is going to be part of the challenge.
Import is real sharing and we're going to add three test cases down below.
They describe block should be something like is real string and the three test cases will be as follows.
Should reject the 9 string values in this case.
I want you to pass a number object or anything else into the real string function.
You should get false back.
Next up should reject strings with only spaces.
If I have a string that's just a bunch of spaces that should not pass the is real string function validation.
That's also going to fail trim is going to remove all of those spaces and the length will be zero.
Last up.
Should allow strings with non space characters.
In this case you can pass in whatever you like some sort of valid value.
You could have space space.
L O T R for a lord of the Rings.
The beginning spaces are going to get trimmed out so it's not important.
You put out the letter.
Any valid string is going to pass this one.
Go ahead and set up those three test cases making sure the right boolean value comes back from.
Is real string when you're done run NPM test from the terminal.
Make sure all of your three tests passed and then you can go ahead and click play how you do hopefully
you were able to test this function without too much trouble.
The first thing we're going to do is inport it by making a variable we can make this a constant or a
variable.
I'm going to go with a constant.
And we're going to use yes 60 structuring to grab it is real string and we're going to grab it off of
the required call to our local file forward slash validation which is just alongside the current file
validation test dot J S.
Now we can add the things we have down below starting with our describe the block.
We're going to describe the is real string function.
Then we can add our arrow function and inside of here we can go ahead and provide our individual test
cases.
It and I'm going to copy it directly should reject non string values.
This is going to be a synchronous test so there's no reason to add the Done argument inside of here.
We're going to pass in a non string value.
I'm going make a variable called response which will store the return result from is real string.
We're going to call it passing in some sort of non-cheating value.
Anything would work.
I'm going to use a number 98.
Now down below we can use expect to assert that the response variable equals false which should be the
case.
We're expecting response to be false.
Perfect.
Next up it should reject string with only spaces.
I'm going to copy that text exactly pasting it inside of our IT name.
Then we can go ahead and add our arrow function.
And for this case all we're gonna do is create a variable called response passing in some sort of string
with just spaces.
We're still going to be calling.
Is real strength.
And right here we'll pass in a bunch of spaces.
And now we're going to assert that responds is false expect response to be false which it should be
because we do not have a valid string.
Next up last test case it should allow strings with non space characters.
I'm going to paste that in here and then we can go ahead and actually set up the test case.
You could have provided a bunch of different values as the argument to is real string.
We're still going to make that response variable.
We're still going to call is real string but right here I'm going to choose to pass in that space space
Andrew space space which is valid.
The trim function is going to remove those spaces in the validation process and the Double-O we can
expect that response is true to be true.
Awesome.
That's all you needed to do.
We can go ahead and remove the comments since we have the actual code in place and the last thing to
do is run the test case to make sure our code actually works.
NPM test is going to get that done.
This is going to run our test suite and right here we have our three test cases for is real string.
All of them are passing which is fantastic.
Now as I mentioned you could pretty much pass anything in here.
The letter D would work as a valid room name or user name.
If I rerun the test suite with as my string the test case still passes it doesn't really matter what
you passed into here.
As long as it had a real non-space character.
Now that we have this in place we are done we're not going to make a commit just yet.
We're kind of halfway through a feature we'll commit once we have a little more in place that's coming
up next so stay tuned.
I will see you then.