In the last video we set up a event listener on the server listening for that joint event.
And we did some validation this at least make sure we have the name and the room name both of which
are going to be required.
The real next step is to actually use the socket IO library to join rooms and this is not going to let
us just join remans but it's also going to give us a different set of methods.
We can choose to emit to everybody connected to the server or just to people in specific rooms.
And that's exactly what we're going to be doing.
We want to emit Chiat messages just to other people who are also in the room.
Now in order to join what you do is you call socket dot joyn socket dot join takes a string the name
and we have that name.
It's available under harams dot room just like we used right here.
And that is it.
We now have a special place for people to talk who are in the same room.
Now this is a string so it would be something like The Office fans or anything else and you have to
join by the string value.
Right here though Paramjit room will get the job done.
Now you can also choose to leave a room using socket leave socket don't leave leaving a room by its
name and the office fans for example this is going to kick you out of that group and you're not going
to get those private messages the messages sent specifically to the group.
Now the next step in the process is to figure out how to actually take advantage of this.
Adding the user to the room is great but if we can't target them specifically and others in that room
it's not very useful.
Well it turns out we have a couple ways to do just that in order to illustrate how we're going to target
specific users.
Let's look at all the ways we've admitted events on the server.
We've used IO and emit this admits it to every single connected user and that's currently what we're
doing for things like create message a new message comes in.
And we admitted to everyone connected.
Next up we have used socket dot broadcasts dot emet we use that right here and as we know this sends
the message to everyone connected to the socket server except for the current user.
The last one we used inside of server dot J S is socket.
We used it right here.
This emits an event specifically to one user.
Now we can take these events so we can convert them over to their room counterpart in order to send
it to a specific room.
We're going to be changing on the two method.
This is going to look a little something like this.
Let's say we want to emit an event to every single person connected to a room and let's just call this
room the office fans for the moment to do that.
We're going to call I know dot to dot to is a method and it takes the room name exactly as it was provided
in the call to join.
In our case that is going to be the office fans just like this.
And then we would chain on a call to a Met and this is going to send an event to everybody connected
to a room the office fans.
Now we can also do the same thing with broadcast meaning that we want to send an event to everybody
in a room except for the current user in order to do that.
We would use the following socket datt broadcast adapt to.
And this works just like the two method defined above the office fans would get passed in and on here
we would call it met.
This is going to send an event to everybody in the office fans room except for the current user or the
one who's actually calling Sacket dot broadcast.
Now the last way we've used a Mehta's socket Amet we're still going to use that when we want to send
something to a specific user.
There is no reason to target them by room since we just want to target them.
This is the two ways we're going to emit two specific rooms in order to actually start wiring some of
that up and we can do is take these two calls up above and we can move them down inside of join.
Meaning that we're not going to tell someone that someone joined a run until it actually joined to the
room by calling join.
We're also not going to tell a user that they have joined around until the call has actually gone through.
It might not go through if the data like the name or the room name are invalid.
Let's take both of these calls and cut them out and we're just going to take them as they are and we're
going to move them down into join for the moment we can move them down below our comments.
I'm going to leave the comments in place so you have these as a reference down the line now right here
we call socket Umit and we emit a new message.
Welcome to the chat app and this line it is actually going to stay the same.
We still just want to target the specific user or the next one is going to change though.
Instead of broadcasting to every connected user We're going to broadcast to just users inside of the
room.
We just joined right here using socket broadcast dot to passing in harams dot room.
We're going to emit a new message and this is going to let everyone know that a new user has joined
instead of new user we can actually specify the name we have access to that right here is a template
string injecting the name first programs name followed by has joined perfect now that we have this in
place we can actually test things out.
Well we're going to do is join a realm then we're going to have a second user join.
And we should see the message right here.
Their name has joined.
We're also going to add a third user into the mix to make sure it's actually sending the message to
just one room over inside of the browser.
Let's get started by creating a user called User 1.
This user is going to join a room called uppercase A.
Now we're going to go ahead and create a second user by going to localhost 3000.
This one can be called user 2 and we're going to join them be just like this.
And if I go between room and room B you can see that no join message printed because we haven't joined
the same room.
We're on completely separate rooms so we should not be getting those messages.
Next up we're going to add a third user.
This user is also going to join a room a user 3 room name room.
And we are going to hit join them when we hit join we can go through the tabs and see what data we get
back.
Here we get Welcome to the chat app.
As expected this is only happening because we've successfully joined the room.
Then in the second tab we get Welcome to the chat app too.
There is no message greeting that other user because the other user joined room.
And the first tab has our user three has joined message and this is fantastic.
Both users are in the room.
So this user should get a message when a new user joins and we've injected the name right here.
As expected things were relatively easy for our joint event listener because we had access to both the
name variable and the room variable.
They were actually passed in as arguments.
It's going to be a lot more difficult for create message and create location message.
We're going to need to figure out a way to get the room back for the given socket so we can commit to
just that room.
We also need to set up that people list on the left hand side bar.
We're going to need to figure out how to use that i o object to get a list of all the people by room
name.
All of that is going to be super important because currently the messages we emit some in message are
for example they're going to show up to all users regardless of what room they're in.
To get this working to get those private runs in place will be persisting that data it's coming up next
so stay tuned.
I will see you then