Before you can add sockets to your web application you need a web application to add them to and that
is exactly what we're going to do in this video.
We're going to make a basic express app we're going to get it up on get hub and we're going to deploy
it to Heroku so we can view it live in the browser.
Now the first step to that process is going to be to make a directory.
We're going to do a few things together to get us all going in the right direction and they'll be a
few challenges scattered throughout this one when we're covering something we've already done before.
The first step in the process from the desktop is going to be to run and Diyar to make a new directory
for this project.
I'm going to call mine node hyphen chat hyphen app.
Then we can use C-D to navigate into that directory and we can run a few commands.
First up and PM in it as with all of our projects in this course we are going to be taking advantage
of and PM.
So we're going to run this command and use enter to use the default value for every option.
When we're done we can type yes.
And now we have the package.
Jason File.
Before we move into Adam We're also going to run get in it to initialize a new get repository.
We're going to be putting this project under version control using get and we're also going to be using
to push to get hub and to Heroku with this in place I can use clear to clear the terminal output and
we can move into atom and we can start by opening up the folder and setting up our basic app structure.
I'm going to open up the folder which we just created on the desktop called node chat app and then here
we're going to get started by making a couple directories.
Now unlike the other apps in this course the chat app is going to have a front end which means we're
going to be writing some DML.
We're going to be adding some styles and we're going to be writing some javascript code that runs in
the browser as opposed to running on the server.
For this to work we're going to have two folders.
One is going to be called server which is going to store all of our node JSE code and the other one
is going to be called public.
This is going to store our styles our HVM l files and our client side javascript.
Now inside of server just like we did for the to do API we're going to have a server.
J.S. file and this is going to be the root of our node application.
This file is going to do stuff like create a new Express app configure the public directory to the static
folder express serves up and finally it'll call app Listen to start up the server inside of public what
we're going to do for this video is create just one file index dot HVM index dot h team is going to
be the markup page we serve when someone visits the app.
And for now we're going to make a really simple one that just prints a message to the screen so we can
confirm it's properly getting served up in the next video we'll worry about integrating socket I O on
the client.
For now though we're going to provide a doc type so the browser knows which version of aged female We
want to use.
We're telling it to use HVM which refers to HCM L5.
Next up we're going to open and close our HTL mouth tag.
This is going to let us provide the head and body tag which is exactly what we're going to need to do
to get things working.
First up is head inside of head.
We can provide various configuration tags.
We're going to use just one for now Mehta So we can tell the browser which Chaar set we want to use
on the metal tag we're going to provide the char set attribute setting an equal to inside of quotes
UTF 8.
Next up we're going to provide the body tag inside of HVM all this contains the H-E mail.
We want to actually render to the screen.
And what we're going to do for this one is render a p tag paragraph and we're going to have some simple
text like welcome to the chat app.
This is all that's going to show up for the moment.
I'm going to go ahead and close the paragraph tag.
Now we can move outside of the TNL file going back into the server file.
We want to set up this server to serve the public directory.
Now unlike the original express application we created a server dodgiest file is not in the root of
the project which means we have to go up a directory from server to node.
Chat App and then we have to go into public.
This is going to make it a little hard to set up the Express middleware but we're going to do is take
a look at a built in node module that makes it really easy to convert paths.
Now in order to show you what I'm talking about let's go ahead and use two cons. dot log calls.
The first council call is going to show us how we used to do it.
And the second one is going to show us the better way to do it inside of the first one we're going to
do is provide the same path we provided for our very first express app.
We use underscore underscore Der. name to reference the current directory which in this case is the
server directory.
Because the files inside of the server folder then we can cannonade forward slash public.
Now in this case we do not have a public folder in the server folder the public folder and the server
folder at the exact same level which means we need to use dot dot to call up a directory and then we
need to go into public.
This is the old way to do things and if we run this in the terminal we can see why it looks a little
weird.
I'm going to use gnomon to run server forwards slash server japes.
And what we get is this path we go into users and through desktop the project folder which is expected.
Then we go into server out of server and into public.
This is absolutely unnecessary.
But we'd like to do is just go from the project folder right into public keeping a clean cross OS compatible
path in order to do that.
We're going to use a module that comes with node called Path.
As always I want to show you where the documentation lives because path has plenty of methods that we
won't be using here.
Node.
Jay Yes.
Dot org is where we can find the docs.
We're going to go to that docs page and then we're going to go to the API reference page.
This is a list of all the modules we have available to us where using the path module and inside of
path the method we're going to be using is join which you can see right here if you click it you can
go to a little example of how joyn works join it takes your partial path and it joins them together
which means the example below results in the following path.
We start with foo which you see right here.
We then go into bar which also shows up we go into Baz forward slash SDF which does indeed show up.
The next part is the interesting part.
We go into this queue structure.
Then we go out using dot dot and you can see the result path doesn't show us going into and out of like
our path does.
Over inside of the terminal instead it resolves that into the final path where the queue you x directory
is nowhere in sight.
We're going to use this exact same method to clean up our path over inside an atom.
We can load in the path module by creating a constant called Path and requiring it.
Remember this one does not need to be installed.
It has a built in module.
You have access to it without using any PM.
Next up we're going to make a variable called public path I'm going to make that a constant variable
since we're not going to be making any changes to it and we're going to call path dot join.
We'll pass them arguments into pathed join in a moment.
Before we do though I'm going to console dialog public path now inside of Patkar join what we want to
do is take these two paths but pass them in a separate arguments.
We do still want to start in the D'oh name and directory the server folder.
Then as the second argument we're going to specify the relative path inside of quotes we're going to
go out a directory using dot dot then we're going to use forward slash to go into the public folder.
I'm going to save the server file and we should now be able to go back to the terminal and see our new
path and here it is instead of going into server and then going out like we do above.
We go right into the public directory which is ideal.
This is the path we want to provide to the Express static middleware now that we have this public path
variable in place it's time for your first of two challenges.
This challenge is going to be for you to set up Express locally before we get into the challenge details
we are going to install it together using NPM I the module name is express and we're going to use the
most recent version at four point fourteen point zero with the Save flag.
I'm going to run the installer then we can go ahead and actually use it inside of server.
Yes.
In packaged out Jason we now have it sitting right here with this in place.
Here is your challenge.
You're going to create a brand new Express application and you're also going to configure the Express
static middleware like we've done previously to serve up the public folder.
Finally you're going to call app to listen on port 3000 you're going to provide one of those little
callback functions to print a message to the terminal like server is up on port three thousand.
Once you have the server created you're going to start it up inside of the terminal and head to localhost
3000 in side of the browser.
If I go there right now we're going to get an error because there is no server running on that port.
You should be able to refresh this page and see the little message we typed in the paragraph tag over
inside of index dot HVM.
So take a moment to knock that out.
You can use anything we've done previously in the course we have done all of this before.
You can also use Google or any other resources if you get stuck.
Take a moment to fill out server test it and when you're done click play.
All right.
Hopefully you were able to get that done without too much trouble.
The first thing I'm going to do is load in express by creating a constant called Express and requiring
the library we just installed.
Next up you needed to make an app variable where we can configure our express application.
I'm going to make a variable called app and said equal to a call to express.
Remember we don't configure express by passing in arguments.
Instead we can figure express by calling methods on app to create routes add middleware or start up
the server.
First up we're going to be calling app use to configure our express static middleware.
This is going to serve up that public folder.
What you needed to do was call Express dot static passing in the path.
We created a public path variable which stores exactly the path we need.
The last thing to do is call app dot.
Listen this is going to start up the server on port three thousand and we're going to provide a callback
function as a second argument to print a little message to the terminal.
Once the server is up I'm going to use console dot Lague to print server is up on port three thousand.
With this in place we can now start up the server over inside the terminal and make sure our index team
l file shows up in the browser.
I'm going to go ahead and use clear to clear the terminal output then I'll use gnomon to run the server
server forward slash server.
Jay ass here we get our little message server is up on port three thousand and over in the browser.
If I give things are refreshed we get our markup.
Welcome to the chat app.
This is fantastic.
We now have a basic server set up which means in the next video we can actually add socket I O on both
the client and the back end.
Now before we go we are going to do just one more challenge getting things on get hub and Heroku while
we are going to do first inside of atom is set up a few things we do need to set up a get ignore file
right here.
We're going to provide that in the route of the project inside of get ignore.
Once again the only thing we'll be ignoring is the node modules directory.
We do not want to commit any of this code to our repo because it can be generated using NPM install
and it's subject to change.
It's a real pain to manage that sort of thing and is not recommended.
You commit it.
The next thing we're going to do is configure a few things for her Roku.
First up if you remember we have to use that process.
Ian vidette port environment variable.
I'm going to create a constant port right here sending an equal to process.
Ian V dot uppercase port or 3000 which we'll use locally.
Now we can provide port here and we can provide it in the message down below by changing our regular
string over to a template string server is up on an island ject the port variable value.
Now that we have that in place the next thing we need to change in order to get our app set up for Heroku
that part of our challenge is to update the package.
Scott Jason file adding a start script and specifying the version of node we want to use under scripts.
I'm going to add a start script telling Heroku how to start the application in order to start the app.
You have to run the node command.
You're going to go into the server directory on the file to started up is server.
Jay Yes.
We're also going to specify engines which we've done before.
Engines as you know lets you tell Heroku which version of node to use.
This is going to be important as we are taking advantage of some features only available in the latest
versions of node right here.
I'm going to provide the exact same key value pair I used previously setting node equal to six point
to point two.
If you're using a different version of node you can provide that here instead of the version I have
now that we have this in place you are ready for your challenge.
Your challenge is going to be to make a commit with all of the current uncommitted files you're going
to then go in to get how and create a good hub repository and you're going to push your local code up.
Make sure the code actually gets on get how you can do that by refreshing the get have repo page and
you should see your directory structure right there on the repo.
The next thing you need to do is create a Heroku application and deploy to it once your application
is deployed.
You should be able to visit the app you are at on the browser and you should see the exact same message
as the one we have here.
Welcome to the chat app should print but instead of being on localhost three thousand you should be
on the actual Heroku app.
Now we already made all the changes necessary inside of the project we configured the port variable
and we set up our scripts and engines.
So you don't have to make any more code changes.
You just need to work your wizardry in the browser and in the terminal to get this done.
Take a moment to knock that out add the get hub repo deployed to Heroku test it.
And when you're done click play all right.
Hopefully you didn't have too much trouble getting that done.
The first step while the one I'm going to take first anyways is to make a new get hub repository we
need a place to push up our code.
I'm going head over to get dotcom click that big green new repository button and we can make a new one.
I'm going to call my repository node course to chat app.
I am going to leave this public and I am going to actually create it.
Now that we're here we have a list of commands we can use.
We have an existing repository we want to push it so we can copy these lines over in the terminal before
we can actually push anything.
We do need to make a commit.
I'm going to shut down gnomon and run get status right here you see we have our expected files we have
the publican's server folder we have good ignore and package Scott Jason Noad underscore modules is
nowhere in sight.
Then you needed to use it get at it to add to these untracked files to the next commit.
If you run get status again you can see everything does look good.
We have four changes to be committed for new files.
I'm going to run get commit with the the flag to specify a message the flag is not required to send
some of the files are already added right here in it.
It is going to get the job done.
Once you have that commit in place you can actually push it up to get Hubei running the two lines they
gave you.
I'm going to run both of those and it's now up on get Haab we can confirm that by refreshing the page
and instead of seeing the instructions we see the files we created the next and last thing to do was
get the app on Heroku.
You don't actually have to go to the Heroku web app to get that done.
We can run Heroku create right here we can go ahead and create the application then we can use get push
Heroku master to deploy the app.
I'm going to go ahead and run that this is going to take my local code push it up to Heroku Heroku is
going to see that new code was pushed.
It's then going to go ahead and deploy it once it's up.
We can use the Heroku open command to open up the app you are in the browser or you can always grab
the you are all right here.
I'm going to copy that you are Al from up above head into the browser.
Paste it and right here we should see our app and we do welcome to the chat application shows up to
the screen.
And with this in place we are done.
We have a basic express server we have a backend and a front end.
It's up on get hub and it's up on Heroku we are ready to move on to the next video where we are actually
going to start integrating a socket I O.
I'm super excited to get to it.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time.