As we discussed in the last video we have our Sacket join listener but the problem is that the information
inside of here it gets lost.
Once the callback is complete things like the user's name and the room name.
They're not persisted anywhere.
We're going to need that information to complete our event listeners down below create message is going
to need to know the user's name as well as the room name to send that message to the specific room.
Same thing with create location message.
Now we don't have access to the data that is inside of join up above but we do have access to one common
thing and that is the Sacket ID.
We have access to the socket variable right here.
Socket dot ID and we also have access to it down below inside of our other event listeners and this
is going to be what we use inside of a data structure.
We're about to create.
We're going to create an array of users where we can store this information when we want to look up
a user like you might want to do down below.
We'll simply pass in the idea to some function.
We'll get back the name and the room name and we can emit the event as we want you know in order to
get that done and we are going to make a brand new file in utils.
We're going to call this file users dot J.S. and this is where we're going to store everything related
to that user's data structure and it's going to be nothing more than an array.
It's going to be an array like this.
It'll be an array of objects and on each object we're going to have the ID which will be the socket
ID some sort of really long string like this.
We'll also have our name and this is the display name for the user of mine might be Andrew.
And finally the room the user joined this could be something like The Office fans.
This is all the information we need to store in our data structure for a user to be able to wire everything
up.
Now the real work is going to come inside of the methods that we'll be creating to manipulate this array.
We're going to have four.
We want to be able to add a user via an add user method.
This is going to take three pieces of information the id the name and the Roman name.
We're also going to want to have a method for removing a user when they leave a room.
Remember we want to update that people list in the left hand side bar.
If I go to localhost 3000 right here when someone leaves we want to update the people list removing
them from the list which means we're going to need a way to remove them as well as add them remove user.
And we're going to be removing users by the socket.
I d.
Next up we're going to have a way to fetch a user.
This is going to come in handy when we're trying to send a message like we do inside of the create message
listener right here.
We're going to want access to the user's name as well as the room in order to fire off the new message
event that is going to happen via a get user method which is going to take an I.D. and it will return
the object up above the last one and we're going to be adding is get user a list and get user list get
user list is going to take the room name it is going to figure out exactly which users are in that room
and it's going to return an array of names and we'll print those names to the client.
These four methods are all we need to get this done.
Now there's a couple of ways we could do this.
We could do something like this.
We might make an array called users sending an equal to an empty array and then we might define our
functions.
You don't have to write this out.
I'm going to be deleting this in a moment.
A VAR AD user and we'll set that call to a function that takes ID name and Rome.
Then inside the function we'll do something like manipulate the Saray with a user's push pushing on
some object then we'll export it using modules export exporting and we add a user function as the add
user property and then we would call add user over and server J.
S..
Now I know I went fast there and that's because we're not going to be using this approach.
This approach works fine.
We have a users array and we can manipulate the array.
It does get the job done but what we're going to do instead is use the yes six class syntax.
This is going to let us create a user's class.
We'll be able to make a new instance of that class and fire all of our methods which will be defining
up above.
I'm going to do this as opposed to creating ad hoc functions that all work with one piece of information
right here.
Now we get this done and we are going to have to learn something new.
We're going to be learning about.
Yes.
Six classes in order to talk about those Let's go ahead and simply create one right here.
Now the syntax for creating a new class is going to look a little strange at first.
It is unique to what we're about to do.
But I promise that once you make one or two classes and add a few methods you'll get really used to
defining the methods and the classes themselves to kick things off.
We're going to create a simple class for a person.
This means that we're making a set of data and a set of methods that are useful for manipulating the
person.
Now in order to get started we are going to use the class keyword followed by the class name.
We're going to use an upper case first letter for our class definition since we are going to be creating
new instances of them with the new keyword.
You do not need to use an upper case P this is just common convention across javascript.
If a function is meant to be used with new like new person new object or new anything else it should
have an uppercase first letter.
This is just a styling convention.
Now right after our name we can simply open and close some curly braces and there we have it.
We have a brand new class and we can even make an instance of it.
We can make a variable called me and said it equal to new uppercase.
The person calling it as a function just like this.
Now we have a new instance of the class and we can do whatever we like with it.
Currently it doesn't do anything but we do have an instance created.
Now one of the first things about a class that's really great is the ability to add a constructor function.
A constructor function is a special function.
It is specific to the class.
It automatically fires and it lets you initialize the instance of your class.
In this case we want to do something to customize an individual person when a new person is created
to define a constructor function.
We start with the name constructor but instead of adding a colon or anything else we simply go right
to our function arguments and right into the curly braces.
This is our function.
It's just like a regular function the code inside is going to get executed and these are arguments but
the syntax for setting it up does look pretty different than what we would do on an object or on anything
else.
Now this constructor function it gets called by default.
You do not need to manually call it and that actually gets called with the arguments that you specify
right here.
Which means that we could have our person constructor function take two arguments.
Maybe we want to initialize a new person with a name and an age.
That means we would pass in name and age right here.
I can say that name is a string.
I'm going to set it as my name and age is a number like twenty five.
The constructor function is now going to get called with this data and we can prove this by using cancel
that log.
To print out the name and as the second argument the H.
Now let's go ahead and run this file and see what we got.
It's sitting in server utility.
I'm going to shut down gnomon and run it clear node server.
Forward slash you tills forward slash users.
J.S. when I run the file what do we get we get Andrew 25.
Because the arguments were properly passed into the constructor.
Now passing data in really isn't useful what we want to do is modify the specific instance you want
to set.
This person's name and age not the name and age for all people in order to do that we're going to use
this keyword in class methods and in the constructor function.
This refers to the instance as opposed to the class which means right.
Here we can set a property on this individual person and this dot name equals name just like this.
I can do the exact same thing for age.
This age equals the age.
Using this is how we customize the individual instance.
Now what we have is an object and we can actually access those properties down below the ME variable
right here.
It is identical to the this variable as defined up above.
Which means that we can actually access those properties console dialog.
I'm going to print the string this name for formatting only.
Then I'm going to reference the actual me dot name property and we can do the exact same thing for age.
We're going to print what we had put in as this age only We're going to access it via media age.
We can now rerun the file using gnomon gnomon server forward slash you tills forward slash users.
Jay Yes and what do we get.
We get exactly what we expect the individual person was updated this name was set to Erigeron it is
indeed showing that down below.
Now that we have a basic idea as to how we can initialize a class.
Let's go ahead and talk about methods.
Methods can be any function they could take arguments maybe they don't take arguments and to define
them.
All we do is the following without adding a comma.
Another quirk of the class syntax we specify our method name.
I'm going to create one called a get user description and this one is not going to take any arguments
so we can leave that arguments list empty down below inside of the function itself.
We're going to go ahead and return a description since the method after all is called Get user description.
We're going to return a template string injecting some values inside of there.
The general flow is going to be Jeon is one year inside of parentheses as years old.
This is what we want to print but we want to use those specific values for this individual person and
to do that we're going to access those properties once again instead of a static name we're going to
inject this dot name and instead of a static age we're going to inject the age this dot age.
Now we can go ahead and actually test out get user description by calling it down below.
We can make a variable called description.
We can set it equal to me dot a get user description and we can go ahead and do something with the return
value like printed to the screen using Konsole dot lock inside of the log argument list.
I'm not going to pass in description.
Now we can save the file and we should see over inside of the terminal our description in this case
Andrew in 2005 Andrew is 25 years old when I saved the file gnomon is going to restart and right here
we get just that Andrew is 25 years old prints to the screen.
This is the very basics of classes.
There's a ton of class related features we won't be exploring just yet.
But for now this gives us everything we need in order to get started.
Instead of a person class we're going to create a user's class and instead of methods like get user
description we're going to create methods like the ones we have here.
We're also going to be adding test cases as we go to make sure they work as expected in this video.
We're going to get started adding the users class and in the next one we'll finish it up adding all
of the methods.
For now though we can start defining it.
I am going to comment out the person class down below.
Since we do want it in place as documentation but we're not going to exactly use it inside of the app
will leave it a bit later once we are more comfortable with classes.
Now right here we're going to start by creating our users class using the class keyword class and users
just like this.
We're then going to go ahead and open up and close our curly braces and inside of here we can specify
any methods we like such as the constructor function.
We are going to define a constructor function although they are completely optional when creating classes.
Right here we're going to set up our constructor function by name and then we'll have our arguments
list followed by the opening and closing curly braces.
Now the constructor function for users unlike person is not going to take any arguments when we make
a new users instance.
We just want to start with an empty array of users.
We're going to be making this new instance over inside of server G-S when we first start the app that
is going to happen up top and down below we'll actually be using the methods when someone joins a room
leaves a room or manipulates a room in whatever way they want.
That means that right here all we need to do is set this dot users the users property equal to an empty
array.
And this is going to be the array we've defined right here.
The next thing we're going to do now that we have our constructor function in place is create the add
user method.
We're going to create that right here by defining it like we did forget user description add user just
like this.
We're going to set up the arguments list.
This one is going to take some arguments will specify those in a moment and we're going to open and
close our curly braces for the actual function code.
The three arguments we're going to require is ID name and Rome in order to add a user to the user's
array.
We need those three pieces of information once we have them actually adding them into the list is going
to be really easy.
I'm going to get started by creating a variable user so we can make an object to push on to the array
right here.
Well an ideal property equal to the ID argument and we'll do the same thing for name.
And finally for Rome now we have a user object with those three properties and we can go ahead and push
it on the array.
This dot users dot push to add an object onto the end.
And the thing we're going to be adding on to our array is the user variable.
Now that we have this in place we are basically done.
The last thing I'm going to do is go ahead and return the successfully created user.
Just like this.
And there we go.
Add user is complete.
We're not going to wired up just yet but we can add a test case for add user.
We'll do that over inside of a brand new file called you guessed it users a dot test dot J.
S. in here we'll be able to load in users test it and do whatever else we might need to do.
Now the first step is going to be to actually export users.
Currently we define the class but we do not export it exporting it is going to be the same as exporting
anything else.
There's nothing special there.
Module dot exports.
And we're going to go ahead and export inside of curly braces an object where the users property equals
the users class definition we have above making sure to match that case.
Now that we have this in place we can actually require our class and make new instances of it over inside
of the test file.
Let's get started by loading and expect Konst expect equals require expect and we can also go ahead
and load in our users file Konst using E.S. 60 structuring.
We're going to grab users and we're going to get that via the local file dot Ford slash users.
Awesome.
Now for the moment we're just going to add a test case for adding a user.
We'll make a quick describe that block.
Most of the heavy lifting is going to happen in the next video right here.
We'll describe our users class.
We can then add our aero function and we can go ahead and add a test case.
It inside of quotes should add new user.
I'm going to go ahead and set up the function for this one it's going to be a synchronous function so
there's no need for the Done argument.
And we can create a new instance of what users are users with a lowercase you equals a new users right
here.
Now since we don't take any arguments in the constructor function we're not going to pass any in when
we actually create our instance.
The next thing we're going to do is make a user then we'll be passing its properties to add user making
sure the appropriate thing shows up in the end.
Let's go ahead and make a variable user right here and we'll set that equal to an object.
I'm going to go ahead and set on this object three properties and Id equal to something like 1 to 3
a name property equal to some name like Andrew.
You can go ahead and use your first name and a room name.
I'm going to use the office fans.
Perfect.
Now we have the user in place and we can go ahead and call that method that we just created the add
user method with the three necessary arguments ID name and Rome.
I'm going to store the response in a variable called response user and we'll set it equal to users dot
add user passing in those three pieces of information.
User ID user dot name.
And as the third argument user datt room with the call in place we can now start making our assertions
one assertion we want to make is that the actual users array was updated.
It should've been updated when we called this dot user's dot push.
I'm going to expect that by calling expect we're going to expect something about users ADOT users.
Sorry for the double users.
They're the first user refers to this variable.
And the second one actually accesses the user's array as defined right here.
And then we're going to call two equal.
Remember for arrays and objects you have to use two equal as opposed to B.
We're going to expect it to be an array with just one item.
The item should look just like the user object we have above.
If this passes then we know our user was indeed added to the user's array.
I'm going to go ahead and save the file and shut down node.
Man I'm going to clear the terminal output and run NPM test to make sure our brand new test case is
passing end when I run it.
It does indeed pass.
Right here we have our users block and should add a new user is working as expected.
With this in place we are ready to move on to part 2 where we actually finished the methods as well
as the tests.
Then we can integrate it into our application.
As a quick recap in this one we looked at how we can create classes in year 6 using the class keyword.
We made a person class which was just an example.
And we made our users class which will actually be using throughout the course we looked at adding custom
methods as well as setting up our constructor function.
As I just mentioned we'll be continuing with this in the next one part two.
So stay tuned I'll see you then.