It before we can integrate users into our application let's go ahead and finish building it out which
is going to be the goal of this video.
We have three more methods to add and test.
The first one is remove user which is going to take an argument of the ID of the user.
You want to remove this is also going to return the user that was just removed.
So if I remove the user with an ID of three I want to get rid of it from this list.
But I do want to return the object will leave a little note about that right here.
Return user that was removed.
Awesome.
Now the next method that we're going to be filling out is a get user get user is going to take the exact
same arguments as remove user.
We're going to find a user by id returning the user object but we're not going to be removing it from
the array.
Now the final one that we're going to create as specified up above is a method called the get user list
and this is going to get a list of all the users just their names by the room name which means that
we're going to iterate through the user's array looking for all the users whose room matches the room
specified perfect.
This is going to return an array something like this.
Mike Genn Kalib assuming those are the people inside of the room now notice here we're not specifying
the room or the id property we're just returning an array of strings.
Awesome.
Now that we have this in place let's go ahead and add one thing to our test file in order to get these
methods to work.
We're going to need seed data we're going to need users that already exist.
Otherwise we can't remove one.
We can't get one.
And we definitely can't get a list of the rooms these non-existent users are in in order to fix that
over inside of user test.
J.S. we're going to add a before each call which we've used in the past before each as we know is going
to get called before every single test case.
It's going to help us initialize some data.
Now the data we're going to initialize is going to be defined just above in a variable called users.
And the reason I'm defining an outside of a For Each is so it's accessible inside.
Before each end it's accessible inside of the test cases down below inside before each.
We're going to set users equal to new users and we're also going to set the users users Iraq right here.
We can specify an array of objects and this is going to let us add some initialising data.
Let's go ahead and provide three.
The first one will have an ID equal to one will set the name equal to something like Mike and we can
go ahead and set the room equal to whatever we like.
I'm going to go ahead and use a room name of Noad course we can take this object and copy it two more
times I'm going to add a comma paste in what I just copied and do the same thing again comma followed
by paste.
I'm going to change it to an idea of two for the second user.
We'll change the name to something like Jan and we'll change the room name to react of course.
Now for the last user we are going to change the ID and the name will make the ID 3 and we'll make the
name something like.
Julie but we're going to leave the room as Noad course so we can test that.
Our Get user list function does indeed return the correct results.
The test cases aren't going to be required to use our users variable as defined here we can still define
a custom one like we do down below.
If I run the test watch script and PM run test HIF and watch we're going to see that our one test case
is still passing.
I'm going to save the file to rerun the test suite and right here we have 6 passing test cases regardless
of whether or not we use this.
We can still use a custom one like we do here now that we have this in place we can go ahead and start
filling out some of these methods.
We're going to fill out to get user list together and you're going to be responsible for remove a user
and get user.
Now in order to fill out get a user list we're going to start by finding all of the users whose room
matches the room argument specified here.
In order to do that we're going to use the filter method on arrays which we've used in the past.
Let's make a variable we'll call it users and we'll set it equal to this dot users which is the right
of users dot filter.
Now if you remember filter takes a function as its argument this function gets called with each individual
user and we can return TRUE to keep this item in the array or we can return false to have it removed
from the array.
Right here I'm going to go ahead and return.
And we're going to return user dot to Rome and we're going to check if that equals using three equals
signs.
The room argument if they are equal this is going to result in true that value will get returned if
they're not equal it's going to result in false and the user will not be added to the list above.
Now we can go ahead and use the shortcut for our iOS 6 arrow function instead of adding the return keyword
here and specifying the actual arrow we'll use the shorthand like this exact same functionality just
a different technique.
Now that we have this in place we have a list of all the users who do match the criteria.
The next step in the process is to take that array of objects and convert it to an array of strings.
All we care about is getting that list of names in order to do that.
We're going to use map right here.
I'm going to create a variable called names array.
And we're going to set this equal to users dot nap.
Now we have used map in the past as we know map also takes a function similar to filter it also gets
called with the individual item in this case an individual user.
But map lets us return the value we want to use instead.
So we're going to get an object in here.
This is going to have the ID property room property and the name property and all we want is the name
property.
So we are going to return user dot name and we can simplify that even further using the shorthand for
the arrow function user name.
Right here is going to be implicitly returned.
Now that we have our names are-I all we need to do is go ahead and return it by returning names array.
Now this is going to get the job done.
Before we simplify it any further.
Let's go ahead and write a test case to make sure it works inside of users and test.
J.S. we can get this done below our other test case it should return names for node course right here
we're going to write a test case that returns all of the users inside of the node.
Course we should get the two users back.
Mike and Julie right here we'll make a variable we'll call that variable user list and what we're going
to do is call the users variable defined up here.
This is the one with our seed data.
We do not need to create a custom one like we do for the other test case.
Users do not get user list and we don't get user list takes one argument the name of the room you want
to fetch the list for this one is called node space course.
Make sure your capitalization lines up.
Then we can go ahead and add a semicolon at the end.
The last thing to do is add our assertion making sure that when we get back is what's expected right
here we'll expect that the user list equals using two equal the following array.
It's going to be an array where the first item is Mike.
And the second item is Julie.
If that assertion passes we know get user list worked as expected because that's exactly what we have
to find up above.
Now we can go ahead and copy this test case doing the exact same thing for the react course should return
names for re-act course will change node to react.
And we're going to go ahead and update what we expect the re-act course has just one user that user
has a name equal to Jan..
Now this is a pretty good test case if we save users test.
Yes it's going to rerun the entire test suite.
We should see we have our three tests under the users describe black and they should all be passing.
That is indeed the case.
The next two methods that we're going to be creating remove user and get user are going to be yours
to do as a challenge.
I'd also like you to write some test cases that make sure they work as expected.
Let's go ahead and write the statements for the test cases together and you'll be responsible for actually
filling out the method and filling out the test case right here.
It should remove a user and this method is going to take the idea of one of our seed users whether it's
one two or three it's going to pass it to the function remove user and your job is going to be to assert
that the user was indeed removed.
Now there really is no right or wrong way to make the assertions.
If you find you do things a little differently than what I do as I go through the challenge at the end
that is perfectly fine.
Next up it should not remove user in this case.
I want you to pass in an ID that is not part of our seed user array.
That means something like 44 128 or basically any string that's not one two or three.
In this case you should be asserting that the array has not changed.
We should still have those three items.
Now those are the two test cases for our remove user method.
Next up is get user.
We're going to add to similar test cases.
First up it should find user you should pass in a valid ID and you should get the user object back.
And the other one is going to be it should not find user just like it should not remove a user pass
in an invalid ID and make sure that you do not get a user object back.
Now that you have this in place you know what tests you need to fill out.
Over inside of user data.
Yes.
All you need to do is fill out these two functions and I'll give you a hint.
I used the filter method on the array extensively inside of both of these.
The goal here is to search through the user's array finding items with this idea.
Now there is no wrong way to do it.
If you find you use something like low dash underscore another array method aside from filter whatever
it takes to get the job done.
And that is perfectly fine.
Once you are done go ahead and make sure everything is working as expected by rerunning the test suite.
If you do see all of your tests passing that's great.
You can go ahead and click play Jiddu Hopefully you are able to fill out both of those methods and you
are also able to get those test cases up and running.
I'm going to start off with a get user the goal here is to return the user object whose I.D. matches
the ID of this argument to get that done.
I am going to be using filter.
We're going to return the result from this dot user's dot filter just like we do down below.
We're going to be filtering by ID here we filter by room.
We're going to pass in our era function using the expression syntax.
The argument will be the user.
And right here we are going to go ahead and return true if the user's ID property equals the ID of the
argument if that is the case.
We do want to keep this user in the array.
And in the end we should have just one user or zero users and all were going to do is return the first
item.
If theres one user in the array we're going to get its object back right here.
If there no users we're going to get undefined which is exactly what we want.
Now that we have get user in place we can write the test case for that.
We have to write here it should find user and it should not find user for it should find user.
I'm going to get started by making a variable called user ID and I'm going to set this equal to the
ID I want to use.
I need a valid ID so I'm going to go ahead and use two one two or three it would have worked here.
Next up I am going to go ahead and make a user variable.
This is going to be the return result from a get user.
I'll set it equal to users dot get user and we're going to try to fetch a user whose ID is to by passing
an user ID.
Now the next thing we're going to do is make an assertion about what we get back.
We should have gotten our object back and we can expect that user dot I.D. equals using to be the idea
above the user id variable.
I'm going to go ahead and save the test suite and you can see all of our test cases are still passing
which is fantastic.
If it does not equal the I.D. maybe the ID is three.
You're going to see the test case fail and we do get a pretty clear error message we expected two to
be three which clearly is not the case.
This is the final test case though and we can move on to it should not find a user in this case.
We're going to follow a very similar format creating the user id variable and setting it equal to a
user ID that does not exist inside of our built in users something like 99 would get the job done.
Next up will be making a user variable once again to store the return result from get user users ADOT
to get user passing in our user ID.
Now in this case we would expect that undefined comes back filter should return nothing.
And if you try to fetch the first item in an empty array you're going to get undefined.
We can prove that over in the terminal by running node and right here inside of our little console we
can create an empty array and we can access the first item.
What do we get back.
We get back undefined.
I'm going to shut that down.
Restart our test suite.
And over here we are going to go ahead and make our assertion.
We're going to expect user to not exist.
Perfect.
I'm going to save the file and all of our test cases should still be passing.
They both are.
That's great.
Next up we need to write the remove user method and we also need to fill out the test cases over inside
of user data.
Yes we can get started by finding the user if any.
That means that we're going to use a similar technique to what we have right here.
I'm going to actually copy this line and paste it just right here.
Creating a variable called user sending an equal to what else but this.
Now you could also go ahead and actually call get user right here.
I could call this dot get user passing in the Id just like that.
Both of those solutions are going to work as expected.
Next up if there is a user we want to remove it if user We're going to do something special in here.
And regardless of whether or not a user did exist we are going to return the value user if it didn't
exist.
We're going to return undefined which is great if it did exist after we remove it which is going to
happen right here.
We'll be returning the object also.
What we want.
All we need to do inside of here is figure out how to remove it from the list.
To do this I'm going to set this users equal to this users and we're going to call philtre finding all
users whose I.D. does not match the one specified up above we're going to call FELTER passing in our
aero function.
We're going to get the individual user right here and all we're going to do inside of our erro expression
syntax is add user ID does not equal I d this is going to create a new array right here setting it equal
to this users and we're going to have the item removed if any if there was no item that's fine the statement
is never going to run and we'll be able to continue on returning undefined.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and write a test case that make sure it works as expected.
I'm going to say user dot J.S. and right here we're going to fill both of these out.
Let's get started with should remove a user.
I'm going to make a variable user ID to store the ideal ID which would be 1 2 or 3.
I'll go with one then we can go ahead and actually remove it.
Storing the return result in a user variable.
I'm going to call users dot remove user passing in my user ID variable which is one.
Now that we have the potentially removed user we should be able to go ahead and assert some stuff.
We're going to expect that the user object exists right here.
We're going to expect that it's ID equals the ID we have up above expect that the user removed has an
ID equal to using to be user ID.
Awesome.
Next up we're going to make sure that the user was removed from the array.
We're going to expect users dot users dot length to be in this case too.
It should have been three in the beginning and once we removed the user it should have been two down
below.
We're going to do some similar stuff.
We're just going to be tweaking the user ID.
I can actually copy the contents of our first test case paste it into the second one and only to do
is make a few tweaks.
I'm going to change the ID to an invalid Id like 99.
We are still going to call remove user with the ID.
In this case though instead of expecting the user to have an id property we're going to expect that
user does not exist using two not exist.
Perfect.
Next up we're going to expect the length has not changed right here.
We're going to make sure that the length still equals three.
Now I can go ahead and save the test file.
This is going to restart everything inside of gnomon and what we should get is a test suite that's passing.
It looks like it did already run although the content and change.
So it's a little hard to figure out if anything happened.
I'm going to shut that down and run NPM test just to verify.
And right here you can see all 12 test cases are passing and this is fantastic.
We now have all of the methods we need to persist a user across the different event listeners whether
they're sending a message a location message whether they're connecting or leaving we're going to be
able to keep track of them and send the right thing to the right people.
The actual integration is coming up next so stay tuned.
I will see you then.