In this video we're going to start wiring up that user's class we created and to kick things off.
We're going to wire up the people list which means that we need to do something when a user joins right
here.
And when a user leaves we want to keep that list up today.
And every time we update it we want to give a fresh copy of the list to the client which means that
the server is going to need to emit an event to the client the client is then going to listen for that
in the end.
And it's going to update the markup.
Now we can view exactly where this is going to happen by starting up the server with node Mohn server
forward slash server.
J.S. that is going to head over to localhost 3000 and open up a chat page display name Andrew room name
Lord Of The Rings.
Now once we're in here we have our People list.
Currently it should show us since we are in the room.
And when a new user joins it should automatically show that user.
Right now none of this is happening but with our new event in place it's all going to happen.
Now the first thing we're going to do is figure out exactly what this event is going to look like over
inside of.
Chat dot J.S. we can add a listener figuring out what works for us.
What does the client really need to get this done.
And then we can go ahead and wire up the server to fulfill those needs.
Right here inside of chat dot J.S. somewhere down below just below disconnect.
We're going to add a new listener socket.
On and we're going to listen for a brand new event.
This one is going to be called update user list.
Now update user list is going to need to get past some information.
We're going to need the list of users to show instead of the currently displayed ones which means we're
going to expect one argument a user's array and this user's array is going to just be an array of names
exactly like what we return from a get user list over inside of the user's class back inside of chat.
Yes.
For the moment all we're gonna do is log the list to the screen when it comes through.
Can Soldat log users list.
And the second argument will be the actual users array.
Awesome.
Once we had this wired up all we need to do is add some Jey query to update the DOM.
The harder part is going to be getting a updated and up to date list.
Back to the client.
Over inside of server yes.
Step 1 to that process is going to be to inport declasse that we've been working so hard to create.
Currently we do not use it up above.
I'm going to go ahead and get this done.
Just below where we load an Israel string.
We can make it constant and I'm going to go ahead and pull off the user's property which is the one
we export at the bottom of users.
J.S. and we can import that using require.
I'm going to require the local file daat forward slash.
It's in the hills directory and this one is called users perfect.
Now that we have users in place we can make a new instance of it.
This is going to be the user's instance we use down below we need a way to run these methods.
So right here below our IO variable we can make a new variable called users sending equal to new users
just like this.
Now we're going to be able to call all of our user methods to add remove fetch and otherwise manipulate
that data.
The first step in the process is going to be to add a user to the list when they join a chat room.
We can do that right after our call to socket dot join.
I'm going to remove the old comments although you can choose to keep yours around if you find there
are a good reference just below socket join.
We're going to call users dot add user adding our brand new user and we need to pass in those three
pieces of information.
The socket ID socket ID is where that's stored the name that's on Paramo dot name.
And finally we're going to go ahead and pass in the room name harams dot room.
Awesome.
Now as you notice this code is not supposed to run if there is a validation error meaning that the name
or the room name is not provided.
But currently that's not the case.
Right here we don't actually stop the function execution.
I'm going to use a return to make sure none of the code down below ever fires if the data is not valid.
Perfect.
The next step in the process is going to be to make sure that there is already no user with this ID.
I'm going to call users dot remove user to get that done.
Passing in the only argument it requires the socket Id just like this.
That means that user joins the room.
Then we remove them from any potential previous rooms.
And finally we add them to the new one now that we have this in place we can actually go ahead and admit
that event we're going to emit the event in the client expects update user list with the user's array.
If we don't admit the event the clients is never going to get the new list and we just updated the list.
So we definitely want them to get a fresh copy.
This means we want to emit an event to everyone in the chat room just as we had in our comments earlier
that gets done via IO dot too.
We're going to pass in the room name and then we're going to call emit emitting the event.
Now we can go ahead and fill out too.
First we want to pass in the room name harams room.
Has that information.
And next up we want to emit the event the event name as we just defined over and chat dot J S as Update
user list.
And the last thing we need to do is get the user list.
We already have that users that dot get user list passing in the name of the room.
We want to get the list for once again harams dark room that's going to be the only argument we pass
in with this call in place we should be able to actually view this over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to save this file which is going to restart the server and over inside of the browser I can
open up the developer tools to view the console log statements and I'm going to give the app a refresh
if I do refreshed the application what do we see we see a user's list right here and we have Andrew
printing twice.
We'll talk about why in just a second if I refresh the page for a second time what do we have.
We have Andrew printing three times as you can see this is happening because we're not removing users
from the list when they leave the chat application.
That's the second goal in this video.
We currently have a user list.
All we need to do is update it when a user leaves as well.
That's going to happen inside of atom and down near the bottom in the disconnect Lessner right here
we want to remove the user and then we want to update the list once again.
I'm going to do that by doing a few separate things.
First up we're going to make a variable called user storing any potentially removed users remember the
remove user method does return the user removed.
Users don't remove user passing in the ID socket dot ID.
Now we only want to do something if we actually remove the user if the person had it and joined around
there's no reason to actually do anything.
If a user was removed we are going to emit two events and we're going to emit them to every single person
connected to the chat room which means that we're going to be using IO dot to emit just like we did
up above.
We're going to do this two times so I'm going to copy this line and paste it down below the first one
is going to update the user list and the second one is going to print a little message like Andrew has
left the room.
The first one is going to take the user room property as the only argument user room stores the room
string.
We're going to provide that for both.
And now we can start emitting our events.
I'm going to emit the update user list event first right here inside of quotes update user list.
And we're going to go ahead and call the exact same method we did right up above.
Users not get user list passing in the room.
User datt room.
Now when someone leaves the room they're going to be removed from that list.
And we're not going to see those duplicates that we had over inside of the Web Developer Council.
The next thing that we want to do is emit a message.
We're going to emit a message from the admin to everybody kind of like we did up above.
We greeted the user and we told other users that someone joined right here.
We're going to emit a new message and we're going to call generate message like we've done in the past.
We're going to pass in those two arguments the first one is admen.
This is going to be an admin message.
And the second one can be a template string.
We're going to inject the users name user name and then we're going to say that user has left.
Perfect.
Now that we have this in place everything should be working as expected.
Hopefully over inside of chrome we no longer get those duplicates.
I'm going to give the page or refresh.
And what do we see.
We see we have a users list with just one user.
Andrew if I refresh the page we no longer get the duplicates because when I leave I get removed and
when I come back when the page finally finishes refreshing I get at it.
Now the same thing is going to be true if I add a new user for the moment.
I'm going to switch the browser to just take up half the width on my screen.
I know it's a little cramped will only be here for a second.
I'm going to open up a second tab and drag that to the other half.
So he can view both of these side by side.
I'm also going to open up the developer tools for this second tab and we're going to join the exact
same room.
Let's go to localhost three thousand.
I'm going to join as Mike and the room name is going to be the same l o t r.
Now as soon as I click Join I should see an updated list in both councils.
I'm going to click join.
Right here we get Andrew Mike and right here we also have Andrew Mike which is fantastic.
I also get a little message saying Mike has joined.
That was in place earlier.
The real test is what happens when a user leaves.
I'm going to kick Andrew out of the chat room and over here inside of our other chat window.
We have Andrew has left printing into the screen and we have our new user list with just one user.
Mike this is fantastic.
We're now keeping track of users as they come and go which lets us do really cool things like printing
custom messages and updating the people list.
The last thing to get done is to actually render the names to the screen instead of just printing them
in the council.
We want to go ahead and take these names and add them to the list.
That's going to happen over inside of our event listener.
We're going to use a query like we have in the past right here.
We're going to do something with those users.
First up.
Let's go ahead and make a new Jay Querrey element.
We're going to make a variable called ul.
This is going to store a new element using Jay Querrey.
We're going to create an unordered list.
We can actually create an ordered list since this is an ordered list of users.
That's n o l as opposed to a UL.
Right here we'll create that odel tag awesome.
Now we need to iterate over every user doing something with that user.
Users dot for each is going to let us get that done right here.
We're going to pass in our function and inside of that function we can add the individual user and the
argument for the function is the name.
This is the user string and all we're gonna do is append something to our ordered list up above.
That's going to be a o l dot append.
Now what exactly do we want to append what we want to append and list item the list item is going to
have a Text property equal to the name and that's going to get everything rendering just right.
Right here we can use J query to create a new list item by opening and closing our list item tag.
Then right after the closing parentheses for Jay Querrey we are going to call text so we can safely
set the text property equal to the user's name.
Now we have an updated list but it's not actually getting rendered to the screen.
The last step is to render it by adding it to the DOM.
Now over inside of chat.
HVM L we do have a place for that.
It's this div right here with an idea of users which means that we can select it.
Jay Querrey the selector is going to start with the hash sign since we're selecting by id and we're
selecting users then and we can go ahead and actually add the list.
I'm going to set the HTL male property equal to our ordered list up above as opposed to using it pand
we don't want to update a list.
We want to completely wipe the list replacing it with the new version.
Now we can save chat dot JSA and test things out over inside of the browser.
I'm going to go ahead and close the console refresh the page.
And what do we see.
We see the number one followed by Mike.
Now number one is coming from the fact that we're using an ordered list if I add a second user We're
going to see that second user.
Let's create a second user.
We're going to give it a display name of gen then we'll go to the same room.
EHLO t r and when we join what do we get we get a little message and we get our two users and the same
thing is showing up over here.
Now I'm going to go to the second tab and I'm going to close the first when I do that the list automatically
updates.
And we also get our message saying that Mike has left and this is fantastic.
With this in place we are one step closer to being complete.
The messages are still going to everybody.
They're not specific to the room but that is something we're going to take care of in the next video.
For now we are done.
I am going to make a commit.
It has been a little while and we do have a completed feature.
So let's go ahead and do that.
First up we'll run get status we have some new files as well as some existing ones.
I'll be using add to add all of those to the next commit.
Finally we can use get commit to actually make the commit.
I'm going to use the M flag to add our message and right inside of quotes add users class and update
user list event perfect.
We can go ahead and make this commit and push it up to get hub feel free to push to Heroku if you want
I'm going to hold off a little bit longer.
Everything should be working there as well as locally in the next video we're going to be making sure
those messages whether it's a text message or a location message only gets sent to the people in the
room.
That's coming up next.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then.