In the last video we wired up that people list making sure that as new users come and go the list gets
updated.
In this video we're going to make sure that our text and location messages only get sent to users in
the same room.
Currently it gets sent to everybody.
We can prove that by opening up a new connection.
I'm going to use my name and we're going to join a different room from EHLO TR The Office fans works
when I join the room you can see that the people lists are indeed correct.
A user in one room does not update the people list for a user in another room.
The difference though is that the text messages do not follow those rules.
Neither do the location based messages.
Here we have a text message any location message as well.
If I go over to the chat app for the other room we get both of those and this is a problem.
We also have the name problem.
Currently user displays for the text message and admin displays for the location message.
We want to make sure to use the actual user's name whether it's Jan in this case or whether it's Andrew
in order to get that done we are going to need to make some changes to both server.
J.S. Right here we have our event listeners for create message and create location message and we're
also going to be making some updates over inside of chat.
Yes and this is actually where we're going to start.
Currently the name user the incorrect name we saw over inside of the browser that comes from right here.
The client originally sent the name of this is no longer going to be the case.
The name is stored by the server.
So we're going to remove this as a required property from create message.
We're just going to be sending the text across.
Now with this in place we can modify the event listener over inside of server.
J.S. inside of server ask create message takes those two properties and it stuffs them right here into
to generate message instead we're going to find the user using.
Users not get user.
And we're going to do something with it right here.
We can go ahead and delete our council dialog statement for create message and we're going to make a
variable user setting an equal to users dot get user.
This is the method we created over here get user which takes the idea we can pass in the ID socket dot
ID and now we can do something with that user.
We only want to do something if a user actually exists which means that we're going to check if the
user exists using this statement.
And we're also going to make sure that the text that got passed along was a real string using after
and is real string and will be passing in message dot text.
This means if someone tries to send across an empty message or just a bunch of spaces it's not going
to get sent to everybody else.
Now inside of here all we're going to do is actually emit the message we know it's valid so we do want
to emit something.
We're going to take this line cut it out and paste it right here.
Now currently this line it emits to everybody not just the room the user is connected to.
And we also use message from we really want to use the name property on user.
Your challenge right now is going to be to make those two changes and this event just to the room the
user is connected to and make sure to provide their name right here as opposed to message dot from when
you're done you can refresh your browser tabs send some text messages around and you should see the
user's name as opposed to what you currently see which is the static text user.
Knock that out.
Pause the video and when you're done click play.
All right.
Getting this done requires some modifications to this line.
First up we want to get to just a specific room and we know we can tack on a to call right here to get
that done.
Passing in the room name we have access to that on the user object user dot road.
Now that we're admitting to just the individual room we also do want to change the name we use instead
of message from.
We're going to access the name on the user object user name and there we go.
Now we have a much better system for sending those text messages.
I'm going to refresh my first tab and my second tab and we're going to send some text messages around.
I'm going to send the number one right here.
And we do get Andrew and we do see the number one and over inside of our other tab the message is nowhere
to be found because we're just admitting it to users in the office fans.
But I try to send a message from this first tab.
We're going to see it here with the name Jan..
And the second tab also looks good.
We're not seeing that message from Jan..
Now I can go ahead and join a room again.
I'm going to use the name Mike.
And we're going to join the office fans one more time.
When I joined the room I do see and you and Mike both connected and if I send a message like should
work.
I see it here.
And I also see it in the tab of the other user connected to the office fans.
And once again it's not visible to someone else connected to a different room.
That is all we need to do to get our messages sending correctly.
And the last thing to do is to wire that up for create location message.
Now as we just saw we were also able to fix the validation issue if I tried to hit enter right now.
Nothing happens.
I don't get moved out of the box.
The focus doesn't change and no message is sent.
Right now I am smashing the enter key and nothing's happening which is great.
Over inside of Adam your challenge is going to be to fix create location message.
You're going to want to find the user just like we do above.
If there is a user you're going to want to admit this to just people in the same room instead of providing
admin as the name.
You're also going to want to use the user's real name.
Once you're done you can go ahead and test this out by refreshing those tabs and trying to send the
location around.
Make sure it still gets sent to users in the same room and make sure it does not get sent to users in
other rooms.
Pause the video.
Knock that out test it and when you're done go ahead and click play to do this one.
I am going to start by fetching the user since we are going to need to use the information on that object.
We're going to make a variable user calling.
Users don't get user and we're going to pass in that socket ID socket ID.
This is identical to the line that we used above.
Now we only want to emit a message if we do find a users.
I'm going to check if the user object exists.
If it does we can take this line cut it out and copy it right here if it does exist we are going to
emit new location message.
Now we do still need to emit it to just a specific room by adding on a call to two and passing in the
room name user room stores that information.
And last but not least we do want to update the name instead of sending the static admin name.
We're going to use the user's real name user dot name.
With this in place create location message is now wired up to be private and to send across the correct
information over inside of chrome.
I'm going to go through my tabs one at a time giving them a refresh and on the third tab I am going
to be sending the location.
This is going to take just a couple of seconds to actually fetch it.
And I see it right here with the name showing up.
Correct.
We have Mike and we have a link to view the location inside of Google Maps.
Now if I go to the second tab the user who is also connected to the office fans I see the exact same
location message and then I go to the first one you can see that John does not have access to that message
because she's in a different room.
She can only share her location with anybody in her room.
That happens to be nobody.
This message is not going to show up anywhere because no one else is connected to EHLO t r with that
in place we are now done.
Our messages are private.
They're only going to be visible to folks in the same room.
Let's go ahead and wrap this one up by committing our changes.
I'm going to shut down the no man server.
Use clear and we can run get status to see what kind of changes we have here we just have two files
they're modified which means we can use to get commit with the flag whether it's separate or the same.
They have identical feature sets and then we provide our message string send messages to only people
in same room.
Awesome.
With this in place we can go ahead and use get push to push this up to get hard.
And I'm also going to go ahead and deployed to Heroku using get push Heroku master once it's deployed
on Heroku we can take just a quick moment to make sure all of those features we just added are still
working as expected.
I expect they will still work but it's definitely worth checking out because the environments are little
different and there's always a chance something can go wrong.
Now something does go wrong as a reminder you can always use Heroku lags.
This is going to show you the logs on the server.
It's usually kind of cryptic but when an error occurs you're going to see a really big block.
It's usually pretty easy to spot and it usually contains useful information as to what went wrong.
It looks like our app deployed successfully so I can use Heroku open to open it up inside of my browser.
And once it's open we can actually visit some chat rooms I'm going to close down my local host tab and
I'm going to join as Andrew the room Philadelphia once I'm in the room I am going to send a message
and then I'm going to add a second user to the room.
Local host 3000 excuse me not local host.
We want to visit this Web site our Heroku app.
I'm going to visit that will join the room as victim and we can join the exact same room Philadelphia
when I join.
I see the people list updates for both and sending messages.
Does it still work.
Messages from tab to do appear in Tab 1.
This is great.
All this is possible because we wired up server J ass keeping track of users over time.
When they first join we add them to the list when they send messages we make sure to use their information
and when they leave we remove them from the list.
This ensures that the people list is always up to date and that messages are only getting sent to others
in the same room.
That's it for this one.
I will see you next time.