Now that we have our people list in place and our messages are only getting sent to the users in the
same chat room we are done.
But that doesn't mean you have to stop developing the chat app students like to add on new features
and they always post them in the Q&amp;A and it's really cool to see what people build.
I like to give you a few ideas as to what you can build right now.
You might get stuck with adding these features it might be a real pain in the butt and it might take
forever but I promise you're going to learn so much along the way and doing something on your own.
They have all the skills to do these features so let's just go down the list really quick one awesome
idea would be to make chat rooms case insensitive.
Currently if I go to EHLO TR with a lowercase are not actually in the same chat room as my friend who's
an EHLO TR uppercase r it would be nice if regardless of case we were all in the same room.
Next up I'd like to make user names unique.
Currently I can copy the R L and paste in a new tab and now I have two people with the name of jewels.
It would be cool to reject new users who also have the same name as an existing user.
Next up one idea that I was thinking about adding that would be pretty cool is to add a list of the
currently active chat rooms down below.
This could be a select dropdown.
It's going to repopulate.
Kind of like the People's list repopulate.
This is by far the hardest feature but I think it would be really cool.
That means I would see a drop down in between the join and the input box and it would have the two currently
active rooms.
Hello TR and EHLO TR with an uppercase are although hopefully if you implement that first feature we
would only see one room.
Then instead of typing in a room name I could just pick one from the dropdown type in a name and join
that way.
These are just a few ideas of how you can continue on with a chat app if you do end up adding any of
these.
I would love to see what you built.
Please post it in the Q&amp;A with a link to the Heroku application or any other link that lets me play
around with it and that's it for now.
I will see you soon