It now that you have a basic express application up and running in this one you're going to configure
your server to allow for incoming web socket connections.
This means the server will be able to accept connections and will be setting up the client to make the
connection then we'll have a persistent connection and we can send data back and forth whether it's
data from the server to the client or data from the client to the server because that is the beauty
of web sockets.
You can send data in either direction.
Now in order to set up the web sockets we're going to be using a library called socket I O.
Just like Express makes it really easy to set up an HTP server socket I O makes it dead simple to set
up a server that supports web sockets and to create a front end that communicates with the server socket
Io has a back and front end library.
We're going to be using both to set up Web sockets to get started over inside of the terminal.
Let's go ahead and install the most recent version of socket IO using NPM I the module name is socket
dot I O.
And the most recent version.
At one point four point eight we'll be using the same dev flag to update the package Chaisson file.
Once this is in place we can go ahead and make a few changes to our server file.
First up we're going to go ahead and load in the library.
I'm going to make a constant called socket.
And I'm going to set an equal to the require statement for the socket I O library with this in place.
We now need to integrate socket o into our existing web server.
Currently we use Express to make our web server.
We create a new Express app we configure our middleware and we call app.
Listen now behind the scenes Express is actually using a built in node module called HTP to create this
server.
We're going to need to use HTP ourselves configure express to work with HTP then and only then will
we also be able to add a socket I O support.
Now if that sounded like a mouthful I promise it's actually going to be pretty easy.
We only have to change a few lines to get things to work.
First up we're going to load in this module it's called HTP.
So let's make a constant called HTP.
It's a built in node module so there's no need to install it.
We can simply require HTP just like this from here.
We're going to go ahead and create a server using this HTP library just below our app variable.
Let's make a variable called server.
And what we're going to do is call HTP dot create server.
Now you might not know it but you're actually already using the Create server method behind the scenes
when you call app dot listen on your express app.
It literally calls this exact same method passing in the app as the argument for create server create
server takes a function.
This function looks really similar to one of our express callbacks.
It gets called with a request and a response.
Now as I mentioned HTP is actually used behind the scenes for Express they're integrated so much so
that you can actually provide the app as the argument.
And we are done now before we integrate socket I'll just go ahead and wrap up this change.
We're now using the HTP server as opposed to the Express server.
So instead of calling app listen we're going to call server listen once again.
There's no need to change the arguments passed in here.
They're exactly the same they're built really closely to each other.
So the server listen arguments are the same as the Express app lesson method arguments.
Now that we have this in place we haven't actually changed any app functionality.
Our server is still going to work on port three thousand but we're still not going to have access to
socket.
So over in the terminal I can prove this by clearing the terminal output and starting up our server
using gnomon gnomon server forward slash server.
J.S. and I'm just going to load localhost 3000 in the browser and see what I get back right here.
What do we get.
We get our HTL.
Welcome to the chat app shows up.
This means that our app is still working even though we're now using the HTP server.
The next thing that we're going to do is configure the server to also use socket I O.
That's the entire reason we made this change on the next line.
We're going to make a variable called I O we'll talk about that in just a second.
We're going to set it equal to a call to socket I O.
And we're going to pass in the server that we want to use with our web sockets.
Right.
Here we have access to that server via the server variable so we'll pass that in as the first and only
argument.
Now when we get back is our web sockets server on here we can do anything we want in terms of emitting
or listening to events.
This is how we're going to communicate between the server and the client and we'll talk more about that
in just a second.
With this in place our server is ready to go.
We are ready to accept new connections.
The problem is we don't have any connections to accept when we load our Web page we're not doing anything.
We're not actually connecting to the server and we are going to need to manually run some javascript
code to initiate that connection process.
Now when we integrated socket I O with our server we actually got access to a few cool things.
First up we got access to a route that accepts incoming connections which means that we can now accept
web socket connections and we got access to a javascript library that makes it really easy to work with
socket I O on the client.
This library is available at the following path forward slash socket I O board slash socket dot I O
dot J.
S If you load this javascript file on the browser you can see it's just a really long javascript library.
This contains all of the code we're going to need on the client to make the connection and to transfer
data whether it's server at a client or client to server.
But we're going to do in order to make the connection from our HTL file is load this in I'm going to
go back to localhost 3000 and now we can go ahead and move into Adam opening up index.
H DML and down near the bottom of the body tag we're going to add a script tag loading in the file we
just pulled up in the browser.
First up will make the script tag itself.
Opening and closing it.
And in order to load in an external file We're going to use the source attribute providing the path.
Now this path is relative to our server.
It's going to be a forward slash socket I go forward slash socket Dom IO.
J Yes exactly as we typed in the browser just moments ago by adding the script tag we're now loading
in the library and on the browser we have access to all sorts of methods available because of the socket
library one of those methods is going to let us initiate a connection request and that's exactly what
we're going to do down below.
Let's add a second script to tag this time instead of loading an external script.
We're going to write some javascript right in line right in here we can add any javascript and this
javascript is going to run right after the socket IO library loads a little bit later on we'll be breaking
this out into its own file but for the moment we can simply have our javascript code right inside of
our h tim l file right here but we're going to do is call I O I O is a method available to us because
we loaded in this library.
It's not native to the browser.
And when we call it we're actually initiating the request we're making a request from the client to
the server to open up a web socket and keep that connection open.
Now what we get back from Iowa is really important.
We're going to want to save that in a variable called socket just like this.
This creates our connection and it stores the socket in a variable and this variable is critical to
communicating.
It's exactly what we need in order to listen for data from the server.
And in order to send data to the server now that we have this in place let's go ahead and save our TNL
file.
We're going to move into the browser and we're going to open up the chrome developer tools.
Now regardless of what browser you use whether it's IEEE Safari Firefox or chrome you're going to have
access to a set of developer tools which makes it really easy to debug and see what's going on behind
the scenes in your web page.
We're going to be using the chrome developer tools here to do a little debugging.
I'd highly recommend using Chrome for these videos just so you can follow along exactly.
To open up the developer tools we go to settings more tools developer tools.
You can also use the keyboard shortcut as shown here for your operating system.
When you open developer tools you're going to be greeted with an overwhelming set of options you're
most likely brought to the elements panel if you've never used the developer tools before the panel
we're going to be using right now is the network panel.
The network panel keeps track of all of the requests made by your web page.
So if I make a request for a javascript file I'm going to see that in a nice list here.
We're going to have to refresh the page in order to see the list of network requests.
And right here we have six the network request at the very top is the first one that was made and the
one at the very bottom is the last one that was made.
The first one was for the page you see here it's for the H T and L file that loads Welcome to the chat
app.
The second one is for that javascript file that we saw in the browser.
This gives us the library and gives us access to calling that I O method which starts the connection
process the next four are all related to starting up and maintaining that connection with this in place.
We now have that live connection between the client and the server and we can start communicating whatever
we want to communicate.
Now this communication could be anything at all.
This comes in the form of an event.
Events can be emitted from either the client or the server and either the client or the server can listen
for events.
Let's talk about an event that might happen in an e-mail app in an email app.
For example the server might emit an event called new e-mail when a new e-mail comes in.
The client is then going to listen for that event when it fires it'll get the new e-mail data and it
will render the e-mail to the screen below the other ones.
The same thing could happen the other way maybe the client wants to create a new e-mail and send it
to someone else.
It's going to ask for the e-mail address of the person and the message it's then going to emit an event
on the client that the server is going to listen to.
So this whole server client relationship is entirely ran via these events.
Now we're going to be creating custom events for our specific application throughout this section.
But for now we're going to look at a couple of different ones that are built in that let you keep track
of new users and disconnecting users.
This means we'll be able to do something like greet a user when they join our application in order to
play around with this over inside of Adam inside of server Dom.
J.S. we are going to call a method on I O.
I o dot on I O dot on lets you register an event Lessner we can listen for a specific event and do something
when that event happens.
One built in event that we're going to use the most popular one is called connection.
This lets you listen for a new connection meaning that a client connected to the server and it lets
you do something when that connection comes in in order to do something you provide a callback function
as the second argument and this callback function is going to get called with a socket.
The socket argument is really similar to the socket argument we have access to over inside an index.
HTL this represents the individual socket as opposed to all of the users connected to the server.
Now with this in place we can do whatever we like.
For example I could use council that like to print a little message.
New user connected every time a user connects to our app we're going to print a message to the con.
I'm going to go ahead and save the server japes file move into the terminal and you're going to see
that the message actually already exists to explain why we need to understand one thing about web sockets
web sockets.
As I mentioned they are a persistent technology meaning that the client and server they both keep the
communication channel open for as long as both of them want to if the server shuts down the client doesn't
really have a choice.
And the same thing for the client and server relationship.
And I close a browser tab the server cannot force me to keep the connection open.
Now when a connection drops the client it's still going to try to reconnect when we restart the server
using gnomon.
There's about a quarter of a second of time where the servers down and the client notices that it says
well 00 server went down let's try to reconnect and eventually it reconnects.
And that's why we're seeing the message right here.
New user connected.
I'm going to go ahead and shut down the server and over inside of the client.
You're going to see that network requests are being made right here.
We're trying to reconnect to the server and you can see they're failing because the server is not up.
Now if we go back into the terminal and we restart the server over inside of the client We're going
to try to reconnect again.
We're going to get a successive result from the server and boom we are back just like that.
Now when we reconnect you can see that we get the message over here and that's why we saw it when we
first added it to the server DHHS file.
Now the connection of that also exists over in the client.
That means on the client we can do something when we successfully connect to the server.
It might not happen right away.
It might take a little time over inside of Adam.
We can add this event inside of index HTL right below our call to.
Oh right here we're going to call Sacket dot on we want to listen for an event and this event is a little
different than the one we have here.
It's not on connection.
It's on CONNECT THE on method here is exactly the same as the one we use in server.
J.S. the first argument is the event name and the second argument.
That is the callback function.
In this case we don't get access to a socket argument since we already have it right here called socket.
In this case all I'm going to do is use console dialog to print a little message to the console connected
to server.
Awesome.
Now that we have this in place we can go into the browser and go to a new tab in the developer tools.
We're going to load the console tab the console tab is kind of like the terminal inside of node.
If we use cancel that log in our client side javascript code those messages are going to show up here.
As you can see we also have some errors these errors occurred when our server was down as I was showing
you how it reconnects.
But if we refreshed the page as you're going to see connected to server shows up right here as soon
as the connection happens the client and the server they both had that event fired the client prints
connected to server and the server prints new user connected with this in place we've now used the event
system in socket.
So we haven't set our own custom events but we have taken advantage of some built in ones.
The last thing we're going to talk about in this video is the disconnect event which lets you do something
on both the server and the client when the connection drops.
We're going to add an event listener on the client together and your challenge will be to do the same
thing on the server on the client.
Down below our connect event we can call socket on again to listen to a new event.
Once again the name of the event here is the name of a built in event.
So it's only going to work if you type it correctly.
This one is called Disconnect the disconnect event is going to fire when ever the connection drops.
If the server goes down the client is going to be able to do something for now that something is just
going to be Lague a message console log unable to connect.
Actually on cable is the incorrect terminology disconnected.
From server.
Much clearer now that we had this message in place.
We can actually save our index.
TMF I'll go over to the browser and we can give it a refreshed to load in our new javascript file.
I'm going to go ahead and make my browser screen just a little bit smaller so he can see it in the background
of the terminal.
I'm going to go to the terminal.
I'm going to shut down the connection by shutting down the server.
And over inside of the browser what do we get.
We get disconnected from server printing to the screen.
If I restart my server over inside of the terminal you can see we've automatically connected and connected
to server prints to the screen.
Now the exact same event exists on the server.
We can listen for a disconnecting client and we can do something when they leave in order to register
this event.
You are going to go into server dot J.S. and inside of our callback you're going to call socket dot
on just like we do right here.
It's the exact same signature.
The first argument is the event name it's the disconnect event and the callback function should do something
simple like print client disconnected.
Once you have that in place what I want you to do is open up the browser and open up the terminal then
close the browser tab and you should see the message print in the server whatever message you happen
to type here try to open up another browser tab close that one and make sure you get the same message.
This message should print every time one of your browser tabs closes assuming that browser tab had an
open connection socket dot on is your challenge.
Take a moment to knock this out.
Test it.
And when you're done click play
right all you needed to do was copy the exact same signature as we used here socket.
On takes two arguments the first one is the name.
Disconnect is the event name we're trying to listen to.
And the second argument is the function to run when the event fires.
This means the function to run when a socket is disconnected.
In this case all we're going to do is use console dialog to print user was disconnected just like this
and we're going to save the file which is automatically going to restart our application.
I'm going to switch to the terminal and then to the browser so I can see the terminal in the background.
I'm going to open up a new tab.
So when I close this one the chrome browser doesn't close completely.
I'm going to close the tab with open connection and right here inside of the terminal we got user was
disconnected.
If I open up a new tab and go to a local host 3000 live right as I do it new user connected Prince.
And as soon as I close it bam on the server user it was disconnected prints to the screen.
Hopefully you're starting to see why web sockets are so awesome that instant two way communication makes
any sort of realtime application effortless to build in the next video.
We're going to get into the very very interesting stuff you're going to learn how to emit and listen
to custom events.
This means you can send any data you like from the server to the client and vice versa.
Let's wrap this one up with a comment.
I'm going to shut down our server run and get status and I can see we only have modified files.
So get commit with the M flag is going to get the job done right here we can add our message and connect
and disconnect event handlers.
Awesome.
I'm going to make the commit and push it up to get hub.
There's no need to deploy to Heroku just yet.
With that in place we are done.
I'll see you in the next one.