In the last video you learn how to listen to those built in events things like connection events and
disconnection events.
Those are fine.
There are a great starting place but in this video what we want to talk about is a meeting and listening
to custom events.
And this is where socket IO gets really interesting when you're able to emit and listen to custom events
you can send anything you want from the server to the client or from the client to the server.
Now to go through a quick example of how that a look we're going to use an example app an email application
on the left.
We have our server.
This is starting up a socket IO web server on the right we have our email app which is showing a list
of all our current emails.
Now one customer that not our app might require is a new e-mail event the new e-mail event is going
to get emitted by the server when an e-mail comes in from someone else.
For example I sign up to a new service that service sends me an e-mail to confirm my e-mail.
The server eventually gets that e-mail and it emits an event that the client listens to.
The client is going to listen for the new e-mail event and it'll be able to rerun her the list of e-mails
in the browser using Jay query react Amber or whatever library it happens to be using showing the new
e-mail to the user.
Now aside from just sending that in the event happened the most important piece to the puzzle is sending
data and we can actually do that when you create and emit a custom event you can send whatever information
you like from the server to the client or from the client to the server.
Usually this takes the form of an object with various properties.
In the case of getting a new e-mail I might want to know who the emails from.
I definitely need to know the text of the e-mail.
And I also want to know when the e-mail arrived at my server so I can render that inside of the browser
for whoever happens to be using the email app.
Now this is data flowing from the server to the client which is something we were not able to accomplish
with H-2 requests but it is something we can accomplish using socket I O.
Now another event this one create e-mail is going to flow from the client to the server.
When I create a new email inside of my web browser I'm going to need to emit that event from the client
and the server is going to listen for that event.
Once again we are going to be sending some data across.
Although the data will be a little different.
We want to know who the e-mail needs to get sent to.
We need the text of the e-mail and maybe you want to schedule it for down the line.
So a scheduled time stamp field could be used.
Obviously these are all example fields fields for a real email app would probably be a little different
with this in place though we are ready to go ahead and actually create these two events inside of our
application.
Your challenge which will come a little later in the course is going to be to create custom events not
for an email app but for our messenger application.
Well let's try then starting with new email and create email before we start emitting or listening to
custom events.
Let's go out and make a few tweaks to our client side javascript as you might have noticed in the last
video I accidentally used.
Yes 6 arrow functions inside of our client side javascript code.
And as I mentioned we want to avoid this.
The project is going to work correctly in Chrome but if you tried to load this up on your mobile phone
Internet Explorer or Safari or some versions of Firefox the program is going to crash.
So instead of using aero functions we're going to use regular functions by removing the arrow and adding
the function keyword before our arguments.
I'm going to do this for our on that connect listener and for the on disconnect listener.
Adding the function keyword and removing the arrow.
I'm also going to take our javascript and move it into a separate file instead of editing the client
side javascript to write inside of our HVM file without a separate file where that code lives.
This is the better method for getting things done over in public.
We can make a new folder for this javascript file.
I'm going to make one called J as will have multiple javascript files by the time this apps over.
So it's a good idea to create a folder to house all of those.
For now though we just need one index dot J.S. index dot japes is going to load when we load index dot
h DML it's going to contain all of the JavaScript required to get this page to work starting with the
javascript we wrote down below.
I'm going to cut out all of the code in the script tag pasted into index.
J S.
We can save the file and update our script tag instead of having the code in line.
We're going to load it in by providing the source attribute with the path to the file.
Lord slash ass forward slash index dot J.
Excellent.
Now that we have this in place we have the exact same functionality we had before.
Only this time around the Javascript has been broken out into its own file.
I'm going to start up the server using man server forward slash server J S.
Once it's up we can go ahead and load the app by go into the browser and opening up localhost three
thousand.
I'm going to open up the developer tools as well so we can make sure everything is working as expected
and inside of the console we see connected to server is still printing.
This is code that exists in index.
Yes and the very fact that it's showing up here proves that the file was loaded with this in place we
can now move on to our custom events.
Now we have two events that we talked about for our example email application.
We have new e-mail which is from the server to the client and we have create email which is an event
emitted by the client and listened to by the server.
We're going to get started with new email and to kick things off.
We're going to head into our client side javascript and we're going to listen for that and that when
that event fires we want to do something we want to take the data we want to use.
Jay Querrey react or some other front end framework to render it to the browser so the user can see
the email as soon as it comes in.
Now in order to listen to a custom event we are still going to use socket dot on although instead of
specifying the name of one of the built in events we are going to inside of quotes provide the first
argument as the name of our custom event.
In this case that name is going to be new uppercase the email.
Now the second argument for socket on is the same as the second argument for the built in event listeners
were going to provide a function and this function is going to get called when the event fires.
For now all we're going to do inside of here is use console log to print a little message.
New email this is going to print inside of the Web Developer console.
Every time the client hears this event coming across the pipeline now that we have the listener in place
for new e-mail let's go ahead and emit this event over inside of server.
J.S. in here what we want to do is call a method on socket socket has a method called emet we're going
to use emit on both the client and the server to emit events and emit is really similar to the listeners
although instead of listening to an event we are creating the event.
The first argument is the same it's going to be the name of the event you want to admit.
In this case we have to match it exactly as we specified over here.
New email right here we're going to provide a new e-mail.
Now this is not a listener so we're not going to provide a callback function but we want to do is specify
the data now by default.
We don't have to specify any data.
Maybe we just want to emit new e-mail without anything letting the browser know that something happened.
If we do this over inside of the browser we can refresh the app.
And what do we get in the terminal.
We get new e-mail right here.
The event is still happening even though we're not sending across any customer data.
If you do want to send custom data which is most likely the case it's super easy.
All you have to do is provide a second argument for email.
Now you could provide an argument of three or true or anything else but most commonly you want to send
multiple pieces of data across.
So an object is going to be your second argument.
This is going to let you specify anything you like.
In our case we might specify who the emails from.
By specifying a from attribute It's from Mike an example dot com mania we also have the text for the
email.
Hey what is going on and we might have other attributes as well for example created it could be a time
stamp of when the server got the email.
This data this data is going to get sent along with the new e-mail event from the server to the client.
Now I'm going to go ahead and save server dot J S and over inside of our client side javascript.
We can go ahead and do something with that data.
The data that's emitted with your event is provided as the first argument to your callback function.
Here we have our callback function for a new e-mail which means we can name the first argument email
and we can do whatever we want with it.
We might be appending it to a list of emails in a real web app but for our purposes right now all we're
going to do is provide it as the second argument to console log rendering it to the screen.
With this in place we can now test that everything is working as expected.
If I go to the browser and give things a refresh using command are we see over inside of the console.
We have our new e-mail and Double-O we have our object we can click it to expand it and we see all of
the properties we specified.
We have our from property the TX property are created at property which is misspelled.
All of it is showing up as expected and this is fantastic.
In real time we were able to pass not only an event but event data from the server to the client which
is something we could never do with an HTP a P.
Now on the other side of things we have a situation where we want to emit an event from the client sending
some data to the server.
This is for our create email event.
Now in this case we are going to add our event listener inside of server.
J.S. using socket dot on it just like we do for any other event listener like we have right here.
The Odon on method were used for the connection event is a very special event.
You will usually not be attaching anything to I know you're not going to make calls to Odon on or I
O admit other than the one we have here are custom event listeners are going to happen down below by
calling socket data on like we do for disconnect.
Passing in the name of the event you want to listen to.
In this case it is the create email event.
Now for create email we do want to add a listener.
We are in our node code so we can use an arrow function and we're probably going to expect some data
the email to create so we can name that first argument.
This is going to be the data center law with the event.
I'm going to call this new e-mail and for this example we're going to do is print it to the council
so we can make sure the event is properly going from client to server console dialog.
I'm going to log out the event name it create e-mail and as the second argument I'm going to log out
the data so I can view it over here in the terminal and make sure everything works as expected.
Now we have a listener in place and our server did restart but we're never actually emitting the event
on the client.
We can go ahead and fix this by calling socket dot emet.
Now I'm going to call it right here inside of our connect callback function.
I don't want to admit the event until we are connected socket.
And Mitt is going to let me do just that right here.
I can call socket document and meeting the event the event name is create email and we can pass any
data we like in as the second argument.
In the case of an email app we're probably going to need to send it to someone.
So we'll have to address something like Jan at example dot com.
We're going to need some text obviously.
Hey this is Andrew.
And we might have other properties like subject but for now we're going to stick with just these two.
So what we've done here is we've created a client side script that connects to the server and as soon
as it connects it emits this create e-mail event.
Now this is not a realistic example in a real world app a user is most likely going to fill out a form.
You're going to grab these pieces of data from the form and then you're going to emit it.
We will be working with HVM all farms a little later.
For now though we're just calling socket data to play around with these custom events.
I'm going to save index dot J.S. over inside of the browser we can now give the page a refresh as soon
as it connects.
It's going to emit that event.
And right here in the terminal you see create email printing.
The event was emitted from the client to the server the server got the data and all is well.
Now another cool thing about the console is we have access to the variables created by our application.
Most notably this socket variable which means inside of Google Chrome in the developer Council we can
call socket dot emit and we could emit whatever we like I can emit an action create email I can pass
in some data as the second argument and object where I have a from or excuse me a to attribute equal
to Julie at example dot com and I have my other attributes to something like text setting that equal
to hey this is an example of how we can use the developer Council to make debugging our app even easier.
Right here I can type a statement hit enter.
It's going to go ahead and fire that emitting the event.
And over inside of the terminal we're going to get that event and do something with it whether it's
creating the e-mail or doing anything else we might require.
And right here inside of the terminal you can see create e-mail showed up where sending that one to
Julie.
And here's the text.
Hey it all got to the server from the client.
Now that we have this in place and we've played around with how we can use these custom events it's
time to move from the e-mail application onto the actual app.
We're going to be building new chat application and to talk about what you're going to do for the challenge.
We're going to head back into the presentation for just a few seconds.
Now that you know how to emit and listen to custom advance we're going to move on to your challenge
which is going to be to create two events that we'll actually use in the chat application.
These are going to be new message and create message.
Now for the chat app once again we have our server which is going to be the server we build and we have
our client which is going to be a user who is in the chat application there is most likely going to
be multiple users who all want to communicate with each other.
Now the first event we're going to have is a new message event and this is going to get emitted by the
server and listened to on the client.
When a new message comes in the server is going to send it to everyone connected to the chat room so
they can display it to the screen and a user can go ahead and respond to it.
The new message event is going to require some data.
We're going to need to know who the message was from a string of someone's name like a string.
Andrew the text of the message is something like Hey can you meet up at 6:00 and they created at timestep
all of this data is going to get rendered inside of our chat application in the browser.
We'll be doing that for real in a little bit.
But for now we're just going to print it to the council.
So this is the first event I want you to create.
You're going to make this new message event you're going to omit it from the server.
For now you can simply admit it when a user connects and you're going to listen to it on the client.
And for now on the client you can just print with Cancel that log a little message when you get the
data.
You can say got new message printing the object that got passed with this data.
Next up the second event we're going to work with this create message.
This is going to come from the client to the server.
So if I'm user one I'm going to fire a create message event from my browser.
This is going to go to the server and the server is going to fire New Message Events to everyone else
so they can see my message which means the create message event is gonna get emitted from the client
and the server is going to be the one who's listening for the event.
Now this event is also going to require some data.
We're going to need to know who the message was from and also the text what did they want to say.
We need both of these pieces of information.
Now notice a discrepancy here.
We're sending the from text and created app properties to the client but we're not asking for a created
at property from the client when they create a message.
This created that property it's actually going to get created on the server.
This is going to prevent the user from being able to spoof the time the message was created at There's
certain properties we're going to trust the user to provide us.
There's others that we will not trust them to provide us in one of those is going to be created at now
for create message to do this challenge.
All you have to do is set up an event listener on the server that waits for this to fire.
And once again you can simply print a message like create message and then and you can provide to counsel
dialog.
The data that got passed along printing it to the terminal.
Now once you have that listener in place you're going to want to admit it.
You can admit it when the user first connects and you can also fire a couple socket emit calls from
the chrome developer tools making sure that all of the messages show up in the terminal takes some time
to knock that one out it's going to take a little bit of time.
You can also remove all of the previous event listeners and event emitters that we created for our e-mail
events.
We're not going to actually need those.
Those were just for example purposes.
Now this is the set up video in the next video I'll show you how to solve this challenge since this
one's getting a little long.
And I want to keep these under 20 minutes.
Take some time to knock this out.
Test it.
Make sure everything works as expected and when you're done move on to the next video we're I'll show
you how to get this done.