This video is the solution video for the challenge.
I set up in the end of the last one if you missed that go back in re watch it make sure to complete
the challenge.
Then you can watch this one where I show you how to get it done.
Now in that challenge I told you I wanted you to create two events a new message event emitted by the
server and listened to on the client and a create message of that emitted by the client and listened
to by the server.
We're going to get started inside of server dot J.S. by listening for that create message event.
And this is going to happen down below.
Now we have an old event listener from create email you can remove that and we can call socket dot on
it to listen to our brand new event create message to create message that is going to require a function
to call when the event actually happens.
We're going to want to do something with the message data for the moment.
All you needed to do was use council dot like to print it to the terminal so we can verify that everything
worked as expected.
We're going to get our message data.
This is going to include a from property and a Text property and we're going to print it to the screen.
You don't have to specify the exact message I used.
I'm just going to say create message.
And the second argument will be the data that was passed from the client to the server.
Now that we have our listener in place we can go ahead and emit this over inside of the client in index
dot J.
Yes.
Now currently we have an emit call right here.
I'm going to go ahead and remove this emit call.
We're going to call socket dot emit and we're going to go ahead and emit create message.
We're going to emit create message with the necessary data.
Remember when you're emitting a custom event the first argument is the event name and the second is
the data.
We're going to provide an object with two properties from who is it from.
This one's from Andrew and of the actual text of the message that could be anything like yup that works
for me.
This is going to be the event we admit.
I'm going to save index dot J as head over to the browser and we should be able to refresh the app and
see the data right here.
And inside of the terminal we have create message with the from property we specified and the text Yep
that works for me.
Now we can also emit events right here from the developer tools to play around with socket IO socket
doddy and we can emit any event we like passing in some data.
The event we're going to emit is create message and the data is a from attribute this one one's from
Jen and a text attribute.
Nope.
When I send this off instantly in real time the message shows up on the server.
Right here you can see it's from Jan..
The text is nope everything is working as expected.
Now that's the first event.
The other one is the new message event which is going to get emitted by the server and listened to by
the client to get started with this one we'll add our event listener inside an index.
J.S. we have the old event listener for new email.
I'm going to go ahead and remove that and we'll call socket on it to listen to the new event.
New Message new message is going to require a callback to the moment.
We'll be using council that log to print the message to the console but later we'll be taking this message
and we'll be adding it to the browser.
So a user can actually see it in the screen.
Now we are going to get some data.
We're going to get the message data.
I'll create an argument called message for the moment and we can go ahead and simply log it to the screen
using a console lag printing the name of the event.
So it's easy to track in the terminal and the actual data that was passed from server to client.
Now the last thing we need to do to complete this challenge was simply a new message from the server
making sure it shows up in the client over inside of server dot Jay ass instead of emitting new e-mail.
We will call socket dot emit emitting our custom event new message now we are going to need some data.
We're going to need that message data.
We're going to provide that as the second argument.
It will be an object with a from property from.
It could be from whoever you like.
I'm going to go with John.
Next up we're going to go ahead and provide the text property.
This can be anything as well.
See you then.
And finally we're going to provide that created at property.
This is going to be generated by the server later so a user can't spoof the time a message was created
at.
But for now we'll just use some sort of random number like 1 2 3 1 2 3.
Now as soon as a user connects to the server we're going to be emitting that event over inside of the
browser.
I can go ahead and refresh things.
And what do we see we have our new message of that showing up and the data is exactly as we specified
it in our server.
JS file.
We have our created out time stamp our from property and our text property in the future will be literally
taking this data and rendering it into the browser so it shows up and someone can read it and respond
to it.
But for now we are done.
We have our event listener on the server for create message.
And our event listener on the client for new message.
That is it for this one since we are done we will be making a quick commit.
I'm going to shut down the server and run get status.
We have quite a few changes here.
We have our new J.S. file and the public JS folder and we've also changed server dot J.S. and index
HVM out.
I'm going to run it get add dot to add all of that to the next commit then I'll create a commit using
get commit with the M flag and a good message for this one is ad new message and create message events.
Excellent.
With this in place we can now push our code up to get hub.
There is no need to do anything with Heroku since we don't have anything visual just yet.
We'll hold off on that for a bit later.
And that's it for this one in the next video we're going to wire up messages.
So when tab one emits a message it's visible by tab 2.
This is going to bring us one step closer to actually communicating in real time between different browser
tabs.
Stay tuned I will see you then