Now that we have our customer event listeners any imitators in place it's time to actually wire up the
message system.
So when one user sends a message to the server it actually gets sent to every connected user.
If I have two tabs open and I emit a create message event from one tab I should see the message arrive
in the second one.
Now to test things locally we're going to be using separate tabs but the same would work on Heroku with
separate browsers on separate networks.
As long as everyone has the same you are all in their browser.
They are going to be connected regardless of which machine they're on.
Now obviously for local hosts we don't have that privilege.
But as we deployed to Heroku which we will be doing in this video we'll be able to test this out between
say your phone and the browser running on your machine to get started.
We're going to update the create message listener.
Currently all we do is log the data to the screen instead of just logging it.
We actually want to emit a new event a new message event to everybody.
So every single connected user gets the message that was sent from a specific user in order to get that
done.
We're going to call a method on I O I know dot emit socket data it emits an event to a single connection
i o data emit emits an event to every single connection here.
We're going to emit the event new message specifying it as our first argument and the second argument
as with socket data.
MIT is the data you want to send.
Now we know we're getting a from property and a Text property from the client.
Those appear right here.
Which means what we need to do is pass those along setting from equal to message dot from and setting
text equal to a message dot text.
Now alongside of Freman text we're also going to specify a created app property and this is going to
get generated by the server to prevent a specific client from spoofing when a message was created.
Created that gets set equal to a new date.
And we're going to call the get time method to get that time stamp back which we've done before.
Now that we have this in place we actually have messaging wired up.
We can go ahead and remove our emit calls from both server dot J S and index dot.
J.S. Right here make sure to save both files in with this in place we can go ahead and test this by
opening up two connections to the server and emitting some events.
I'm going to start up a server inside of the terminal using node Amman's server forward slash server
J.S. and inside of the browser we can now open up two tabs both at localhost three thousand for both
tabs I am going to open up the developer tools since that's currently the graphic user interface for
our application.
We don't have any forms just yet.
Which means we need to use the council to run some statements we'll do the same thing for a second tab
and notice that as soon as we open that second tab we get a second new user connected message in the
terminal.
You should be seeing this message when you have your two tabs open.
Now that we have our two tabs open we can go ahead and emit a create message event from either one.
I'm going to emit it from the second one by calling socket Datti MIT emitting a custom event.
The event name is create message and it takes those two props.
We just discussed the from property and the taxed property both of which I'm going to specify in this
object from is going to get set equal to my first name.
Andrew and text is going to get set equal to inside of quotes.
This should work with this in place.
I can now admit my event from the browser.
It's going to go to the server which is going to send the message to every connected user including
the currently connected user who sent the message.
I'm going to hit enter it fires it off and you see we get new message right here we have the message
we just created.
But the cool thing is that over in the other tab We also have the message a message from one user reached
a user in a separate tab which is fantastic.
With this in place we don't have a very basic messaging system set up a user emits an event.
It goes to the server and the server sends it to everyone else who is connected with this in place.
I'd like to make a commit and deployed to Heroku so we can test it out.
We're not done yet.
We are going to set up a few more things and do a challenge but there's no reason we can't commit twice
in one video.
If I run get status I see I have my two changed files as expected I can then run get commit with the
AM flag to specify a message for this commit something like emit new message on create message will
get the job done.
I can then go ahead and actually make the commit.
Pushing it up to both get hub and Heroku get push is going to get it on get hub and get push Heroku
master is going to deploy it alive to the Web and you'll be able to open up our chat application and
make sure it works regardless of the browser computer or any other variable.
Here we go.
We are compressing and launching the app.
It looks like everything is done.
I'm going to go ahead and use Heroku open to open it up.
This is going to open it up in my default browser and right you see we have.
Welcome to the chat application.
Now to demo this what I'm going to do is open up a separate browser window open up Firefox and type
in the exact same.
You are all going to copy this you Aurel then I'll grab the Firefox browser and making it smaller so
we can quickly switch between the two opening up the Heroku app here.
Now Firefox also has developer tools available via this menu.
Here we have a developer section and we're looking for the web at cons. Now that we have this open we
can go into the developer tools for our chrome tab connected to the Heroku application.
And what we're going to do is he met an event using socket daily MIT.
We're going to even get a create a message event.
We're going to specify our custom properties inside of the object.
We can go ahead and have from set to like and we can set the text equal to Heroku.
Now when I go ahead and emit this that everything should work as expected.
Calling socket data emit emitting create message.
We have our data which means it's going to go to the Heroku server which will send it over to Firefox.
I'm going to send this off.
We get the new message right here.
And over inside of Firefox we also have the message.
It's from Mike.
The text is Heroku and we have the created at time stamp added by our server.
And with this in place we have a messaging system that only working locally but working on Heroku which
means anybody in the world can visit this you are l they can emit the event and everyone else connected
is going to see that event in the council.
Now that we've tested it out across browser I am going to close down Firefox and we're going to move
on to the second part of this video which is talking about a different way to emit events.
Some events you want to send to everybody a new message should go to every single user including the
one who sent it so it can show up inside of the list of messages.
Other events on the other hand should only go to other people.
So if user one admits an event it shouldn't go back to user want it should only go to user 2 and 3.
A good example of this is when a user joins a chat room I want to print a little message like Andrew
joined when someone joins and I want to print a message like welcome Andrew for the actual user who
joined.
So in this tab I would see welcome Andrew and over here I would see Andrew joined in order to get that
done.
We're going to look at a different way to meet events in the server.
This is going to get done via broadcasting.
Broadcasting is the term for a meeting and event to everybody but one specific user I'm going to start
up the server once again using gnomon server.
Forward slash server.
J.S. and over inside of atom we can now tweak how we emit the event right here.
Now this is going to be the final way we do things but we'll play around with broadcasting as well which
means I'm going to comment this out as opposed to removing it to broadcast.
We have to specify the individual socket.
This lets the socket IO library know which user shouldn't get the event.
In this case the user that we call right here is not going to get the event everyone else will.
Now we need to call socket daat broadcast broadcast as an object that has its own emet function and
its the exact same syntax as I o data MIT or socket data.
The big difference is who it gets sent to.
This is going to send the event to everybody but this socket which means if I fire a create message
event the new message event will fire to everybody but myself and thats exactly what we can do here.
Its going to be identical which means we can go ahead and pass in the message event name.
The arguments are going to be identical.
The first one is going to be the event name new message and the other one is going to be the object
with our properties from equals message dot from text equals message dot text.
And last up we have created at equal to a new time stamp new date dot yet time with this in place we
are not going to see the messages we send but everybody else will.
We can prove this by heading over to google chrome.
I'm going to give both tabs a refresh and from the second tab once again we are going to emit an event
and we can actually use the up arrow key inside of the Web Developer console to rerun one of our previous
commands and that's exactly what I'm going to do here we're emitting a create message event with a from
property set to and you add a text equal to.
This should work.
If I hit enter to send this off you're going to notice that this tab no longer receives the message.
But if I go to localhost three 3000 we are getting new message showing up with the message data.
This is because tab to broadcasted the event which means it only got received by other connections such
as tap one or any other connected user with broadcasting in place it's time to set up your challenge.
Now as I mentioned we're not going to actually use broadcast in this context.
We're going to comment this out.
So you have it for reference during the challenge and we're going to uncomment our old code.
This is going to be the final way we emit messages.
Your challenge is going to be to emit two events right here right.
When a user connects you're going to first call socket emit to emit a message to the user who joined
your message should come from the admin from admin.
And the text should say something like welcome to the chat app.
Now along with Sacket data you're also going to call socket.
Broadcast dot emit.
This is going to get sent to everybody but the user who joined which means you can go ahead and set
from equal to admin once again and you can set text equal to new user joint.
This means that when we join a chat room we're going to see a message greeting us and everyone else
is going to see a message letting them know that someone else joined both of these events are going
to be new message events just like we met one right here.
We're going to have to specify from which is admen the text which is whatever I said it should be and
created at.
Go ahead and add those two statement calls here then go ahead and test it in the browser.
Close your tabs open one then open a second one.
The second one it should see the greeting and the first one should see the alert that a new user joined.
Take a moment to knock this out.
Test it in when you're done click play.
Hopefully that went well and you were able to get both of those calls working as expected to kick things
off.
We're going to fill out the first call.
This is a call to socket data MIT and this call is going to be responsible for greeting the individual
user.
We are still going to send an event of a type new message and we are still going to send the exact same
data from text and created at the only difference here is that we're going to be generating all of the
properties as opposed to getting some of them from the user like we do below.
Let's get started with from this one is going to be from the admin.
Any time we send a message via the server we'll call that admin and the text is going to be our little
message.
Welcome to the chat app.
Later on we'll greet them by name.
We don't have the information for the moment.
So we're going to stick with a generic greeting with this call in place we can remove the comment and
we can move onto the second one.
This is our broadcast call that's going to alert every other user except for the one who joined that
someone new is here to get that done.
We're going to use socket dot broadcast Umit and we're going to emit a new message event providing our
props from once again is going to get set equal to the string admin.
The text is going to get set equal to our little message.
New User joined and later on will also be adding a user name here but for now we'll keep it generic
and last up is created at which I forgot.
Up above created app is going to get set equal to a new date by calling the date get time method with
the date in place for this call.
We'll also add it for the one above.
Excellent.
Now we can remove our comment for the second call and we are done.
The challenge everything should work as expected.
The next thing you needed to do was test out that all of this is working as expected by heading into
the browser.
There's a couple ways you could have done it as long as you got it done.
It doesn't really matter.
I'm going to choose to close both of my old tabs I'm then going to open up the developer tools before
ever visiting the page.
Then we can go to localhost three thousand.
And we should see a little message right here.
Here we see a new message welcome into the chat app printing which is fantastic.
Next up we want a test that the broadcast is working as expected.
For the second tab I'm also going to open up the developer tools.
I'm going to go to localhost three thousand once again and once again we get our little message.
Welcome to the chat app.
If we go to the first tab We also see that a new user joined and this is fantastic.
With this in place we don't have a rudimentary but working messaging system which is a great place to
start.
We're going to continue on in the next video adding more features and building out the UI.
But before we do that I am going to make a commit to save these changes.
Let's go ahead and shut down the server and use get status.
Then we can go ahead and run it get commit with the flag and specify a message right here.
Greet new user and alert others.
Once the commit is in place we can use get pushed to push it up to get a job.
There's no need to deploy to Heroku right now although you could easily deploy and test if you feel
so inclined.
With this in place we are now done.
I will see you in the next one