In this video you are going to break out some functionality currently in server G-S into a separate
file.
And we're also going to set up our test suite so we can verify that those utility functions are working
as expected.
For the moment our goal is going to be to create a function that helps us generate this object instead
of having to define the object every single time.
We'll simply pass in two arguments to a function the name and the text it'll generate the object.
So we will have to do that work down below.
Now to get this done we are going to make a separate file that we load into server japes with a method
we call instead of defining the object inside of the server folder.
We're going to make a new directory called utils and inside of utils we're going to make a file called
Message dot.
J.S. this is going to store our utility functions related to messaging and in our case we're going to
make a new one called generate message.
Let's make a variable called generate message.
This is going to be a function and it's going to take those two arguments I talked about earlier from
end text it's then going to return an object just like the objects we pass in as the second argument
to emit.
Now we'll do this together and your challenge will be the testing side of things.
For now all we need to do is return an object specifying from as the From argument up above text as
the text argument up above.
And to create it at.
And that is going to get generated by calling a new date and calling it's got time method.
With this in place our utility function is now done all we need to do is export it down below.
Module exports.
We're going to set that equal to an object that has a generate message property equal to the generate
message variable defined above.
We'll eventually be able to integrate this into server Dom.
J.S. But before we do let's go ahead and write some test cases to make sure it works as expected.
This means we are going to need to install Moka And we're also going to need to install the expect assertion
library then we'll set up our package that Jason scripts then we can write the test case first up inside
of the terminal.
We are going to install using NPM install two modules we need expect which is our assertion library.
At one point twenty point two.
And we're also going to install Moka to run our test suite at Version 3 point zero point two and we're
going to use the save death flag to add these as development dependencies.
Let's go ahead and run this command and once it's done we can move into packaged up Jason and set up
those test scripts.
They're going to be identical to the ones we used in the last project inside a package.
Jason we now have two dev dependencies and inside of scripts we can get started by removing the old
test script.
And we're going to add those two scripts test and test.
Watch.
Let's go ahead and fill out the basics first test.
Set that equal to an empty string for the moment and test high and watch the test watch script as we
know simply calls gnomon calling the NPM test script gnomon hyphen hyphen the X is C then inside single
quotes NPM test that is going to get the job done.
Now when we run gnomon here we're actually running the globally installed gnomon.
We can also install it locally to fix that to get that done.
We're going to do is run NPM install node mohn.
We're going to add the most recent version which is version one point ten point two and we are going
to use the save dead flag to install it.
Now when we install node like this our application no longer relies on that global node Mohn installation.
So if someone else grabs this from get hub they're going to be able to get started without needing to
install anything globally.
Next up is that test script the test script first has to set up those environment variables that were
going to be configuring.
We'll do that later.
For now we're going to do is run Moka passing in the pattern for the files we want to test the files
we want to test are in that server directory.
They could be in any subdirectory.
So we'll use star star and the files regardless of their name are going to end in test dot J.
S And with this in place we are done.
We can now run our test suite over in the terminal.
If I run NPM test all we're going to see is that we have 0 tests in place.
Here we have the server test file.
Globbing pattern it could not resolve any files.
We can fix this issue by simply adding a test file.
I'm going to add a test file for the message utility message test.
J.S..
Now we can go ahead and rerun the NPM test command this time around.
It does indeed find a file and we see we have zero passing tests which is a great starting point inside
of here.
We're going to need to add a test for the message function.
We just defined.
Now this test is going to verify that the object we get back is what we would expect given the parameters
we passed in we'll set up the basic structure of the test file together and you're going to write the
individual test case.
First up we need to load and expect no way to get around that var expect equals require expect.
This is going to let us make our assertions about the return value from our generate message function.
The next thing we're going to do is add a describe block here we're going to add a describe block for
the function generate message and inside of the callback function we'll have all of the test cases for
that function.
And before we can actually create a test case and fill it out we do need to load in the module or testing.
I'm going to make a variable and using yes 60 structuring.
We're going to pull off.
Generate message generate message and then we can go ahead and require it using require specifying the
local path dot forward slash message.
It's in the same directory as the test file where we currently are.
So there's no reason to do any directory moving with this in place.
We can now add to the individual test case.
It should generate the correct message object and your job is going to be to write the test case this
is going to be a synchronous test.
So there is no need to provide done.
All you need to do is call generate message with two values a from value and a text value.
You're going to get the response back store response in variable then you're going to make some assertions
about the response.
First up assert that firm is correct.
Assert from matches the value you passed in you're also going to assert that the text matches up.
And lastly you're going to assert that the created value is a number.
It doesn't matter what number it is you're going to use the to be a method to check the type assert
create it at is number once you have all of that done you should be able to rerun the test script over
inside of the terminal and you should say you have one test and it is indeed passing.
Now but there's a little open ended because we have tested quite a few things in the past.
Feel free to refer to any other videos or any other code you wrote for this course to get this challenge
done.
So once again call the function grab its return value and assert things about that value.
Pause the video and when you're done click play it all right to get this done.
The first thing I'm going to do is define some variables.
It's fine if you win about things a different way.
As long as you got the assertions working correctly to get started I'm going to make a from a variable
to store the from value.
I'll go ahead and use gen I'm also going to make a text variable to store the text value some message.
Now what I want to do is make my final variable which is going to store the response the message that
comes back from the generate message function which is exactly what I'm going to call right here.
I'm going to call generate message passing in the two necessary arguments.
The From argument end of the text argument I have that right here from comma text.
Next up and the final thing we need to do is make assertions about this object that comes back.
I am going to expect that message dot created at is a number using to be a.
And passing in the type number.
This was the first assertion you needed to make to verify the property is correct.
Next up we're going to expect that message has certain properties inside of it.
We're going to do this using the to include assertion though you could have created two separate statements
one for message dot from and a separate one for message dot text.
All of those are valid solutions.
I'm just going to happen to use to include and we're going to specify some things that message should
include first up it should have a from property equal to the from a variable up above.
We can go ahead and use yes six to define that.
And the same thing is going to happen for text text should equal text.
And we're going to use yes 6 to set that up.
We can even simplify this further from comma text.
Excellent.
Would this in place are test cases now done and we can go ahead and remove these commented out lines.
And the final thing you needed to do was run the test suite from the terminal by running NPM test.
When we do it what do we get we get our one test under generate message should generate correct message
object and it is indeed passing which is fantastic.
Now that we have some tests verifying our function works as expected.
Let's go ahead and integrate it into our application by moving into server J S and replacing all of
the objects we pass to the emet function with calls to our new function.
The first step in this process is going to be to inport the function we just created.
I'm going to do that up above by creating a constant will you.
Yes 60 structuring to grab a generate message and we're going to grab it off of a call to require now
or requiring a local file in a different directory.
We're going to start with.
Forward slash.
We're going to go into the utility directory since we're currently in the server directory.
Then we can grab the file message by specifying it right here.
Now we have access to generate message and instead of creating these objects we can call generate message
right here.
We're going to replace Welcome to the chat app and the admin variables with arguments generate a message
from admin and the tax is going to be a welcome to the chat app we have the exact same functionality
but now we're using a function to generate that object for us which is going to make scaling that out
a lot easier.
It's also going to make updating what is inside of a message much easier as well.
Next up we can change the one we have down below for new user joined.
We're going to go ahead and replace this with a call to generate messages.
Well once again this one's from the admin.
So the first argument will be the string admin.
The second argument is the text new user joined.
Excellent.
This one is done too and the final one is the one that actually gets sent to the user from a user which
means we have message data from a message text.
Those are going to be our arguments.
We're going to call generate message with those two message doctor from.
And as the second argument.
Message dot text.
And with this in place we are done.
The last thing left to do for this video is test that this is working as expected.
I'm going to start up the server using gnomon without a space between node and my own server forwards
Siavash server.
J.S. once the server is up we can go ahead and test things out by opening up a couple of tabs with the
developer tools open for the first tab.
Going to visit local host 3000 inside of the council we should see our new message printing.
The object looks the same even though it's now generated by the function and we can test that everything
else is working as expected to by opening up a second tab and opening up its developer tools.
And this time around the first tab should see a new message.
Here we have a new user joined.
That's still working.
And if we emit a custom message from this second tab it should show up in the first.
I'm going to use the up arrow key to run one of our previous create message event emitters.
I'm going to fire off the function and if I go to the first tab We do indeed get the message which is
fantastic.
This should work print's in the first tab and also Prince in the second sense we're calling IO data
as opposed to the broadcast method.
Now that everything is working we are done we can make a commit and wrap this one up.
I'm going to call get status from the terminal.
Here we have new files as well as modified ones which means we're going to want to call get ad dot.
Next up we can call get commit with a message flag create generate message utility.
Excellent.
I'm going to push this up to get hub and that is it for this one.
Then the next one we're going to take a look at socket I O acknowledgements which are fantastic It's
coming up next so stay tuned.
I'll see you then.