In this video you're going to learn how to use event acknowledgements.
They are a fantastic feature inside of socket.
I know in order to illustrate exactly what they are and why you'd ever want to use them we're going
to quickly run through the slides for the chat app.
These are the two events that we actually have in our application if you remember the first one is the
new message event.
It gets emitted by the server and it gets listened to by the client it sends across the from text and
created out properties all of which are required to render the message to the screen.
Now the event that we're going to be updating is the create message event.
This one gets emitted by the client and listened to by the server.
Once again we are sending some data across from and text.
Now the problem with our create message event is that the data flows in one direction.
The data comes from a form inside of the browser.
It then gets sent over to the server and the server is kind of stuck.
Sure the data might be valid the From and text fields might be correctly set up and that case we can
emit a new message event rendering it to every browser who's connected to the server.
But if the server receives invalid data it has no way to let the client know that something went wrong.
What we need is a way to acknowledge we got a request and have the option to send some data back.
In this case we're going to added acknowledgment for create message if the client emits a valid request
with valid from and text properties.
We're going to acknowledge that sending back no error message if the data sent from client to server
is invalid.
We're going to acknowledge it's sending back the errors so the client knows exactly what it needs to
do to send a valid request.
Now the result is going to look a little bit like this.
And the data flow from server to client is going to be done via a callback.
Your knowledge could be anything you like.
In our case it could be was the message data valid.
If you're creating an email application you might only send the acknowledgment back to the client when
the email was successfully sent.
You don't need to send data which is what we're going to do when valid data is sent across the pipeline
we're simply going to say hey we got that message.
Everything's got to go and the client can respond to that.
Now that we've gone through this let's go ahead and implemented into our application setting up acknowledgements
really isn't that bad if you already have a listener in place.
All you have to do is make a quick change to the listener and a quick change to the emitter and everything
will work as expected.
Now in this case the listener happens to be on the server and the emitter is going to be on the client
but acknowledgements also work in the other direction.
I can emit and event from the server and I can acknowledge it from the client in order to set this up
we are going to emit a create message event over inside of index.
Yes.
Using socket dowdy.
And we're going to pass in the same arguments we would otherwise.
The first one is the event name.
Create message and we're going to pass in some valid data in object with those two properties.
We can set from equal to something like Frank and we can set a text property equal to something like
high.
Now with this in place we have a standard event emitter and a standard event listener.
I can go ahead and start up the app using gnomon and we can make sure everything's working as expected.
Gnomon server server.
Yes.
Once the server is up we can visit it in the browser.
I'm going to open up the developer tools as well.
Then we're going to go to localhost three thousand
and you can see over inside of the terminal we have create message showing up.
And we also have new message showing up here.
We have the new message for our little Welcome to the chat app greeting.
And we have the new message from Frank which we admitted now the goal here is to send an acknowledgement
from the server back to the client that we got the data in order to get this done and we have to make
a change to both the listener and the emitter.
If you only make a change to one it is not going to work as expected.
We're going to start with the event emitter.
We want a way to run some code when the acknowledgement has been sent from the server back to the client
in order to get that done.
We're going to add a third argument which is going to be a callback function.
This function is going to fire when the acknowledgment arrives at the client and we can do anything
we like.
For now we'll just print using console that log.
Got it.
Now this is all we need to do.
Bare bones style to add an acknowledgment to the client on the server it's also pretty simple.
We're going to add a second argument to our callback argument list the first one is still going to be
the data that was emitted.
The second one though is going to be a function that we're going to refer to as callback and we can
call it anywhere down below to acknowledge that we got that request when we call this function like
we're going to call it right here it is in turn going to send an event back to the front end.
And it is going to call the function as we have it here.
This means that if I save both files we can play around with acknowledgements over in the browser.
I'm going to refresh the app.
And what do we get we get.
Got it.
That means our data successfully went to the server.
We can prove that by seeing the console log statement here.
The server acknowledged it got the data by calling callback.
And right here.
Got it prints.
Now acknowledgements are pretty useful but they're even more useful when you send data back if the data
for the message is invalid.
For example we're probably going to want to send some errors back something we will be doing a little
later.
For now though we can play around with an acknowledgment by sending anything we want back.
We send data back by providing one argument to callback.
If you want to add multiple things simply specify an object.
Adding as many properties as you like.
In our case though we can send as the only argument to call back a string.
I'm going to set my string too.
This is from the server.
This string is going to be passed into the callback and it's going to end up inside of our callback
right here which means I can create a variable for that value we can call it data or anything else you
like and we can print it to the screen or do something with it.
For now we're just going to print it to the screen.
If I save index dot J.S. we can test that.
Everything is working as expected.
I'm going to go ahead and give the app a refresh and what do we see we see.
Got it.
Meaning we got the acknowledgement and we see the data the data that was sent from the server to the
client acknowledgements play an important role in realtime applications.
Let's go back to that e-mail app example for a second imagine I type in some values like a to value
and a text value when I send the e-mail.
I want to get an acknowledgment back that either A the email sent successfully or B the e-mail did not
send successfully in which case I want to know why.
Maybe it was a form error where I can show some error messages to the user or maybe the server was down
for maintenance or something like that.
Either way acknowledgements allow the request listener to send something back to the request emitter.
Now that we know how to use acknowledgements we're going to integrate them into our application that
is coming up in the next video as we add an actual form field to our index.
H file where users can submit new messages and view them.
It's all coming up next.
Stay tuned.
I will see you then.