In this video you're going to add a form field to your index.
HCM el file this is going to render an input field and a button to the screen and a user is going to
be able to interact with that as opposed to having to call socket dot emit from the developer tools
which is not a sustainable option for real users.
This only works for us developers.
Now in order to get started we're going to be editing index dot HTL and then we're going to move into
index dot J.S..
We're going to add a listener that's going to wait for the form to be submitted.
And inside of that listener call back we are going to fire socket Dummett with the data typed in the
field.
We're also going to take a moment to render all incoming messages to the screen at the end of this video
will have a ugly yet working chat application.
Now before we do any of that we are going to be using a library called the Jay Querrey to do DOM manipulation
which means that we want to be able to do stuff with our rendered DML but we want to be able to do that
from our javascript file.
We're going to use Jey query to make that a lot easier in terms of cross browser compatibility to grab
this library we're going to head over to Google Chrome go to Jay Querrey dot com and you can grab the
most recent version.
The version is not going to matter for here.
We're using very basic features available in all versions.
I'm grabbing the most recent version.
Three point one.
Point zero.
Then I'm going to go ahead and download decompressed production version.
Am I right clicking and opening it in a new tab.
Here we have the actual javascript that we want to load in to our application which means we can Right-Click
some sort of empty area.
Save As and go into our projects folder desktop node A Chat App public J.S. and inside of japes I'm
going to create a new directory called libs where we'll store third party javascript.
We're going to be working with a few more client side javascript libraries throughout the section so
it's nice to create a folder to stay organized.
I'm going to save that in there.
Close the tab as well as the downloads area.
And now we can go ahead and load it into index dot h DML and at our forum down here just between socket
I O an index Scott J.S. we're going to add a new script tag to load and Jay Querrey we've got to specify
that source attribute with the path to the file forward slash J.S. forward slash libs followed by a
forward slash and the file name Jay Querrey hyphen three point one point zero dot men dot J.
S awesome.
And now let's go ahead and set up our form at TAG this is going to render our form fields to the browser.
If you're not familiar with these tags that is perfectly fine simply follow along and I'll explain as
we go.
First up we need a form tag.
This creates a form that submittal by the user.
This is exactly what we're going to use to submit our messages.
And on this form tag we're going to add one attribute.
It's the ID attribute which lets us give this element a unique identifier making it really easy to target
without javascript.
A bit later on remember we're going to want to add a listener to this element when the form gets submitted.
We're going to want to do something in our javascript file notably but we're going to want to do is
call Sacket dot emit.
I'm going to set id equal to inside of quotes message hyphen form.
Now that we have a form tag complete we can add some tags inside of it to get started we're going to
add a button which is going to appear at the bottom of the form.
This button on click is going to submit the form on opening and closing my tag and just inside I can
type whatever text I want to appear on the button.
I'm going to go with send now that we have our button in place.
The only thing we need to do is add the little text field.
This is going to be the text field where the user types their message.
This is going to require us to use an input tag and instead of opening and closing an input tag like
this we're going to use the self-closing syntax because we don't need to actually put anything inside
of it like we do for a button here or like we do for form.
Here we are going to be adding quite a few attributes on input.
First step name we want to give this field a unique name something like.
Message is going to get the job done.
We also want to go ahead and set the type.
There's a lot of different types for input tags types could include something like a checkbox or in
our case the type we're going to use inside of quotes is text or the last attribute we're going to add
to input is called placeholder.
We're going to set this value equal to inside of quotes a string.
This string is going to get rendered in the field in a light grey before the user actually enters a
value.
I'm going to tell the user that this is where a message goes with this in place.
We can actually test out our forms rendering by starting up the server using gnomon server forward slash
server.
J.S. and going to local host 3000.
The server is up.
I'm going to visit Google Chrome go to localhost three thousand and you'll notice something kind of
cool.
I haven't actually visited that al yet but you can see that the connection has already occurred.
Chrome does some lazy loading if it thinks you're going to go to a u r l.
It's actually going to make the request.
So when I do visit it it loads even faster.
Now if I visit localhost three thousand What do we get.
We get our little form.
We can type in a message like test and we can send it off now by default.
Forms are very old school.
If I try to submit this form it's actually going to go through a full page refresh then it's going to
add to the data like our message text as a query string you are l.
This is not what we want to do.
We want to run some custom javascript on forms submit.
So we're going to attach a custom event listener and override the default behavior to get that done
we are going to have to use J query and we're going to need to select this form field before we dive
into index Dot.
Yes let's take a quick moment to talk about how we can use Jey query to select elements J query which
is accessible via the J query variable with an uppercase.
Q takes as its argument your selector right here we're going to add a string and we can select our elements.
For example if we want to select all the paragraph tags on the screen we would type P in here.
These are really similar to CSSA selectors if you're familiar with them and right here we've selected
our paragraph tag.
I could also go ahead and select all of the divs inside of my program or I could select elements by
ID or class.
And that's what we're going to do in order to select an element by ID.
We first start with the pound sign and then we type the name and our case we have a form called Message
hyphen form.
And if I fire this off we do indeed get that back.
This is going to allow us to add an event listener over inside of index.
Yes we're going to add that exact same selector near the bottom Jay query calling it with our selector
pound sign message hyphen form and now we're going to add an event listener and the event listener is
going to look pretty similar to our socket I O event listeners we are going to be calling on and we
are going to be providing those two arguments the event name inside of quotes submit and a function.
This function is going to fire when a user tries to submit the form.
Now unlike our socket I O event listeners we are going to get one argument right here.
The event argument and we are going to need to access this.
We're going to need to access this event argument in order to override that default behavior that causes
that page refresh right here.
We're going to call the DOT prevent default prevent default prevents the default behavior for the event
and by default a submitter that goes through that page refresh process.
We can go ahead and test that everything is working by going into Google Chrome giving the page a refresh
also going to remove the query string from the U r l.
Now we can type in some sort of message like test.
Hit send and you can see that nothing happens nothing happens because we overrode the default behavior.
All we need to do to make something happen is call socket dot emit.
We're going to emit the create message event right here.
Create message and we're going to go ahead and provide our data.
Now the name from field for now is just going to be user in upper case.
We're going to leave this as anonymous for the moment although we will be updating that a bit later
in the section.
Now the textfield this is going to come from the form we're going to want to add a selector and we're
going to want to get the value back.
Let's go ahead and do that using Jay Querrey.
We're going to call Jay Coria once again and we're going to select this input right here.
We can go ahead and selected by its name name equals message in order to get that done.
We're going to open up brackets like this setting name equal to message.
This is going to select any element that has a name attribute equal to a message which is just our one
and we can go ahead and get its value using the dot Vau method.
No semi-colon required since we're inside of object creation.
With this in place we can now go ahead and add our callback function for our knowledge amn't for the
moment it doesn't really do anything but that's perfectly fine.
We have to add it in order to fulfill the acknowledgment setup we currently have in place now that we
have our event listener set up.
Let's go ahead and test this out.
I'm going to head back into Krumm give the page a refresh type in some message like this should work.
And when we submit the form we should see it show up over here as a new message.
I'm going to send it off and you can see that right inside of the terminal we have a user sending this
should work.
And it also shows up right here the same thing is true if I open up a second connection I'm going to
open up the developer tools so he can see exactly what's happening behind the scenes.
I'm going to type some message like from tab to send it off.
And we should see it over in tab 1 and we do.
Perfect.
Everything is working as expected.
Now obviously the set is not complete.
We want to wipe that form value after we send the message and we want to take care of a few other you
I related things.
But for now it is working pretty well.
With a basic form in place the second thing we're going to do is render incoming messages to the screen.
Now once again it is going to look pretty ugly but it will get the job done to get this done.
We have to create a place inside of our Dom inside of our index.
H Tim L file where we can render the messages.
Once again we're going to give this element a idea that we can easily access over inside of index just
so we can render those messages.
First up what we're going to do is create a ordered list by creating an AOL tag just like this.
This list is going to let us add items to it and those items are going to be the individual messages.
Now we are going to be giving this an id attribute.
I'm going to call the I.D. in this case messages awesome.
Now this is all we need to do in indexed out HDMI.
All of the heavy lifting is going to happen over inside of index.
Yes.
When a new message comes in we want to add something inside of the ordered list so that gets rendered
to the screen over inside of index Dhananjay.
Yes we can get this done by modifying our callback function when a new message arrives.
The first thing we're going to do is create a list item and we're going to do this once again using
Jay Querrey.
We're going to make a variable.
This variable is going to be called out I and we're going to go ahead and use Jay query slightly differently
rather than using Jay Querrey to select an element we're going to use Jay Querrey to create an element
and then we can modify that element and add it into the markup making it visible right here inside of
quotes.
We're going to open and close an ally tag just like we would inside of index dot H.T. amount.
Now that we have this in place we have to go ad in its text property.
I'm going to set ally dot text by calling ally dot text with de-value.
I want to use in this case the text is going to require us to set up a little template string inside
of the template string.
We are going to go ahead and use the data that comes back.
For now we're going to use the frim attribute and the text attribute.
Let's get started with who it's from.
Then we'll add a little colon and a space to separate that from the actual message.
And finally it will inject message text at the end.
Now at this point we've created an element but we haven't rendered it to the DOM.
What we're going to do is use a query to select that brand new element we created.
We gave it an idea of messages and we're going to append something to it by calling the append method.
This is going to add it as its last child.
So there's already three items in the list.
The newest one will show up below those three as the fourth item in our ordered list.
Oh we have to do is call append as a function passing in our list item.
And with this in place we are done.
Now if you're not familiar with J queries this can be a bit overwhelming but I promise the techniques
we use here will be using throughout the course by the end you'll be much more comfortable selecting
and creating elements.
Let's go ahead and test things out over inside of Google Chrome.
I'm going to refresh tab 1 and when I do you can see from is not defined over in the right hand side.
If I go back into Adam this is most likely just a really small typo and you can see that is the case.
Message from is defined which means I can save the file and give things a refresh simple errors like
this can easily be checked down using the developer tools.
They actually give you some pretty great error information as well as an entire call stack on the right
hand side.
You can usually click this little link.
This is going to bring you to the sources tab but it's going to show you exactly where the error occurred.
Here you can see not only the line the error occurred but the actual indentation into the line the error
occurred right here.
This is really fantastic it makes the bugging much easier if you run into an error inside of the console.
You can usually get more information by either expanding it or going right to the source of the problem.
Now that we've fixed that error and we give the app a refresh we do see are two messages.
Welcome to the chat app shows up.
And Frank says hi.
Now welcome to the chat app.
Should Show Up the Frank Hyde message is coming from right here inside an index Dot.
Yes we can actually go ahead and remove that we no longer need to automatically emit messages since
we have a form set up to get that done for us.
Once again we can save the file refresh the browser and this time around we have a nice little setup.
Welcome to the chat app.
I'm going to do the same thing for our second tab this time around we get Welcome to the chat app.
And in the first how we get new user joined this is fantastic.
Now the true test is going to be to send a message from one tab to the other.
This should go to tab two.
I'm going to send this off and when I click this button it's going to emit the event that's going to
go to the server and the server is going to send it to everyone connected.
Right here I can see this should go to tab two renders and over inside of my second tab we get the message
as well.
I can come here and respond.
And when I respond it shows up in both tabs.
Now we're not quite done with the UI or the actual user experience.
Custom names and time stamps are coming up but we do have a fantastic start.
We now have a form where we can submit messages and we can see all of the incoming messages inside of
the browser which means we didn't need to do anything in the developer tools anymore.
In terms of a meeting or reading our messages that is it for this one let's go ahead and wrap things
up by making a commit now that we have some working changes.
I'm going to shut down the server.
Clear the output and run it get status so he can double check all of our changes.
Everything looks good here.
I'm going to use.
Get add to add all of the files including my untracked.
Jay Querrey file to the repo then I can use.
Get commit to make the commit.
I'm going to use the flag here and a good message for this one would be add form for messages and show
incoming messages in browser once we have this in place we can go ahead and push this up to get how
but I am going to take a moment to deploy the Heroku now that we have something real visible and tangible
to use get push Heroku master is going to get that done.
Once this is up we'll be able to visit it in the browser as you can see over inside of my council socket
I O is trying to reconnect to the server.
Unfortunately we're not going to be bringing it back up so it's going to try a little longer.
Here we are we're verifying the deploy and everything is up and running.
You can either on Heroku open or copy this.
You are out directly I'm going to go ahead and close my two localhost tabs and open up the actual Heroku
app right here.
We do get our Welcome to the chat app message.
And we do get our form everything looks good so far.
I'm going to go ahead and open up a different browser like Safari going to go to the chat app as well.
And we're going to bring these windows side by side over inside a safari.
I'm going to type a little message.
This is live on Heroku.
Click send or hit the enter key and instantly it shows up in the other browser in the other tab.
This is because our lives socket server is transmitting this data.
This could happen between any computer in the world you do not need to be on my machine since we're
using a real Heroku you are.
Now that everything's working on Heroku we are done.
I will see you next time